Genesis

1 In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.

2 Now the earth proved to be formless and waste and there was darkness upon the surface of the watery deep; and God’s active force was moving to and fro over the surface of the waters.

3 And God proceeded to say: “Let light come to be.” Then there came to be light. 4 After that God saw that the light was good, and God brought about a division between the light and the darkness. 5 And God began calling the light Day, but the darkness he called Night. And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a first day.

6 And God went on to say: “Let an expanse come to be in between the waters and let a dividing occur between the waters and the waters.” 7 Then God proceeded to make the expanse and to make a division between the waters that should be beneath the expanse and the waters that should be above the expanse. And it came to be so. 8 And God began to call the expanse Heaven. And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a second day.

9 And God went on to say: “Let the waters under the heavens be brought together into one place and let the dry land appear.” And it came to be so. 10 And God began calling the dry land Earth, but the bringing together of the waters he called Seas. Further, God saw that it was good. 11 And God went on to say: “Let the earth cause grass to shoot forth, vegetation bearing seed, fruit trees yielding fruit according to their kinds, the seed of which is in it, upon the earth.” And it came to be so. 12 And the earth began to put forth grass, vegetation bearing seed according to its kind and trees yielding fruit, the seed of which is in it according to its kind. Then God saw that it was good. 13 And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a third day.

14 And God went on to say: “Let luminaries come to be in the expanse of the heavens to make a division between the day and the night; and they must serve as signs and for seasons and for days and years. 15 And they must serve as luminaries in the expanse of the heavens to shine upon the earth.” And it came to be so. 16 And God proceeded to make the two great luminaries, the greater luminary for dominating the day and the lesser luminary for dominating the night, and also the stars. 17 Thus God put them in the expanse of the heavens to shine upon the earth, 18 and to dominate by day and by night and to make a division between the light and the darkness. Then God saw that it was good. 19 And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a fourth day.

20 And God went on to say: “Let the waters swarm forth a swarm of living souls and let flying creatures fly over the earth upon the face of the expanse of the heavens.” 21 And God proceeded to create the great sea monsters and every living soul that moves about, which the waters swarmed forth according to their kinds, and every winged flying creature according to its kind. And God got to see that it was good. 22 With that God blessed them, saying: “Be fruitful and become many and fill the waters in the sea basins, and let the flying creatures become many in the earth.” 23 And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a fifth day.

24 And God went on to say: “Let the earth put forth living souls according to their kinds, domestic animal and moving animal and wild beast of the earth according to its kind.” And it came to be so. 25 And God proceeded to make the wild beast of the earth according to its kind and the domestic animal according to its kind and every moving animal of the ground according to its kind. And God got to see that it was good.

26 And God went on to say: “Let us make man in our image, according to our likeness, and let them have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and the domestic animals and all the earth and every moving animal that is moving upon the earth.” 27 And God proceeded to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them. 28 Further, God blessed them and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many and fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving upon the earth.”

29 And God went on to say: “Here I have given to YOU all vegetation bearing seed which is on the surface of the whole earth and every tree on which there is the fruit of a tree bearing seed. To YOU let it serve as food. 30 And to every wild beast of the earth and to every flying creature of the heavens and to everything moving upon the earth in which there is life as a soul I have given all green vegetation for food.” And it came to be so.

31 After that God saw everything he had made and, look! it was very good. And there came to be evening and there came to be morning, a sixth day.

Genesis

6 Now it came about that when men started to grow in numbers on the surface of the ground and daughters were born to them, 2 then the sons of the true God began to notice the daughters of men, that they were good-looking; and they went taking wives for themselves, namely, all whom they chose. 3 After that Jehovah said: “My spirit shall not act toward man indefinitely in that he is also flesh. Accordingly his days shall amount to a hundred and twenty years.”

4 The Neph′i·lim proved to be in the earth in those days, and also after that, when the sons of the true God continued to have relations with the daughters of men and they bore sons to them, they were the mighty ones who were of old, the men of fame.

5 Consequently Jehovah saw that the badness of man was abundant in the earth and every inclination of the thoughts of his heart was only bad all the time. 6 And Jehovah felt regrets that he had made men in the earth, and he felt hurt at his heart. 7 So Jehovah said: “I am going to wipe men whom I have created off the surface of the ground, from man to domestic animal, to moving animal and to flying creature of the heavens, because I do regret that I have made them.” 8 But Noah found favor in the eyes of Jehovah.

9 This is the history of Noah.

Noah was a righteous man. He proved himself faultless among his contemporaries. Noah walked with the true God. 10 In time Noah became father to three sons, Shem, Ham and Ja′pheth. 11 And the earth came to be ruined in the sight of the true God and the earth became filled with violence. 12 So God saw the earth and, look! it was ruined, because all flesh had ruined its way on the earth.

13 After that God said to Noah: “The end of all flesh has come before me, because the earth is full of violence as a result of them; and here I am bringing them to ruin together with the earth. 14 Make for yourself an ark out of wood of a resinous tree. You will make compartments in the ark, and you must cover it inside and outside with tar. 15 And this is how you will make it: three hundred cubits the length of the ark, fifty cubits its width, and thirty cubits its height. 16 You will make a tso′har [roof; or, window] for the ark, and you will complete it to the extent of a cubit upward, and the entrance of the ark you will put in its side; you will make it with a lower story, a second story and a third story.

17 “And as for me, here I am bringing the deluge of waters upon the earth to bring to ruin all flesh in which the force of life is active from under the heavens. Everything that is in the earth will expire. 18 And I do establish my covenant with you; and you must go into the ark, you and your sons and your wife and your sons’ wives with you. 19 And of every living creature of every sort of flesh, two of each, you will bring into the ark to preserve them alive with you. Male and female they will be. 20 Of the flying creatures according to their kinds and of the domestic animals according to their kinds, of all moving animals of the ground according to their kinds, two of each will go in there to you to preserve them alive. 21 And as for you, take for yourself every sort of food that is eaten; and you must gather it to yourself, and it must serve as food for you and for them.”

22 And Noah proceeded to do according to all that God had commanded him. He did just so.

Genesis

7 After that Jehovah said to Noah: “Go, you and all your household, into the ark, because you are the one I have seen to be righteous before me among this generation. 2 Of every clean beast you must take to yourself by sevens, the sire and its mate; and of every beast that is not clean just two, the sire and its mate; 3 also of the flying creatures of the heavens by sevens, male and female, to preserve offspring alive on the surface of the entire earth. 4 For in just seven days more I am making it rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and I will wipe every existing thing that I have made off the surface of the ground.” 5 And Noah proceeded to do according to all that Jehovah had commanded him.

6 And Noah was six hundred years old when the deluge of waters occurred on the earth. 7 So Noah went in, and his sons and his wife and his sons’ wives with him, into the ark ahead of the waters of the deluge. 8 Of every clean beast and of every beast that is not clean and of the flying creatures and everything that moves on the ground, 9 they went in by twos to Noah inside the ark, male and female, just as God had commanded Noah. 10 And seven days later it turned out that the waters of the deluge came upon the earth.

11 In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life, in the second month, on the seventeenth day of the month, on this day all the springs of the vast watery deep were broken open and the floodgates of the heavens were opened. 12 And the downpour upon the earth went on for forty days and forty nights. 13 On this very day Noah went in, and Shem and Ham and Ja′pheth, Noah’s sons, and the wife of Noah and the three wives of his sons with him, into the ark; 14 they and every wild beast according to its kind, and every domestic animal according to its kind, and every moving animal that moves on the earth according to its kind, and every flying creature according to its kind, every bird, every winged creature. 15 And they kept going to Noah inside the ark, two by two, of every sort of flesh in which the force of life was active. 16 And those going in, male and female of every sort of flesh, went in, just as God had commanded him. After that Jehovah shut the door behind him.

17 And the deluge went on for forty days upon the earth, and the waters kept increasing and began carrying the ark and it was floating high above the earth. 18 And the waters became overwhelming and kept increasing greatly upon the earth, but the ark kept going on the surface of the waters. 19 And the waters overwhelmed the earth so greatly that all the tall mountains that were under the whole heavens came to be covered. 20 Up to fifteen cubits the waters overwhelmed them and the mountains became covered.

21 So all flesh that was moving upon the earth expired, among the flying creatures and among the domestic animals and among the wild beasts and among all the swarms that were swarming upon the earth, and all mankind. 22 Everything in which the breath of the force of life was active in its nostrils, namely, all that were on the dry ground, died. 23 Thus he wiped out every existing thing that was on the surface of the ground, from man to beast, to moving animal and to flying creature of the heavens, and they were wiped off the earth; and only Noah and those who were with him in the ark kept on surviving. 24 And the waters continued overwhelming the earth a hundred and fifty days.

Genesis

8 After that God remembered Noah and every wild beast and every domestic animal that was with him in the ark, and God caused a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters began to subside. 2 And the springs of the watery deep and the floodgates of the heavens became stopped up, and so the downpour from the heavens was restrained. 3 And the waters began receding from off the earth, progressively receding; and at the end of a hundred and fifty days the waters were lacking. 4 And in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, the ark came to rest on the mountains of Ar′a·rat. 5 And the waters kept on progressively lessening until the tenth month. In the tenth month, on the first of the month, the tops of the mountains appeared.

6 So it occurred that at the end of forty days Noah proceeded to open the window of the ark that he had made. 7 After that he sent out a raven, and it continued flying outdoors, going and returning, until the waters dried off the earth.

8 Later he sent out from him a dove to see whether the waters had abated from the surface of the ground. 9 And the dove did not find any resting-place for the sole of its foot, and so it returned to him into the ark because the waters were yet upon the surface of the whole earth. At that he put his hand out and took it and brought it to himself inside the ark. 10 And he went on waiting still another seven days, and once again he sent out the dove from the ark. 11 Later on the dove came to him about the time of evening and, look! there was an olive leaf freshly plucked in its bill, and so Noah got to know that the waters had abated from the earth. 12 And he went on waiting still another seven days. Then he sent out the dove, but it did not come back again to him anymore.

13 Now in the six hundred and first year, in the first month, on the first day of the month, it came about that the waters had drained from off the earth; and Noah proceeded to remove the covering of the ark and to look, and here the surface of the ground had drained dry. 14 And in the second month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, the earth had dried off.

15 God now spoke to Noah, saying: 16 “Go out of the ark, you and your wife and your sons and your sons’ wives with you. 17 Every living creature that is with you of every sort of flesh, among the flying creatures and among the beasts and among all the moving animals that move upon the earth, bring out with you, as they must swarm in the earth and be fruitful and become many upon the earth.”

18 At that Noah went out, and also his sons and his wife and his sons’ wives with him. 19 Every living creature, every moving animal and every flying creature, everything that moves on the earth, according to their families they went out of the ark. 20 And Noah began to build an altar to Jehovah and to take some of all the clean beasts and of all the clean flying creatures and to offer burnt offerings upon the altar. 21 And Jehovah began to smell a restful odor, and so Jehovah said in his heart: “Never again shall I call down evil upon the ground on man’s account, because the inclination of the heart of man is bad from his youth up; and never again shall I deal every living thing a blow just as I have done. 22 For all the days the earth continues, seed sowing and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night, will never cease.”

Genesis

49 Later on Jacob called his sons and said: “Gather yourselves together that I may tell YOU what will happen to YOU in the final part of the days. 2 Assemble yourselves and listen, YOU sons of Jacob, yes, listen to Israel YOUR father.

3 “Reu′ben, you are my firstborn, my vigor and the beginning of my generative power, the excellence of dignity and the excellence of strength. 4 With reckless license like waters, do not you excel, because you have gone up to your father’s bed. At that time you profaned my lounge. He went up to it!

5 “Sim′e·on and Le′vi are brothers. Instruments of violence are their slaughter weapons. 6 Into their intimate group do not come, O my soul. With their congregation do not become united, O my disposition, because in their anger they killed men, and in their arbitrariness they hamstrung bulls. 7 Cursed be their anger, because it is cruel, and their fury, because it acts harshly. Let me parcel them out in Jacob and let me scatter them in Israel.

8 “As for you, Judah, your brothers will laud you. Your hand will be on the back of the neck of your enemies. The sons of your father will prostrate themselves to you. 9 A lion cub Judah is. From the prey, my son, you will certainly go up. He bowed down, he stretched himself out like a lion and, like a lion, who dares rouse him? 10 The scepter will not turn aside from Judah, neither the commander’s staff from between his feet, until Shi′loh comes; and to him the obedience of the peoples will belong. 11 Tying his full-grown ass to a vine and the descendant of his own she-ass to a choice vine, he will certainly wash his clothing in wine and his garment in the blood of grapes. 12 Dark red are his eyes from wine, and the whiteness of his teeth is from milk.

13 “Zeb′u·lun will reside by the seashore, and he will be by the shore where the ships lie anchored; and his remote side will be toward Si′don.

14 “Is′sa·char is a strong-boned ass, lying down between the two saddlebags. 15 And he will see that the resting-place is good and that the land is pleasant; and he will bend down his shoulder to bear burdens and he will become subject to slavish forced labor.

16 “Dan will judge his people as one of the tribes of Israel. 17 Let Dan prove to be a serpent by the roadside, a horned snake at the wayside, that bites the heels of the horse so that its rider falls backward. 18 I shall indeed wait for salvation from you, O Jehovah.

19 “As for Gad, a marauder band will raid him, but he will raid the extreme rear.

20 “Out of Ash′er his bread will be fat, and he will give the dainties of a king.

21 “Naph′ta·li is a slender hind. He is giving words of elegance.

22 “Offshoot of a fruit-bearing tree, Joseph is the offshoot of a fruit-bearing tree by the fountain, that propels its branches up over a wall. 23 But the archers kept harassing him and shot at him and kept harboring animosity against him. 24 And yet his bow was dwelling in a permanent place, and the strength of his hands was supple. From the hands of the Powerful One of Jacob, from there is the Shepherd, the Stone of Israel. 25 He is from the God of your father, and he will help you; and he is with the Almighty, and he will bless you with the blessings of the heavens above, with the blessings of the watery deep lying down below, with the blessings of the breasts and womb. 26 The blessings of your father will indeed be superior to the blessings of the eternal mountains, to the ornament of the indefinitely lasting hills. They will continue upon the head of Joseph, even upon the crown of the head of the one singled out from his brothers.

27 “Benjamin will keep on tearing like a wolf. In the morning he will eat the animal seized and at evening he will divide spoil.”

28 All these are the twelve tribes of Israel, and this is what their father spoke to them when he was blessing them. He blessed them each one according to his own blessing.

29 After that he commanded them and said to them: “I am being gathered to my people. Bury me with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of E′phron the Hit′tite, 30 in the cave that is in the field of Mach·pe′lah that is in front of Mam′re in the land of Ca′naan, the field that Abraham purchased from E′phron the Hit′tite for the possession of a burial place. 31 There they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife. There they buried Isaac and Re·bek′ah his wife, and there I buried Le′ah. 32 The field purchased and the cave that is in it were from the sons of Heth.”

33 Thus Jacob finished giving commands to his sons. Then he gathered his feet up onto the couch and expired and was gathered to his people.

Exodus

14 Jehovah now spoke to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, that they should turn back and encamp before Pi·ha·hi′roth between Mig′dol and the sea in view of Ba′al-ze′phon. In front of it YOU are to encamp by the sea. 3 Then Phar′aoh will certainly say respecting the sons of Israel, ‘They are wandering in confusion in the land. The wilderness has closed in upon them.’ 4 So I shall indeed let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, and he will certainly chase after them and I shall get glory for myself by means of Phar′aoh and all his military forces; and the Egyptians will certainly know that I am Jehovah.” Accordingly they did just that.

5 Later it was reported to the king of Egypt that the people had run away. Immediately the heart of Phar′aoh as well as his servants was changed regarding the people, so that they said: “What is this that we have done, in that we have sent Israel away from slaving for us?” 6 So he proceeded to make his war chariots ready, and he took his people with him. 7 And he proceeded to take six hundred chosen chariots and all the other chariots of Egypt and warriors upon every one of them. 8 Thus Jehovah let the heart of Phar′aoh the king of Egypt become obstinate, and he went chasing after the sons of Israel, while the sons of Israel were going out with uplifted hand. 9 And the Egyptians went chasing after them, and all the chariot horses of Phar′aoh and his cavalrymen and his military forces were overtaking them while camping by the sea, by Pi·ha·hi′roth in view of Ba′al-ze′phon.

10 When Phar′aoh got close by, the sons of Israel began to raise their eyes and here the Egyptians were marching after them; and the sons of Israel got quite afraid and began to cry out to Jehovah. 11 And they proceeded to say to Moses: “Is it because there are no burial places at all in Egypt that you have taken us here to die in the wilderness? What is this that you have done to us in leading us out of Egypt? 12 Is this not the word we spoke to you in Egypt, saying, ‘Let us alone, that we may serve the Egyptians’? For it is better for us to serve the Egyptians than for us to die in the wilderness.” 13 Then Moses said to the people: “Do not be afraid. Stand firm and see the salvation of Jehovah, which he will perform for YOU today. For the Egyptians whom YOU do see today YOU will not see again, no, never again. 14 Jehovah will himself fight for YOU, and YOU yourselves will be silent.”

15 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Why do you keep crying out to me? Speak to the sons of Israel that they should break camp. 16 As for you, lift up your rod and stretch your hand out over the sea and split it apart, that the sons of Israel may go through the midst of the sea on dry land. 17 As for me, here I am letting the hearts of the Egyptians become obstinate, that they may go in after them and that I may get glory for myself by means of Phar′aoh and all his military forces, his war chariots and his cavalrymen. 18 And the Egyptians will certainly know that I am Jehovah when I get glory for myself by means of Phar′aoh, his war chariots and his cavalrymen.”

19 Then the angel of the true God who was going ahead of the camp of Israel departed and went to their rear, and the pillar of cloud departed from their van and stood in the rear of them. 20 So it came in between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel. On the one hand it proved to be a cloud together with darkness. On the other hand it kept lighting up the night. And this group did not come near that group all night long.

21 Moses now stretched his hand out over the sea; and Jehovah began making the sea go back by a strong east wind all night long and converting the sea basin into dry ground, and the waters were being split apart. 22 At length the sons of Israel went through the midst of the sea on dry land, while the waters were a wall to them on their right hand and on their left. 23 And the Egyptians took up the pursuit, and all the horses of Phar′aoh, his war chariots and his cavalrymen began going in after them, into the midst of the sea. 24 And it came about during the morning watch that Jehovah began to look out upon the camp of the Egyptians from within the pillar of fire and cloud, and he went throwing the camp of the Egyptians into confusion. 25 And he kept taking wheels off their chariots so that they were driving them with difficulty; and the Egyptians began to say: “Let us flee from any contact with Israel, because Jehovah certainly fights for them against the Egyptians.”

26 Finally Jehovah said to Moses: “Stretch your hand out over the sea, that the waters may come back over the Egyptians, their war chariots and their cavalrymen.” 27 Moses at once stretched his hand out over the sea, and the sea began to come back to its normal condition at the approaching of morning. All the while the Egyptians were fleeing from encountering it, but Jehovah shook the Egyptians off into the midst of the sea. 28 And the waters kept coming back. Finally they covered the war chariots and the cavalrymen belonging to all of Phar′aoh’s military forces and who had gone into the sea after them. Not so much as one among them was let remain.

29 As for the sons of Israel, they walked on dry land in the midst of the seabed, and the waters were for them a wall on their right hand and on their left. 30 Thus on that day Jehovah saved Israel from the hand of the Egyptians, and Israel got to see the Egyptians dead on the seashore. 31 Israel also got to see the great hand that Jehovah put in action against the Egyptians; and the people began to fear Jehovah and to put faith in Jehovah and in Moses his servant.

Exodus

21 “And these are the judicial decisions that you are to set before them:

2 “In case you should buy a Hebrew slave, he will be a slave six years, but in the seventh he will go out as one set free without charge. 3 If he should come in by himself, by himself he will go out. If he is the owner of a wife, then his wife must go out with him. 4 If his master should give him a wife and she does bear him sons or daughters, the wife and her children will become her master’s and he will go out by himself. 5 But if the slave should insistently say, ‘I really love my master, my wife and my sons; I do not want to go out as one set free,’ 6 then his master must bring him near to the true God and must bring him up against the door or the doorpost; and his master must pierce his ear through with an awl, and he must be his slave to time indefinite.

7 “And in case a man should sell his daughter as a slave girl, she will not go out in the way that the slave men go out. 8 If she is displeasing in the eyes of her master so that he does not designate her as a concubine but causes her to be redeemed, he will not be entitled to sell her to a foreign people in his treacherously dealing with her. 9 And if it should be to his son that he designates her, he is to do to her according to the due right of daughters. 10 If he should take another wife for himself, her sustenance, her clothing and her marriage due are not to be diminished. 11 If he will not render these three things to her, then she must go out for nothing, without money.

12 “One who strikes a man so that he actually dies is to be put to death without fail. 13 But where one does not lie in wait and the true God lets it occur at his hand, then I must fix for you a place where he can flee. 14 And in case a man becomes heated against his fellow to the point of killing him with craftiness, you are to take him even from being at my altar to die. 15 And one who strikes his father and his mother is to be put to death without fail.

16 “And one who kidnaps a man and who actually sells him or in whose hand he has been found is to be put to death without fail.

17 “And one who calls down evil upon his father and his mother is to be put to death without fail.

18 “And in case men should get into a quarrel and one does strike his fellow with a stone or a hoe and he does not die but must keep to his bed; 19 if he gets up and does walk about out of doors upon some support of his, then the one who struck him must be free from punishment; he will make compensation only for the time lost from that one’s work until he gets him completely healed.

20 “And in case a man strikes his slave man or his slave girl with a stick and that one actually dies under his hand, that one is to be avenged without fail. 21 However, if he lingers for a day or two days, he is not to be avenged, because he is his money.

22 “And in case men should struggle with each other and they really hurt a pregnant woman and her children do come out but no fatal accident occurs, he is to have damages imposed upon him without fail according to what the owner of the woman may lay upon him; and he must give it through the justices. 23 But if a fatal accident should occur, then you must give soul for soul, 24 eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, 25 branding for branding, wound for wound, blow for blow.

26 “And in case a man should strike the eye of his slave man or the eye of his slave girl and he really ruins it, he is to send him away as one set free in compensation for his eye. 27 And if it should be the tooth of his slave man or the tooth of his slave girl that he knocks out, he is to send him away as one set free in compensation for his tooth.

28 “And in case a bull should gore a man or a woman and that one actually dies, the bull is to be stoned without fail, but its flesh is not to be eaten; and the owner of the bull is free from punishment. 29 But if a bull was formerly in the habit of goring and warning was served on its owner but he would not keep it under guard, and it did put a man or a woman to death, the bull is to be stoned and also its owner is to be put to death. 30 If a ransom should be imposed upon him, then he must give the redemption price for his soul according to all that may be imposed upon him. 31 Whether it gored a son or gored a daughter, it is to be done to him according to this judicial decision. 32 If it was a slave man or a slave girl that the bull gored, he will give the price of thirty shekels to that one’s master, and the bull will be stoned.

33 “And in case a man should open a pit, or in case a man should excavate a pit and should not cover it, and a bull or an ass does fall into it, 34 the owner of the pit is to make compensation. The price he is to return to its owner, and the dead animal will become his own. 35 And in case a man’s bull should hurt another’s bull and it does die, then they must sell the live bull and divide the price paid for it; and also the dead one they should divide. 36 Or if it was known that a bull was in the habit of goring formerly but its owner would not keep it under guard, he should without fail make compensation with bull for bull, and the dead one will become his own.

Exodus

22 “In case a man should steal a bull or a sheep and he does slaughter it or sell it, he is to compensate with five of the herd for the bull and four of the flock for the sheep.

2 (“If a thief should be found in the act of breaking in and he does get struck and die, there is no bloodguilt for him. 3 If the sun has shone forth upon him, there is bloodguilt for him.)

“He is to make compensation without fail. If he has nothing, then he must be sold for the things he stole. 4 If there should be unmistakably found in his hand what was stolen, from bull to ass and to sheep, alive, he is to make double compensation.

5 “If a man causes a field or a vineyard to be grazed over and he does send out his beasts of burden and cause a consuming in another field, he is to make compensation with the best of his own field or with the best of his own vineyard.

6 “In case a fire should spread out and it does catch thorns, and sheaves or standing grain or a field gets consumed, the one who started the fire is to make compensation without fail for what was burned.

7 “In case a man should give his fellow money or articles to keep, and it gets stolen from the man’s house, if the thief should be found, he is to make double compensation. 8 If the thief should not be found, then the owner of the house must be brought near to the true God to see whether he did not put his hand upon the goods of his fellow. 9 As regards any case of transgression, concerning a bull, an ass, a sheep, a garment, anything lost of which he may say, ‘This is it!’ the case of them both is to come to the true God. The one whom God will pronounce wicked is to make double compensation to his fellow.

10 “In case a man should give his fellow an ass or bull or sheep or any domestic animal to keep, and it does die or get maimed or gets led off while nobody is looking, 11 an oath by Jehovah is to take place between them both that he did not put his hand on the goods of his fellow; and their owner must accept it, and the other is not to make compensation. 12 But if they should for a fact be stolen from him, he is to make compensation to their owner. 13 If it should for a fact be torn by a wild beast, he is to bring it as evidence. For something torn by a wild beast he is not to make compensation.

14 “But in case anybody should ask for something of his fellow, and it does get maimed or die while its owner is not with it, he is to make compensation without fail. 15 If its owner is with it, he is not to make compensation. If it is hired, it must come in its hire.

16 “Now in case a man seduces a virgin who is not engaged, and he actually lies down with her, he is to obtain her without fail as his wife for the purchase price. 17 If her father flatly refuses to give her to him, he is to pay over the money at the rate of purchase money for virgins.

18 “You must not preserve a sorceress alive.

19 “Anyone lying down with a beast is positively to be put to death.

20 “One who sacrifices to any gods but Jehovah alone is to be devoted to destruction.

21 “And you must not maltreat an alien resident or oppress him, for YOU people became alien residents in the land of Egypt.

22 “YOU people must not afflict any widow or fatherless boy. 23 If you should afflict him at all, then if he cries out to me at all, I shall unfailingly hear his outcry; 24 and my anger will indeed blaze, and I shall certainly kill YOU with the sword, and YOUR wives must become widows and YOUR sons fatherless boys.

25 “If you should lend money to my people, to the afflicted alongside you, you must not become like a usurer to him. YOU must not lay interest upon him.

26 “If you should at all seize the garment of your fellow as a pledge, you are to return it to him at the setting of the sun. 27 For it is his only covering. It is his mantle for his skin. In what will he lie down? And it must occur that he will cry out to me, and I shall certainly hear, because I am gracious.

28 “You must not call down evil upon God nor curse a chieftain among your people.

29 “Your full produce and the overflow of your press you must not give hesitantly. The firstborn of your sons you are to give to me. 30 The way you are to do with your bull and your sheep is this: Seven days it will continue with its mother. On the eighth day you are to give it to me.

31 “And YOU should prove yourselves holy men to me; and YOU must not eat flesh in the field that is something torn by a wild beast. YOU should throw it to the dogs.

Exodus

23 “You must not take up an untrue report. Do not cooperate with a wicked one by becoming a witness who schemes violence. 2 You must not follow after the crowd for evil ends; and you must not testify over a controversy so as to turn aside with the crowd in order to pervert justice. 3 As for the lowly one, you must not show preference in a controversy of his.

4 “Should you come upon your enemy’s bull or his ass going astray, you are to return it without fail to him. 5 Should you see the ass of someone who hates you lying down under its load, then you must refrain from leaving him. With him you are without fail to get it loose.

6 “You are not to pervert the judicial decision of your poor man in his controversy.

7 “You are to keep far from a false word. And do not kill the innocent and the righteous, for I shall not declare the wicked one righteous.

8 “You are not to accept a bribe, for the bribe blinds clear-sighted men and can distort the words of righteous men.

9 “And you must not oppress an alien resident, as YOU yourselves have known the soul of the alien resident, because YOU became alien residents in the land of Egypt.

10 “And for six years you are to sow your land with seed and you must gather its produce. 11 But the seventh year you are to leave it uncultivated and you must let it lie fallow, and the poor ones of your people must eat of it; and what is left over by them the wild beasts of the field are to eat. That is the way you are to do with your vineyard and your olive grove.

12 “Six days you are to do your work; but on the seventh day you are to desist, in order that your bull and your ass may rest and the son of your slave girl and the alien resident may refresh themselves.

13 “And YOU are to be on YOUR guard respecting all that I have said to YOU; and YOU must not mention the name of other gods. It should not be heard upon your mouth.

14 “Three times in the year you are to celebrate a festival to me. 15 You will keep the festival of unfermented cakes. You will eat unfermented cakes seven days, just as I have commanded you, at the appointed time in the month of A′bib, because in it you came out of Egypt. And they must not appear before me empty-handed. 16 Also, the festival of harvest of the first ripe fruits of your labors, of what you sow in the field; and the festival of ingathering at the outgoing of the year, when you gather in your labors from the field. 17 On three occasions in the year every male of yours will appear before the face of the true Lord, Jehovah.

18 “You must not sacrifice along with what is leavened the blood of my sacrifice. And the fat of my festival should not stay overnight until morning.

19 “The best of the first ripe fruits of your ground you are to bring to the house of Jehovah your God.

“You must not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.

20 “Here I am sending an angel ahead of you to keep you on the road and to bring you into the place that I have prepared. 21 Watch yourself because of him and obey his voice. Do not behave rebelliously against him, for he will not pardon YOUR transgression; because my name is within him. 22 However, if you strictly obey his voice and really do all that I shall speak, then I shall certainly be hostile to your enemies and harass those who harass you. 23 For my angel will go ahead of you and will indeed bring you to the Am′or·ites and the Hit′tites and the Per′iz·zites and the Ca′naan·ites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, and I shall certainly efface them. 24 You must not bow down to their gods or be induced to serve them, and you must not make anything like their works, but you will without fail throw them down and you will without fail break down their sacred pillars. 25 And YOU must serve Jehovah YOUR God, and he will certainly bless your bread and your water; and I shall indeed turn malady away from your midst. 26 Neither a woman suffering an abortion nor a barren woman will exist in your land. I shall make the number of your days full.

27 “And I shall send the fright of me ahead of you, and I shall certainly throw into confusion all the people among whom you come, and I shall indeed give the back of the neck of all your enemies to you. 28 And I will send the feeling of dejection ahead of you, and it will simply drive the Hi′vites, the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites out from before you. 29 I shall not drive them out from before you in one year, that the land may not become a desolate waste and the wild beasts of the field really multiply against you. 30 Little by little I shall drive them out from before you, until you become fruitful and really take possession of the land.

31 “And I will fix your boundary from the Red Sea to the sea of the Phi·lis′tines and from the wilderness to the River; because I shall give into YOUR hand the inhabitants of the land, and you will certainly drive them out from before yourself. 32 You are not to conclude a covenant with them or their gods. 33 They should not dwell in your land, that they may not cause you to sin against me. In case you should serve their gods, it would become a snare to you.”

Exodus

24 And to Moses he said: “Go up to Jehovah, you and Aaron, Na′dab and A·bi′hu and seventy of the older men of Israel, and YOU must bow down from a distance. 2 And Moses by himself must approach Jehovah; but they should not approach, and the people should not go up with him.”

3 Then Moses came and related to the people all the words of Jehovah and all the judicial decisions, and all the people answered with one voice and said: “All the words that Jehovah has spoken we are willing to do.” 4 Accordingly Moses wrote down all the words of Jehovah. Then he got up early in the morning and built at the foot of the mountain an altar and twelve pillars corresponding with the twelve tribes of Israel. 5 After that he sent young men of the sons of Israel and they offered up burnt offerings and sacrificed bulls as sacrifices, as communion sacrifices to Jehovah. 6 Then Moses took half the blood and put it in bowls, and half the blood he sprinkled upon the altar. 7 Finally he took the book of the covenant and read it in the ears of the people. Then they said: “All that Jehovah has spoken we are willing to do and be obedient.” 8 So Moses took the blood and sprinkled it upon the people and said: “Here is the blood of the covenant that Jehovah has concluded with YOU as respects all these words.”

9 And Moses and Aaron, Na′dab and A·bi′hu and seventy of the older men of Israel proceeded to go up, 10 and they got to see the God of Israel. And under his feet there was what seemed like a work of sapphire flagstones and like the very heavens for purity. 11 And he did not put out his hand against the distinguished men of the sons of Israel, but they got a vision of the true God and ate and drank.

12 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Come up to me in the mountain and stay there, as I want to give you the stone tablets and the law and the commandment that I must write in order to teach them.” 13 So Moses and Joshua his minister got up and Moses went up into the mountain of the true God. 14 But to the older men he had said: “YOU wait for us in this place until we return to YOU. And, look! Aaron and Hur are with YOU. Whoever has a case at law, let him approach them.” 15 Thus Moses went up into the mountain while the cloud was covering the mountain.

16 And Jehovah’s glory continued to reside upon Mount Si′nai, and the cloud continued to cover it for six days. At length on the seventh day he called to Moses from the midst of the cloud. 17 And to the eyes of the sons of Israel the sight of Jehovah’s glory was like a devouring fire on the mountaintop. 18 Then Moses entered into the midst of the cloud and went on up the mountain. And Moses continued in the mountain forty days and forty nights.

Exodus

25 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, that they may take up a contribution for me: From every man whose heart incites him YOU people are to take up the contribution of mine. 3 And this is the contribution that YOU are to take up from them: gold and silver and copper, 4 and blue thread, and wool dyed reddish purple, and coccus scarlet material, and fine linen, and goat’s hair, 5 and ram skins dyed red, and sealskins, and acacia wood; 6 oil for the luminary, balsam oil for the anointing oil and for perfumed incense; 7 and onyx stones and setting stones for the eph′od and for the breastpiece. 8 And they must make a sanctuary for me, as I must tabernacle in the midst of them. 9 According to all that I am showing you as the pattern of the tabernacle and pattern of all its furnishings, that is the way YOU are to make it.

10 “And they must make an Ark of acacia wood, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width and a cubit and a half its height. 11 And you must overlay it with pure gold. Inside and outside you are to overlay it, and you must make a border of gold round about upon it. 12 And you must cast four rings of gold for it and put them above its four feet, with two rings upon the one side of it and two rings upon its other side. 13 And you must make poles of acacia wood and overlay them with gold. 14 And you must put the poles through the rings upon the sides of the Ark in order to carry the Ark with them. 15 In the rings of the Ark the poles are to stay. They are not to be removed from it. 16 And you must place in the Ark the testimony that I shall give you.

17 “And you must make a cover of pure gold, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width. 18 And you must make two cherubs of gold. Of hammered work you are to make them on both ends of the cover. 19 And make one cherub on this end and one cherub on that end. On the cover YOU are to make the cherubs at its two ends. 20 And the cherubs must be spreading out their two wings upward, screening over the cover with their wings, with their faces one toward the other. Toward the cover the faces of the cherubs should be. 21 And you must place the cover above upon the Ark, and in the Ark you will place the testimony that I shall give you. 22 And I will present myself to you there and speak with you from above the cover, from between the two cherubs that are upon the ark of the testimony, even all that I shall command you for the sons of Israel.

23 “And you must make a table of acacia wood, two cubits its length and a cubit its width and a cubit and a half its height. 24 And you must overlay it with pure gold, and you must make for it a border of gold round about. 25 And you must make for it a rim of a handbreadth round about, and you must make the border of gold for its rim round about. 26 And you must make for it four rings of gold and place the rings on the four corners that are for the four feet. 27 The rings should be close by the rim as supports for the poles to carry the table. 28 And you must make the poles of acacia wood and overlay them with gold, and they must carry the table with them.

29 “And you must make its dishes and its cups and its pitchers and its bowls with which they will pour libations. You are to make them out of pure gold. 30 And you must put the showbread upon the table before me constantly.

31 “And you must make a lampstand of pure gold. Of hammered work the lampstand is to be made. Its base, its branches, its cups, its knobs and its blossoms are to proceed out from it. 32 And six branches are running out from its sides, three branches of the lampstand from its one side and three branches of the lampstand from its other side. 33 Three cups shaped like flowers of almond are on the one set of branches, with knobs and blossoms alternating, and three cups shaped like flowers of almond on the other set of branches, with knobs and blossoms alternating. This is the way it is with the six branches running out from the lampstand. 34 And on the lampstand are four cups shaped like flowers of almond, with its knobs and its blossoms alternating. 35 And the knob under two branches is out of it and the knob under the two other branches is out of it and the knob under two more branches is out of it, for the six branches running out from the lampstand. 36 Their knobs and their branches are to proceed out from it. All of it is one piece of hammered work, of pure gold. 37 And you must make seven lamps for it; and the lamps must be lit up, and they must shine upon the area in front of it. 38 And its snuffers and its fire holders are of pure gold. 39 Of a talent of pure gold he should make it with all these utensils of it. 40 And see that you make them after their pattern that was shown to you in the mountain.

Exodus

28 “And as for you, bring near to yourself Aaron your brother and his sons with him from the midst of the sons of Israel that he may act as priest to me, Aaron, Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar, the sons of Aaron. 2 And you must make holy garments for Aaron your brother, for glory and beauty. 3 And you yourself are to speak to all the ones wise with a heart that I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, and they must make Aaron’s garments for sanctifying him, that he may act as priest to me.

4 “And these are the garments that they will make: a breastpiece, and an eph′od and a sleeveless coat and a robe of checkerwork, a turban and a sash; and they must make the holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons, that he may act as priest to me. 5 And they themselves will take the gold and the blue thread and the wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and the fine linen.

6 “And they must make the eph′od of gold, blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple, coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen, the work of an embroiderer. 7 And it is to have two shoulder pieces to be joined at its two extremities, and it must be joined. 8 And the girdle, which is upon it for tying it close, according to its workmanship should be of its materials, of gold, blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen.

9 “And you must take two onyx stones and engrave upon them the names of the sons of Israel, 10 six of their names upon the one stone and the names of the six remaining ones upon the other stone in the order of their births. 11 With the work of a craftsman in stones, with the engravings of a seal, you are to engrave the two stones with the names of the sons of Israel. Set in settings of gold is how you will make them. 12 And you must put the two stones upon the shoulder pieces of the eph′od as memorial stones for the sons of Israel; and Aaron must carry their names before Jehovah upon his two shoulder pieces as a memorial. 13 And you must make settings of gold, 14 and two chains of pure gold. As cords you will make them, with the workmanship of a rope; and you must attach the ropelike chains to the settings.

15 “And you must make the breastpiece of judgment with the workmanship of an embroiderer. Like the workmanship of the eph′od you will make it. Of gold, blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen you will make it. 16 It should be foursquare when doubled, a span of the hand being its length and a span of the hand its width. 17 And you must fill it with a filling of stones, there being four rows of stones. A row of ruby, topaz and emerald is the first row. 18 And the second row is turquoise, sapphire and jasper. 19 And the third row is lesh′em stone, agate and amethyst. 20 And the fourth row is chrys′o·lite and onyx and jade. Sockets of gold should be in their fillings. 21 And the stones should be according to the names of the sons of Israel, the twelve according to their names. With the engravings of a seal they should be, each one according to its name, for the twelve tribes.

22 “And you must make upon the breastpiece wreathed chains, in ropework, of pure gold. 23 And you must make upon the breastpiece two rings of gold, and you must put the two rings upon the two extremities of the breastpiece. 24 And you must put the two ropes of gold through the two rings at the extremities of the breastpiece. 25 And you will put the two ends of the two ropes through the two settings, and you must put them upon the shoulder pieces of the eph′od, at the forefront of it. 26 And you must make two rings of gold and set them at the two extremities of the breastpiece upon its edge that is on the side toward the eph′od inward. 27 And you must make two rings of gold and put them upon the two shoulder pieces of the eph′od from below, on its forefront, near its place of joining, above the girdle of the eph′od. 28 And they will bind the breastpiece by its rings to the rings of the eph′od with a blue string, that it may continue above the girdle of the eph′od and the breastpiece may not get displaced from on top the eph′od.

29 “And Aaron must carry the names of the sons of Israel on the breastpiece of judgment over his heart when he comes into the Holy as a memorial before Jehovah constantly. 30 And you must put the U′rim and the Thum′mim into the breastpiece of judgment, and they must prove to be over Aaron’s heart when he comes in before Jehovah; and Aaron must carry the judgments of the sons of Israel over his heart before Jehovah constantly.

31 “And you must make the sleeveless coat of the eph′od completely of blue thread. 32 And there must be an opening at its top in the middle of it. Its opening should have a border round about, the product of a loom worker. Like the opening of a coat of mail it should be for it, that it may not be torn. 33 And you must make upon the hem of it pomegranates of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material, upon its hem round about, and bells of gold in between them round about; 34 a bell of gold and a pomegranate, a bell of gold and a pomegranate upon the hem of the sleeveless coat round about. 35 And it must be upon Aaron that he may minister, and the sound from him must be heard when he goes into the sanctuary before Jehovah and when he comes out, that he may not die.

36 “And you must make a shining plate of pure gold and engrave upon it with the engravings of a seal, ‘Holiness belongs to Jehovah.’ 37 And you must fasten it with a blue string, and it must come to be upon the turban. On the forefront of the turban it should come to be. 38 And it must come to be upon Aaron’s forehead, and Aaron must answer for the error committed against the holy objects, which the sons of Israel will sanctify, that is to say, all their holy gifts; and it must stay upon his forehead constantly, to gain approval for them before Jehovah.

39 “And you must weave in checkerwork the robe of fine linen and make a turban of fine linen, and you will make a sash, the work of a weaver.

40 “And for Aaron’s sons you will make robes, and you must make sashes for them, and you will make headgears for them for glory and beauty. 41 And with them you must clothe Aaron your brother and his sons with him, and you must anoint them and fill their hand with power and sanctify them, and they must act as priests to me. 42 And make drawers of linen for them to cover the naked flesh. From the hips and to the thighs they are to extend. 43 And they must be upon Aaron and his sons when they come into the tent of meeting or when they go near to the altar to minister in the holy place, that they may not incur error and certainly die. It is a statute to time indefinite for him and his offspring after him.

Exodus

29 “And this is the thing that you are to do to them to sanctify them for acting as priests to me: Take a young bull, and two rams, sound ones, 2 and unfermented bread and unfermented ring-shaped cakes moistened with oil and unfermented wafers smeared with oil. Out of fine wheat flour you will make them. 3 And you must put them upon a basket and present them in the basket, and also the bull and the two rams.

4 “And you will present Aaron and his sons at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and you must wash them with water. 5 Then you must take the garments and clothe Aaron with the robe and the sleeveless coat of the eph′od and with the eph′od and the breastpiece, and you must tie it closely to him with the girdle of the eph′od. 6 And you must set the turban upon his head and put the holy sign of dedication upon the turban. 7 And you must take the anointing oil and pour it upon his head and anoint him.

8 “Then you will bring his sons near and you must clothe them with the robes. 9 And you must gird them with the sashes, Aaron as well as his sons, and you must wrap the headgear upon them; and the priesthood must become theirs as a statute to time indefinite. So you must fill the hand of Aaron and the hand of his sons with power.

10 “You must now present the bull before the tent of meeting, and Aaron and his sons must lay their hands upon the bull’s head. 11 And you must slaughter the bull before Jehovah, at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 12 And you must take some of the bull’s blood and put it with your finger upon the horns of the altar, and all the rest of the blood you will pour out at the base of the altar. 13 And you must take all the fat that covers the intestines, and the appendage upon the liver, and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, and you must make them smoke upon the altar. 14 But the bull’s flesh and its skin and its dung you will burn with fire outside the camp. It is a sin offering.

15 “Then you will take the one ram, and Aaron and his sons must lay their hands upon the ram’s head. 16 And you must slaughter the ram and take its blood and sprinkle it round about upon the altar. 17 And you will cut up the ram into its pieces, and you must wash its intestines and its shanks and put its pieces to one another and up to its head. 18 And you must make the entire ram smoke upon the altar. It is a burnt offering to Jehovah, a restful odor. It is an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

19 “Next you must take the other ram, and Aaron and his sons must lay their hands upon the ram’s head. 20 And you must slaughter the ram and take some of its blood and put it upon the lobe of Aaron’s right ear and upon the lobe of his sons’ right ear and upon the thumb of their right hand and the big toe of their right foot, and you must sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar. 21 And you must take some of the blood that is upon the altar and some of the anointing oil, and you must spatter it upon Aaron and his garments and upon his sons and the garments of his sons with him, that he and his garments and his sons and the garments of his sons with him may indeed be holy.

22 “And you must take from the ram the fat and the fat tail and the fat that covers the intestines, and the appendage of the liver, and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, and the right leg, for it is a ram of installation; 23 also a round loaf of bread and a ring-shaped cake of oiled bread and a wafer out of the basket of unfermented cakes that is before Jehovah. 24 And you must place them all upon the palms of Aaron and upon the palms of his sons, and you must wave them to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah. 25 And you must take them off their hands and make them smoke upon the altar upon the burnt offering as a restful odor before Jehovah. It is an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

26 “And you must take the breast of the ram of installation, which is for Aaron, and wave it to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah, and it must become your portion. 27 And you must sanctify the breast of the wave offering and the leg of the sacred portion that was waved and that was contributed from the ram of installation, from what was for Aaron and from what was for his sons. 28 And it must become Aaron’s and his sons’ by a regulation to time indefinite to be performed by the sons of Israel, because it is a sacred portion; and it will become a sacred portion to be rendered by the sons of Israel. From their communion sacrifices it is their sacred portion for Jehovah.

29 “And the holy garments that are Aaron’s will serve for his sons after him to anoint them in them and to fill their hand with power in them. 30 Seven days the priest who succeeds him from among his sons and who comes into the tent of meeting to minister in the holy place will wear them.

31 “And you will take the ram of installation, and you must boil its flesh in a holy place. 32 And Aaron and his sons must eat the flesh of the ram and the bread that is in the basket at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 33 And they must eat the things with which atonement has been made to fill their hand with power, in order to sanctify them. But a stranger may not eat them, because they are something holy. 34 And if any of the flesh of the installation sacrifice and of the bread should be left over until the morning, then you must burn what is left over with fire. It must not be eaten, because it is something holy.

35 “And you must do this way to Aaron and his sons according to all that I have commanded you. You will take seven days to fill their hand with power. 36 And you will offer the bull of the sin offering daily for an atonement, and you must purify the altar from sin by your making atonement over it, and you must anoint it to sanctify it. 37 You will take seven days to make atonement over the altar, and you must sanctify it that it may indeed become a most holy altar. Anyone who touches the altar is to be holy.

38 “And this is what you will offer upon the altar: young rams each a year old, two a day constantly. 39 And you will offer the one young ram in the morning, and you will offer the other young ram between the two evenings. 40 And a tenth part of an e′phah measure of fine flour moistened with the fourth of a hin of beaten oil, and a drink offering of the fourth of a hin of wine, will go for the first young ram. 41 And you will offer the second young ram between the two evenings. With a grain offering like that of the morning and with a drink offering like its, you will render it as a restful odor, an offering made by fire to Jehovah. 42 It is a constant burnt offering throughout YOUR generations at the entrance of the tent of meeting before Jehovah, where I shall present myself to YOU people to speak to you there.

43 “And I will present myself there to the sons of Israel, and it will certainly be sanctified by my glory. 44 And I will sanctify the tent of meeting and the altar; and I shall sanctify Aaron and his sons for them to act as priests to me. 45 And I will tabernacle in the midst of the sons of Israel, and I will prove to be their God. 46 And they will certainly know that I am Jehovah their God, who brought them out of the land of Egypt that I may tabernacle in the midst of them. I am Jehovah their God.

Exodus

31 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “See, I do call by name Bez′al·el the son of U′ri the son of Hur of the tribe of Judah. 3 And I shall fill him with the spirit of God in wisdom and in understanding and in knowledge and in every kind of craftsmanship, 4 for designing devices, for working in gold and silver and copper, 5 and in working of stones to set them and in working of wood to make products of every kind. 6 As for me, look! I do put with him O·ho′li·ab the son of A·his′a·mach of the tribe of Dan, and in the heart of everyone wise of heart I do put wisdom, that they may indeed make everything I have commanded you: 7 the tent of meeting and the Ark for the testimony and the cover that is upon it, and all the utensils of the tent, 8 and the table and its utensils, and the lampstand of pure gold and all its utensils, and the altar of incense, 9 and the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils, and the basin and its stand, 10 and the garments of knitted work and the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons for acting as priests; 11 and the anointing oil and the perfumed incense for the sanctuary. According to everything I have commanded you they will do.”

12 And Jehovah said further to Moses: 13 “As for you, speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘Especially my sabbaths YOU are to keep, for it is a sign between me and YOU during YOUR generations that YOU may know that I Jehovah am sanctifying YOU. 14 And YOU must keep the sabbath, for it is something holy to YOU. A profaner of it will positively be put to death. In case there is anyone doing work on it, then that soul must be cut off from the midst of his people. 15 Six days may work be done, but on the seventh day is a sabbath of complete rest. It is something holy to Jehovah. Anyone doing work on the sabbath day will positively be put to death. 16 And the sons of Israel must keep the sabbath, so as to carry out the sabbath during their generations. It is a covenant to time indefinite. 17 Between me and the sons of Israel it is a sign to time indefinite, because in six days Jehovah made the heavens and the earth and on the seventh day he rested and proceeded to refresh himself.’”

18 Now as soon as he had finished speaking with him on Mount Si′nai he proceeded to give Moses two tablets of the Testimony, tablets of stone written on by God’s finger.

Exodus

34 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Carve out for yourself two tablets of stone like the first ones, and I must write upon the tablets the words that appeared on the first tablets, which you shattered. 2 And get ready for the morning, as you must go up in the morning into Mount Si′nai and station yourself by me there on the top of the mountain. 3 But nobody may go up with you and, too, let nobody else be seen in all the mountain. What is more, no flock or herd should be pasturing in front of that mountain.”

4 Accordingly Moses carved out two tablets of stone like the first ones and got up early in the morning and went on up into Mount Si′nai, just as Jehovah had commanded him, and he was taking the two tablets of stone in his hand. 5 And Jehovah proceeded to come down in the cloud and station himself with him there and declare the name of Jehovah. 6 And Jehovah went passing by before his face and declaring: “Jehovah, Jehovah, a God merciful and gracious, slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness and truth, 7 preserving loving-kindness for thousands, pardoning error and transgression and sin, but by no means will he give exemption from punishment, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons and upon grandsons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation.”

8 Moses at once hurried to bow low to the earth and prostrate himself. 9 Then he said: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, O Jehovah, let Jehovah, please, go along in the midst of us, because it is a stiff-necked people, and you have to forgive our error and our sin, and you must take us as your possession.” 10 In turn he said: “Here I am concluding a covenant: Before all your people I shall do wonderful things that have never been created in all the earth or among all the nations; and all the people in the midst of whom you are will indeed see the work of Jehovah, because it is a fear-inspiring thing that I am doing with you.

11 “For your part keep what I am commanding you today. Here I am driving out from before you the Am′or·ites and the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites. 12 Watch yourself that you do not conclude a covenant with the inhabitants of the land to which you are going, for fear it may prove itself a snare in your midst. 13 But their altars YOU people are to pull down, and their sacred pillars YOU are to shatter, and their sacred poles YOU are to cut down. 14 For you must not prostrate yourself to another god, because Jehovah, whose name is Jealous, he is a jealous God; 15 for fear that you may conclude a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, as they will certainly have immoral intercourse with their gods and sacrifice to their gods, and someone will be certain to invite you, and you will certainly eat some of his sacrifice. 16 Then you will have to take some of their daughters for your sons, and their daughters will be certain to have immoral intercourse with their gods and make your sons have immoral intercourse with their gods.

17 “You must not make molten idol gods for yourself.

18 “The festival of unfermented cakes you are to keep. You will eat unfermented cakes, just as I have commanded you, seven days at the appointed time in the month of A′bib, because it was in the month of A′bib that you came out of Egypt.

19 “Everything that first opens the womb is mine, and, as regards all your livestock, the male firstling of bull and of sheep. 20 And the firstling of an ass you are to redeem with a sheep. But if you will not redeem it, then you must break its neck. Every firstborn of your sons you are to redeem. And they must not appear before me empty-handed.

21 “Six days you are to labor, but on the seventh day you will keep sabbath. In plowing time and in harvest you will keep sabbath.

22 “And you will carry on your festival of weeks with the first ripe fruits of the wheat harvest, and the festival of ingathering at the turn of the year.

23 “Three times in the year every male of yours is to appear before the true Lord, Jehovah, the God of Israel. 24 For I shall drive the nations away from before you, and I will make your territory spacious; and nobody will desire your land while you are going up to see the face of Jehovah your God three times in the year.

25 “You must not slaughter along with what is leavened the blood of my sacrifice. And the sacrifice of the festival of the passover should not stay overnight until the morning.

26 “The best of the first ripe fruits of your soil you are to bring to the house of Jehovah your God.

“You must not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.”

27 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “Write down for yourself these words, because it is in accordance with these words that I do conclude a covenant with you and Israel.” 28 And he continued there with Jehovah forty days and forty nights. He ate no bread and he drank no water. And he proceeded to write upon the tablets the words of the covenant, the Ten Words.

29 Now it came about when Moses came down from Mount Si′nai that the two tablets of the Testimony were in the hand of Moses when he came down from the mountain, and Moses did not know that the skin of his face emitted rays because of his having spoken with him. 30 When Aaron and all the sons of Israel got to see Moses, why, look! the skin of his face emitted rays and they grew afraid of coming near to him.

31 And Moses proceeded to call them. So Aaron and all the chieftains among the assembly came back to him, and Moses began to speak to them. 32 First after that all the sons of Israel came near to him, and he began commanding them all that Jehovah had spoken with him on Mount Si′nai. 33 When Moses would finish speaking with them, he would put a veil over his face. 34 But when Moses would go in before Jehovah to speak with him, he would take away the veil until his going out. And he went out and spoke to the sons of Israel what he would be commanded. 35 And the sons of Israel saw Moses’ face, that the skin of Moses’ face emitted rays; and Moses put the veil back over his face until he went in to speak with him.

Exodus

35 Later Moses called the entire assembly of the sons of Israel together and said to them: “These are the words that Jehovah has commanded, to do them: 2 Six days may work be done, but on the seventh day it will become something holy to YOU, a sabbath of complete rest to Jehovah. Anybody doing work on it will be put to death. 3 YOU must not light a fire in any of YOUR dwelling places on the sabbath day.”

4 And Moses went on to say to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel: “This is the word that Jehovah has commanded, saying, 5 ‘From among yourselves take up a contribution for Jehovah. Let every willing-hearted one bring it as Jehovah’s contribution, namely, gold and silver and copper 6 and blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine linen and goat’s hair 7 and ram skins dyed red and sealskins and acacia wood 8 and oil for the luminary and balsam oil for the anointing oil and for the perfumed incense 9 and onyx stones and setting stones for the eph′od and for the breastpiece.

10 “‘And let all the wise-hearted ones among YOU come and make all that Jehovah has commanded, 11 namely, the tabernacle with its tent and its covering, its hooks and its panel frames, its bars, its pillars and its socket pedestals; 12 the Ark and its poles, the cover and the curtain of the screen; 13 the table and its poles and all its utensils and the showbread; 14 and the lampstand of illumination and its utensils and its lamps and the oil for illumination; 15 and the altar of incense and its poles; and the anointing oil and the perfumed incense; and the screen of the entrance for the tabernacle’s entrance; 16 the altar of burnt offering and the copper grating that is for it, its poles and all its utensils; the basin and its stand; 17 the hangings of the courtyard, its pillars and its socket pedestals; and the screen of the gate of the courtyard; 18 the tent pins of the tabernacle and the tent pins of the courtyard and their cords; 19 the garments of knitted work for ministering in the sanctuary, the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons for acting as priests.’”

20 Accordingly all the assembly of the sons of Israel went out from before Moses. 21 Then they came, everyone whose heart impelled him, and they brought, everyone whose spirit incited him, Jehovah’s contribution for the work of the tent of meeting and for all its service and for the holy garments. 22 And they kept coming, the men along with the women, every willing-hearted one. They brought brooches and earrings and rings and female ornaments, all sorts of articles of gold, that is, everyone who presented the wave offering of gold to Jehovah. 23 And all those with whom there were found blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine linen and goat’s hair and ram skins dyed red and sealskins, brought them. 24 All those contributing the contribution of silver and copper brought Jehovah’s contribution, and all those with whom there was found acacia wood for all the work of the service brought it.

25 And all the women who were wise of heart spun with their hands, and they kept bringing as yarn the blue thread and the wool dyed reddish purple, the coccus scarlet material and the fine linen. 26 And all the women whose hearts impelled them with wisdom spun the goat’s hair.

27 And the chieftains brought onyx stones and setting stones for the eph′od and the breastpiece, 28 and the balsam oil and the oil for illumination and for the anointing oil and for the perfumed incense. 29 Every man and woman whose hearts incited them to bring something for all the work that Jehovah had commanded to make by means of Moses did so; the sons of Israel brought a voluntary offering to Jehovah.

30 Then Moses said to the sons of Israel: “See, Jehovah has called by name Bez′al·el the son of U′ri the son of Hur of the tribe of Judah. 31 And he proceeded to fill him with the spirit of God in wisdom, in understanding and in knowledge and in every sort of craftsmanship 32 and for designing devices, for working in gold and silver and copper, 33 and in working of stones to set them and in working of wood to make ingenious products of every sort. 34 And he has put it into his heart that he should teach, he and O·ho′li·ab the son of A·his′a·mach of the tribe of Dan. 35 He has filled them with wisdom of heart to do all the work of a craftsman and an embroiderer and of a weaver in blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple, in coccus scarlet material and fine linen, and of a loom worker, men doing every sort of work and designing devices.

Exodus

37 Bez′al·el now made the Ark of acacia wood. Two cubits and a half was its length, and a cubit and a half its width, and a cubit and a half its height. 2 Then he overlaid it with pure gold inside and outside and made a border of gold round about for it. 3 After that he cast four rings of gold for it, for above its four feet, with two rings on its one side and two rings on its other side. 4 He next made poles of acacia wood and overlaid them with gold. 5 Then he put the poles through the rings on the sides of the Ark for carrying the Ark.

6 And he went on to make the cover of pure gold. Two cubits and a half was its length, and a cubit and a half its width. 7 He further made two cherubs of gold. Of hammered work he made them on both ends of the cover. 8 One cherub was on the end over there, and the other cherub on the end over here. He made the cherubs on the cover on both of its ends. 9 And they came to be cherubs spreading out two wings upward, screening over the cover with their wings, and their faces were one to the other. The faces of the cherubs proved to be toward the cover.

10 And he proceeded to make the table of acacia wood. Two cubits was its length, and a cubit its width, and a cubit and a half its height. 11 Then he overlaid it with pure gold and made a border of gold round about for it. 12 Next he made for it a rim of a handbreadth round about and made a border of gold for its rim round about. 13 Further, he cast four rings of gold for it and put the rings upon the four corners that were for the four feet. 14 The rings proved to be near the rim, as supports for the poles for carrying the table. 15 Then he made the poles of acacia wood and overlaid them with gold for carrying the table. 16 After that he made the utensils that are upon the table, its dishes and its cups and its bowls and its pitchers with which libations would be poured, out of pure gold.

17 Then he made the lampstand of pure gold. Of hammered work he made the lampstand. Its sides and its branches, its cups, its knobs and its blossoms proceeded out of it. 18 And six branches were running out from its sides, three branches of the lampstand out from its one side and three branches of the lampstand out from its other side. 19 Three cups shaped like flowers of almond were on the one set of branches, with knobs and blossoms alternating; and three cups shaped like flowers of almond were on the other set of branches, with knobs and blossoms alternating. That is the way it was for the six branches running out from the lampstand. 20 And on the lampstand there were four cups shaped like flowers of almond, with its knobs and its blossoms alternating. 21 And the knob under two branches was out of it, and the knob under two other branches was out of it, and the knob under two more branches was out of it, for the six branches running out from the lampstand. 22 Their knobs and their branches proceeded out from it. All of it was one piece of hammered work, of pure gold. 23 Then he made its seven lamps and its snuffers and its fire holders out of pure gold. 24 Of a talent of pure gold he made it and all its utensils.

25 He now made the altar of incense out of acacia wood. A cubit was its length and a cubit its width, it being foursquare, and two cubits was its height. Its horns proceeded out of it. 26 Then he overlaid it with pure gold, its top surface and its sides round about and its horns, and he made a border of gold round about for it. 27 And he made for it two rings of gold down below its border upon two of its sides, upon two opposite sides of it, as supports for the poles with which to carry it. 28 After that he made the poles of acacia wood and overlaid them with gold. 29 He made additionally the holy anointing oil and the pure, perfumed incense, the work of an ointment maker.

Exodus

38 And he went on to make the altar of burnt offering out of acacia wood. Five cubits was its length, and five cubits its width, it being foursquare, and three cubits was its height. 2 Then he made its horns upon its four corners. Its horns proceeded out of it. Next he overlaid it with copper. 3 After that he made all the utensils of the altar, the cans and the shovels and the bowls, the forks and the fire holders. All its utensils he made of copper. 4 He further made for the altar a grating, a network of copper, under its rim, down toward its center. 5 Then he cast four rings on the four extremities near the grating of copper, as supports for the poles. 6 After that he made the poles of acacia wood and overlaid them with copper. 7 Then he put the poles into the rings on the sides of the altar for carrying it with them. He made it a hollow chest of planks.

8 Then he made the basin of copper and its stand of copper, by the use of the mirrors of the women servants who did organized service at the entrance of the tent of meeting.

9 And he proceeded to make the courtyard. For the side toward the Neg′eb, to the south, the hangings of the courtyard were of fine twisted linen, for a hundred cubits. 10 Their twenty pillars and their twenty socket pedestals were of copper. The pegs of the pillars and their joints were of silver. 11 Also, for the north side there were a hundred cubits. Their twenty pillars and their twenty socket pedestals were of copper. The pegs of the pillars and their joints were of silver. 12 But for the west side the hangings were for fifty cubits. Their pillars were ten and their socket pedestals ten. The pegs of the pillars and their joints were of silver. 13 And for the east side toward the sunrising there were fifty cubits. 14 The hangings were for fifteen cubits to the one wing. Their pillars were three and their socket pedestals three. 15 And for the other wing, on this as well as that side, of the gate of the courtyard, the hangings were for fifteen cubits. Their pillars were three and their socket pedestals three. 16 All the hangings of the courtyard round about were of fine twisted linen. 17 And the socket pedestals for the pillars were of copper. The pegs of the pillars and their joints were of silver and the overlaying of their tops was of silver, and there were silver joinings for all the pillars of the courtyard.

18 And the screen of the gate of the courtyard was the work of a weaver, of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen, and twenty cubits was the length, and the height throughout its extent was five cubits equally with the hangings of the courtyard. 19 And their four pillars and their four socket pedestals were of copper. Their pegs were of silver and the overlaying of their heads and their joints were of silver. 20 And all the tent pins for the tabernacle and for the courtyard round about were of copper.

21 The following are the things inventoried of the tabernacle, the tabernacle of the Testimony, which was inventoried at the command of Moses, as the service of the Levites under the guidance of Ith′a·mar the son of Aaron the priest. 22 And Bez′al·el the son of U′ri the son of Hur of the tribe of Judah did all that Jehovah had commanded Moses. 23 And with him was O·ho′li·ab the son of A·his′a·mach of the tribe of Dan, a craftsman and embroiderer and weaver in the blue thread and the wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine linen.

24 All the gold that was used for the work in all the work of the holy place came to the amount of the gold of the wave offering, twenty-nine talents and seven hundred and thirty shekels by the shekel of the holy place. 25 And the silver of the ones registered of the assembly was a hundred talents and one thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels by the shekel of the holy place. 26 The half shekel for an individual was the half of a shekel by the shekel of the holy place, for every man who was passing over to those who were registered from twenty years of age and upward, amounting to six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty.

27 And a hundred talents of silver went into the casting of the socket pedestals of the holy place and the socket pedestals of the curtain. A hundred socket pedestals equaled a hundred talents, a talent to a socket pedestal. 28 And out of the thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels he made pegs for the pillars and overlaid their tops and joined them together.

29 And the copper of the wave offering was seventy talents and two thousand four hundred shekels. 30 And with this he proceeded to make the socket pedestals of the entrance of the tent of meeting and the copper altar and the copper grating that belonged to it, and all the utensils of the altar, 31 and the socket pedestals of the courtyard round about, and the socket pedestals of the gate of the courtyard, and all the tent pins of the tabernacle and all the tent pins of the courtyard round about.

Exodus

40 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 2 “On the day of the first month, on the first of the month, you are to set up the tabernacle of the tent of meeting. 3 And you must place the ark of the testimony in it and shut off approach to the Ark with the curtain. 4 And you must bring the table in and set its arrangement in order, and you must bring in the lampstand and light up its lamps. 5 And you must put the golden altar for incense before the ark of the testimony and put the screen of the entrance for the tabernacle in place.

6 “And you must put the altar of burnt offering before the entrance of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, 7 and you must put the basin between the tent of meeting and the altar and put water in it. 8 And you must place the courtyard round about and put up the screen of the gate of the courtyard. 9 And you must take the anointing oil and anoint the tabernacle and all that is in it, and you must sanctify it and all its utensils, and so it must become something holy. 10 And you must anoint the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils and sanctify the altar, and so it must become a most holy altar. 11 And you must anoint the basin and its stand and sanctify it.

12 “Then you must bring Aaron and his sons near to the entrance of the tent of meeting and wash them with water. 13 And you must clothe Aaron with the holy garments and anoint him and sanctify him, and so he must act as priest to me. 14 After that you will bring his sons near and you must clothe them with robes. 15 And you must anoint them just as you anointed their father, and so they must act as priests to me, and their anointing must serve continually for them as a priesthood to time indefinite during their generations.”

16 And Moses proceeded to do according to all that Jehovah had commanded him. He did just so.

17 Accordingly it came about that in the first month, in the second year, on the first day of the month, the tabernacle was set up. 18 When Moses proceeded to set up the tabernacle, he went putting its socket pedestals down and placing its panel frames and putting its bars in and setting up its pillars. 19 Then he spread out the tent over the tabernacle and placed the covering of the tent above upon it, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

20 After that he took the Testimony and put it into the Ark and placed the poles on the Ark and put the cover above upon the Ark. 21 Then he brought the Ark into the tabernacle and put the curtain of the screen in place and shut off approach to the ark of the testimony, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

22 Next he put the table in the tent of meeting on the side of the tabernacle to the north outside the curtain, 23 and he arranged the row of bread upon it before Jehovah, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

24 Then he placed the lampstand in the tent of meeting in front of the table, on the side of the tabernacle to the south. 25 He then lit up the lamps before Jehovah, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

26 He next placed the golden altar in the tent of meeting before the curtain, 27 that he might make perfumed incense smoke upon it, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

28 Finally he put the screen of the entrance of the tabernacle in place.

29 And he placed the altar of burnt offering at the entrance of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, that he might offer up the burnt offering and the grain offering upon it, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

30 Then he placed the basin between the tent of meeting and the altar and put water in it for washing. 31 And Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet at it. 32 When they went into the tent of meeting and when they went near to the altar they would wash, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

33 Finally he set up the courtyard round about the tabernacle and the altar and put up the screen of the gate of the courtyard.

So Moses finished the work. 34 And the cloud began to cover the tent of meeting, and Jehovah’s glory filled the tabernacle. 35 And Moses was not able to go into the tent of meeting, because the cloud resided over it and Jehovah’s glory filled the tabernacle.

36 And when the cloud lifted itself up from over the tabernacle the sons of Israel would break camp during all their stages of journey. 37 However, if the cloud did not lift itself up, then they would not break camp until the day when it lifted itself up. 38 For Jehovah’s cloud was over the tabernacle by day, and a fire continued upon it by night in the sight of all the house of Israel during all their stages of journey.

Leviticus

1 And Jehovah proceeded to call Moses and speak to him out of the tent of meeting, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘In case some man of YOU would present an offering to Jehovah from the domestic animals, YOU should present YOUR offering from the herd and from the flock.

3 “‘If his offering is a burnt offering from the herd, a male, a sound one, is what he should present. At the entrance of the tent of meeting he should present it of his own free will before Jehovah. 4 And he must lay his hand upon the head of the burnt offering, and it must be graciously accepted for him to make atonement for him.

5 “‘Then the young bull must be slaughtered before Jehovah; and the sons of Aaron, the priests, must present the blood and sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar, which is at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 6 And the burnt offering must be skinned and cut up into its parts. 7 And the sons of Aaron, the priests, must put fire on the altar and set wood in order on the fire. 8 And the sons of Aaron, the priests, must set the pieces in order with the head and the suet over the wood that is on the fire that is on the altar. 9 And its intestines and its shanks will be washed with water; and the priest must make all of it smoke on the altar as a burnt offering, an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah.

10 “‘And if his offering for a burnt offering is from the flock, from the young rams or the goats, a male, a sound one, is what he will present. 11 And it must be slaughtered at the side of the altar to the north before Jehovah, and the sons of Aaron, the priests, must sprinkle its blood round about upon the altar. 12 And he must cut it up into its parts and its head and its suet, and the priest must set them in order over the wood that is on the fire that is on the altar. 13 And he will wash the intestines and the shanks with water; and the priest must present all of it and make it smoke on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah.

14 “‘However, if his offering as a burnt offering to Jehovah is from the fowls, then he must present his offering from the turtledoves or the young pigeons. 15 And the priest must present it at the altar and nip off its head and make it smoke upon the altar, but its blood must be drained out upon the side of the altar. 16 And he must remove its crop with its feathers and throw it beside the altar, to the east, to the place for the fatty ashes. 17 And he must cleave it at its wings. He must not divide it. Then the priest must make it smoke on the altar over the wood that is on the fire. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah.

Leviticus

3 “‘And if his offering is a communion sacrifice, if he is presenting it from the herd, whether a male or a female, a sound one is what he will present before Jehovah. 2 And he must lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and it must be slaughtered at the entrance of the tent of meeting; and Aaron’s sons, the priests, must sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar. 3 And he must present some of the communion sacrifice as an offering made by fire to Jehovah, namely, the fat that covers the intestines, even all the fat that is over the intestines, 4 and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, the same as that upon the loins. And as for the appendage upon the liver, he will remove it along with the kidneys. 5 And Aaron’s sons must make it smoke on the altar, upon the burnt offering that is over the wood that is on the fire, as an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah.

6 “‘And if his offering is from the flock for a communion sacrifice to Jehovah, a male or a female, a sound one is what he will present. 7 If he is presenting a young ram as his offering, then he must present it before Jehovah. 8 And he must lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and it must be slaughtered before the tent of meeting; and Aaron’s sons must sprinkle its blood round about upon the altar. 9 And from the communion sacrifice he must present its fat as an offering made by fire to Jehovah. The entire fatty tail is what he will remove near the backbone, and the fat that covers the intestines, even all the fat that is upon the intestines, 10 and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, the same as that upon the loins. And as for the appendage upon the liver, he will remove it along with the kidneys. 11 And the priest must make it smoke on the altar as food, an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

12 “‘And if his offering is a goat, then he must present it before Jehovah. 13 And he must lay his hand upon its head, and it must be slaughtered before the tent of meeting; and Aaron’s sons must sprinkle its blood round about upon the altar. 14 And from it he must present as his offering, as an offering made by fire to Jehovah, the fat that covers the intestines, even all the fat that is upon the intestines, 15 and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, the same as that upon the loins. And as for the appendage upon the liver, he will remove it along with the kidneys. 16 And the priest must make them smoke upon the altar as food, an offering made by fire for a restful odor. All the fat belongs to Jehovah.

17 “‘It is a statute to time indefinite for YOUR generations, in all YOUR dwelling places: YOU must not eat any fat or any blood at all.’”

Leviticus

4 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘In case a soul sins by mistake in any of the things that Jehovah commands should not be done, and he actually does one of them:

3 “‘If the priest, the anointed one, sins so as to bring guiltiness upon the people, then he must present for his sin that he has committed a sound young bull to Jehovah as a sin offering. 4 And he must bring the bull to the entrance of the tent of meeting before Jehovah and must lay his hand upon the bull’s head, and he must slaughter the bull before Jehovah. 5 And the priest, the anointed one, must take some of the bull’s blood and bring it into the tent of meeting; 6 and the priest must dip his finger in the blood and spatter some of the blood seven times before Jehovah in front of the curtain of the holy place. 7 And the priest must put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar of perfumed incense before Jehovah, which is in the tent of meeting, and all the rest of the bull’s blood he will pour at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.

8 “‘As to all the fat of the bull of the sin offering, he will lift up from it the fat that covers over the intestines, even all the fat that is over the intestines, 9 and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them, the same as that upon the loins. And as for the appendage upon the liver, he will remove it along with the kidneys. 10 It will be the same as what is lifted up of a bull of the communion sacrifice. And the priest must make them smoke upon the altar of burnt offering.

11 “‘But as for the skin of the bull and all its flesh along with its head and its shanks and its intestines and its dung, 12 he must have the entire bull taken out to the outskirts of the camp to a clean place where the fatty ashes are poured out, and he must burn it upon wood in the fire. Where the fatty ashes are poured out it should be burned.

13 “‘Now if the entire assembly of Israel makes a mistake and the matter has been hidden from the eyes of the congregation in that they have done one of all the things that Jehovah commands should not be done and so have become guilty, 14 and the sin that they have committed against it has become known, then the congregation must present a young bull for a sin offering and must bring it before the tent of meeting. 15 And the older men of the assembly must lay their hands upon the bull’s head before Jehovah, and the bull must be slaughtered before Jehovah.

16 “‘Then the priest, the anointed one, must bring some of the bull’s blood into the tent of meeting. 17 And the priest must dip his finger into some of the blood and spatter it seven times before Jehovah in front of the curtain. 18 And he will put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar that is before Jehovah, which is in the tent of meeting; and all the rest of the blood he will pour at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 19 And he will lift up all its fat from it, and he must make it smoke on the altar. 20 And he must do to the bull just as he did to the other bull of the sin offering. That is the way he will do to it; and the priest must make an atonement for them, and so it must be forgiven them. 21 And he must have the bull taken out to the outskirts of the camp and must burn it, just as he burned the first bull. It is a sin offering for the congregation.

22 “‘When a chieftain sins and he does commit unintentionally one of all the things that Jehovah his God commands should not be done, and so has become guilty, 23 or his sin that he has committed against the commandment has been made known to him, then he must bring as his offering a male kid of the goats, a sound one. 24 And he must lay his hand upon the head of the young goat and slaughter it in the place where the burnt offering is regularly slaughtered before Jehovah. It is a sin offering. 25 And the priest must take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and he will pour the rest of its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering. 26 And he will make all its fat smoke on the altar like the fat of the communion sacrifice; and the priest must make an atonement for him for his sin, and so it must be forgiven him.

27 “‘And if any soul of the people of the land sins unintentionally by his doing one of the things that Jehovah commands should not be done and he does become guilty, 28 or his sin that he has committed has been made known to him, then he must bring as his offering a female kid of the goats, a sound one, for his sin that he has committed. 29 And he must lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering and slaughter the sin offering in the same place as the burnt offering. 30 And the priest must take some of its blood with his finger and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and he will pour all the rest of its blood at the base of the altar. 31 And he will remove all its fat, just as the fat was removed from off the communion sacrifice; and the priest must make it smoke on the altar as a restful odor to Jehovah; and the priest must make an atonement for him, and so it must be forgiven him.

32 “‘But if he would bring a lamb as his offering for a sin offering, a sound female lamb is what he should bring. 33 And he must lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering and slaughter it as a sin offering in the place where the burnt offering is regularly slaughtered. 34 And the priest must take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and he will pour all the rest of its blood at the base of the altar. 35 And he will remove all its fat the same as the fat of the young ram of the communion sacrifice is regularly removed, and the priest must make them smoke on the altar upon Jehovah’s offerings made by fire; and the priest must make an atonement for him for his sin that he has committed, and so it must be forgiven him.

Leviticus

6 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “In case a soul sins in that he does behave unfaithfully toward Jehovah and does deceive his associate about something in his charge or a deposit in hand or a robbery or he does defraud his associate, 3 or he does find something lost and is actually deceptive about it and does swear falsely over any of all the things that the man might do to sin by them; 4 then it must occur that in case he sins and indeed becomes guilty, he must return the robbed thing which he has robbed or the extorted thing which he has taken by fraud or the thing in his charge which was put in his charge or the thing lost that he has found, 5 or anything at all over which he might swear falsely, and he must make compensation for it in its full amount, and he will add to it a fifth of it. To the one whose it is he will give it on the day his guilt is proved. 6 And as his guilt offering he will bring to Jehovah a sound ram from the flock according to the estimated value, for a guilt offering, to the priest. 7 And the priest must make an atonement for him before Jehovah, and so it must be forgiven him regarding any of all the things that he might do resulting in guiltiness by it.”

8 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 9 “Command Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the law of the burnt offering: The burnt offering will be on the hearth upon the altar all night long until the morning, and the fire of the altar will be kindled in it. 10 And the priest must clothe himself with his official dress of linen, and he will put the linen drawers on over his flesh. Then he must lift up the fatty ashes of the burnt offering that the fire regularly consumes upon the altar, and he must place them beside the altar. 11 And he must strip off his garments and put on other garments, and he must take the fatty ashes out to a clean place outside the camp. 12 And the fire on the altar will be kept burning on it. It must not go out. And the priest must burn wood on it morning by morning and set the burnt offering in order over it, and he must make the fatty pieces of the communion sacrifices smoke over it. 13 Fire will be kept constantly burning on the altar. It must not go out.

14 “‘Now this is the law of the grain offering: YOU sons of Aaron, present it before Jehovah in front of the altar. 15 And one of them must lift up by his handful some of the fine flour of the grain offering and some of its oil and all the frankincense that is upon the grain offering, and he must make it smoke upon the altar as a restful odor for a remembrancer of it to Jehovah. 16 And what is left of it Aaron and his sons will eat. It will be eaten as unfermented cakes in a holy place. They will eat it in the courtyard of the tent of meeting. 17 It should not be baked with anything leavened. I have given it as their share out of my offerings made by fire. It is something most holy, like the sin offering and like the guilt offering. 18 Every male among the sons of Aaron will eat it. It is an allowance to time indefinite throughout YOUR generations from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire. Everything that may touch them will become holy.’”

19 And Jehovah went on speaking to Moses, saying: 20 “This is the offering of Aaron and his sons that they will present to Jehovah on the day of his being anointed: the tenth of an e′phah of fine flour as a grain offering constantly, half of it in the morning and half of it in the evening. 21 It will be made with oil upon a griddle. You will bring it well mixed. You will present the pastries of the grain offering in pieces as a restful odor to Jehovah. 22 And the priest, the one anointed in place of him from among his sons, will make it. It is a regulation to time indefinite: As a whole offering it will be made to smoke to Jehovah. 23 And every grain offering of a priest should prove to be a whole offering. It must not be eaten.”

24 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 25 “Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the law of the sin offering: In the place where the burnt offering is regularly slaughtered the sin offering will be slaughtered before Jehovah. It is a most holy thing. 26 The priest who offers it for sin will eat it. In a holy place it will be eaten in the courtyard of the tent of meeting.

27 “‘Everything that may touch its flesh will become holy, and when anyone spatters some of its blood upon the garment, you will wash what he spatters blood upon in a holy place. 28 And the earthenware vessel in which it may be boiled is to be shattered. But if it was boiled in a copper vessel, then it must be scoured and rinsed with water.

29 “‘Every male among the priests will eat it. It is something most holy. 30 However, no sin offering of which some of the blood will be brought into the tent of meeting to make atonement in the holy place must be eaten. It is to be burned with fire.

Leviticus

9 And it came about on the eighth day that Moses called Aaron and his sons and the older men of Israel. 2 Then he said to Aaron: “Take for yourself a young calf for a sin offering and a ram for a burnt offering, sound ones, and present them before Jehovah. 3 But to the sons of Israel you will speak, saying, ‘Take a male goat for a sin offering and a calf and a young ram, each a year old, sound ones, for a burnt offering, 4 and a bull and a ram for communion sacrifices to sacrifice them before Jehovah, and a grain offering moistened with oil, because today is when Jehovah will certainly appear to YOU.’”

5 Accordingly they took what Moses had commanded before the tent of meeting. Then the whole assembly came near and stood before Jehovah. 6 And Moses went on to say: “This is the thing that Jehovah has commanded YOU should do, that the glory of Jehovah may appear to YOU.” 7 Then Moses said to Aaron: “Go near to the altar and render up your sin offering and your burnt offering, and make atonement in your own behalf and in behalf of your house; and render up the offering of the people and make atonement in their behalf, just as Jehovah has commanded.”

8 Aaron immediately went near to the altar and slaughtered the calf of the sin offering that was for him. 9 Then Aaron’s sons presented the blood to him and he dipped his finger in the blood and put it upon the horns of the altar, and the rest of the blood he poured at the base of the altar. 10 And he made the fat and the kidneys and the appendage of the liver from the sin offering smoke upon the altar, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 11 And he burned the flesh and the skin with fire outside the camp.

12 Then he slaughtered the burnt offering and Aaron’s sons handed him the blood and he sprinkled it round about upon the altar. 13 And they handed him the burnt offering in its pieces and the head, and he proceeded to make them smoke upon the altar. 14 Further, he washed the intestines and the shanks and made them smoke upon the burnt offering on the altar.

15 He now went presenting the offering of the people and took the goat of the sin offering that was for the people and slaughtered it and made an offering for sin with it as with the first. 16 Then he presented the burnt offering and handled it according to the regular procedure.

17 He next presented the grain offering and filled his hand with some of it and made it smoke upon the altar, apart from the burnt offering of the morning.

18 After that he slaughtered the bull and the ram of the communion sacrifice that was for the people. Then Aaron’s sons handed him the blood and he sprinkled it round about upon the altar. 19 As for the fatty pieces of the bull and the fat tail of the ram and the fat covering and the kidneys and the appendage of the liver, 20 they now placed the fatty pieces upon the breasts, after which he made the fatty pieces smoke upon the altar. 21 But the breasts and the right leg Aaron waved to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah, just as Moses had commanded.

22 Then Aaron raised his hands toward the people and blessed them and came down from rendering the sin offering and the burnt offering and the communion sacrifices. 23 Finally Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting and came out and blessed the people.

Then Jehovah’s glory appeared to all the people, 24 and fire came out from before Jehovah and began consuming the burnt offering and the fatty pieces upon the altar. When all the people got to see it, they broke out into shouting and went falling upon their faces.

Leviticus

11 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses and Aaron, saying to them: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘This is the living creature that YOU may eat of all the beasts that are upon the earth: 3 Every creature that splits the hoof and forms a cleft in the hoofs and chews the cud among the beasts, that is what YOU may eat.

4 “‘Only this is what YOU must not eat among the chewers of the cud and the splitters of the hoof: the camel, because it is a chewer of the cud but is no splitter of the hoof. It is unclean for YOU. 5 Also the rock badger, because it is a chewer of the cud but does not split the hoof. It is unclean for YOU. 6 Also the hare, because it is a chewer of the cud but it does not have the hoof split. It is unclean for YOU. 7 Also the pig, because it is a splitter of the hoof and a former of a cleft in the hoof, but it itself does not chew the cud. It is unclean for YOU. 8 YOU must not eat any of their flesh, and YOU must not touch their dead body. They are unclean for YOU.

9 “‘This is what YOU may eat of everything that is in the waters: Everything that has fins and scales in the waters, in the seas and in the torrents, those YOU may eat. 10 And everything in the seas and the torrents that has no fins and scales, out of every swarming creature of the waters and out of every living soul that is in the waters, they are a loathsome thing for YOU. 11 Yes, they will become a loathsome thing to YOU. YOU must not eat any of their flesh, and YOU are to loathe their dead body. 12 Everything in the waters that has no fins and scales is a loathsome thing to YOU.

13 “‘And these are what YOU will loathe among the flying creatures. They should not be eaten. They are a loathsome thing: the eagle and the osprey and the black vulture, 14 and the red kite and the black kite according to its kind, 15 and every raven according to its kind, 16 and the ostrich and the owl and the gull and the falcon according to its kind, 17 and the little owl and the cormorant and the long-eared owl, 18 and the swan and the pelican and the vulture, 19 and the stork, the heron according to its kind, and the hoopoe and the bat. 20 Every winged swarming creature that goes on all fours is a loathsome thing to YOU.

21 “‘Only this is what YOU may eat of all the winged swarming creatures that go upon all fours, those that have leaper legs above their feet with which to leap upon the earth. 22 These are the ones of them YOU may eat of: the migratory locust according to its kind, and the edible locust after its kind, and the cricket according to its kind, and the grasshopper according to its kind. 23 And every other winged swarming creature that does have four legs is a loathsome thing to YOU. 24 So by these YOU would make yourselves unclean. Everyone touching their dead bodies will be unclean until the evening. 25 And everyone carrying any of their dead bodies will wash his garments, and he must be unclean until the evening.

26 “‘As for any beast that is a splitter of the hoof but is not a former of a cleft and is not a chewer of the cud, they are unclean for YOU. Everyone touching them will be unclean. 27 As for every creature going upon its paws among all the living creatures that go on all fours, they are unclean to YOU. Everyone touching their dead bodies will be unclean until the evening. 28 And he who carries their dead bodies will wash his garments, and he must be unclean until the evening. They are unclean to YOU.

29 “‘And this is what is unclean to YOU among the swarming creatures that swarm upon the earth: the mole rat and the jerboa and the lizard according to its kind, 30 and the gecko fanfoot and the large lizard and the newt and the sand lizard and the chameleon. 31 These are unclean to YOU among all the swarming creatures. Everyone touching them in their death state will be unclean until the evening.

32 “‘Now anything upon which any of them should fall in its death state will be unclean, whether it be some wooden vessel or a garment or a skin or sackcloth. Any vessel of which some use is made will be put in water, and it must be unclean until the evening and then be clean. 33 As for any earthenware vessel into which any of them should fall, anything that is within it will be unclean, and YOU will smash it. 34 Any sort of food that may be eaten upon which water may come from it will be unclean, and any drink that may be drunk in any vessel will be unclean. 35 And everything upon which any of their dead bodies may fall will be unclean. Whether oven or jar stand, it is to be broken down. They are unclean, and they will become unclean to YOU. 36 Only a spring and a pit of impounded waters will continue clean, but anyone touching their dead bodies will be unclean. 37 And should any of their dead bodies fall upon any seed of a plant that is to be sown, it is clean. 38 But in case water should be put upon seed and something of their dead bodies had fallen upon it, it is unclean to YOU.

39 “‘Now in case any beast that is YOURS for food should die, he who touches its dead body will be unclean until the evening. 40 And he who eats any of its dead body will wash his garments, and he must be unclean until the evening; and he who carries off its dead body will wash his garments, and he must be unclean until the evening. 41 And every swarming creature that swarms upon the earth is a loathsome thing. It must not be eaten. 42 As for any creature that goes upon the belly and any creature that goes on all fours or any great number of feet of all the swarming creatures that swarm upon the earth, YOU must not eat them, because they are a loathsome thing. 43 Do not make YOUR souls loathsome with any swarming creature that swarms, and YOU must not make yourselves unclean by them and actually get unclean by them. 44 For I am Jehovah YOUR God; and YOU must sanctify yourselves and YOU must prove yourselves holy, because I am holy. So YOU must not make YOUR souls unclean by any swarming creature that moves upon the earth. 45 For I am Jehovah who is leading YOU up out of the land of Egypt to prove myself God to YOU; and YOU must prove yourselves holy, because I am holy.

46 “‘This is the law about the beast and the flying creature and every living soul that moves about in the waters and concerning every soul that swarms upon the earth, 47 in order to make a distinction between the unclean and the clean and between the living creature that is eatable and the living creature that may not be eaten.’”

Leviticus

15 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and YOU must say to them, ‘In case any man has a running discharge occur from his genital organ, his discharge is unclean. 3 And this will become his uncleanness by his discharge: Whether his genital organ has flowed with a running discharge or his genital organ is obstructed from his running discharge, it is his uncleanness.

4 “‘Any bed upon which the one having a running discharge may lie down will be unclean, and any article upon which he may sit will be unclean. 5 And a man who may touch his bed should wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 6 And whoever sits upon the article upon which the one having a running discharge was sitting should wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 7 And whoever touches the flesh of the one having a running discharge should wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 8 And in the case of the one who has a running discharge spitting upon someone clean, he must in that case wash his garments and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 9 And any saddle upon which the one having a running discharge was riding will be unclean. 10 And anyone touching anything that happens to be under him will be unclean until the evening; and he who carries them will wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 11 And anyone whom the one having a running discharge might touch when he has not rinsed his hands in water must then wash his garments and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 12 And an earthenware vessel that the one having a running discharge might touch should be smashed; and any wooden vessel should be rinsed with water.

13 “‘Now in case the one having a running discharge would become clean from his running discharge, he must then count for himself seven days for his purification, and he must wash his garments and bathe his flesh in running water; and he must be clean. 14 And on the eighth day he should take for himself two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and he must come before Jehovah to the entrance of the tent of meeting and give them to the priest. 15 And the priest must offer them, the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering; and the priest must make atonement for him before Jehovah concerning his running discharge.

16 “‘Now in case a man has an emission of semen go out from him, he must then bathe all his flesh in water and be unclean until the evening. 17 And any garment and any skin upon which the emission of semen gets to be must be washed with water and be unclean until the evening.

18 “‘As for a woman with whom a man may lie down with an emission of semen, they must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.

19 “‘And in case a woman is having a running discharge, and her running discharge in her flesh proves to be blood, she should continue seven days in her menstrual impurity, and anyone touching her will be unclean until the evening. 20 And anything upon which she may lie down in her menstrual impurity will be unclean, and everything upon which she may sit will be unclean. 21 And anyone touching her bed should wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 22 And anyone touching any article upon which she was sitting should wash his garments, and he must bathe in water and be unclean until the evening. 23 And if it was upon the bed or upon another article that she was sitting, by his touching it he will be unclean until the evening. 24 And if a man lies down with her at all and her menstrual impurity comes to be upon him, he must then be unclean seven days, and any bed upon which he might lie down will be unclean.

25 “‘As for a woman, in case the running discharge of her blood should be flowing many days when it is not the regular time of her menstrual impurity, or in case she should have a flow longer than her menstrual impurity, all the days of her unclean running discharge will prove as in the days of her menstrual impurity. She is unclean. 26 Any bed upon which she may lie any of the days of her running discharge will become for her as the bed of her menstrual impurity, and any article upon which she may sit will become unclean like the uncleanness of her menstrual impurity. 27 And anyone touching them will be unclean, and he must wash his garments and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.

28 “‘However, if she has become clean from her running discharge, she must also count for herself seven days, and afterward she will be clean. 29 And on the eighth day she should take for herself two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and she must bring them to the priest at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 30 And the priest must make the one a sin offering and the other a burnt offering; and the priest must make atonement for her before Jehovah concerning her unclean running discharge.

31 “‘And YOU must keep the sons of Israel separate from their uncleanness, that they may not die in their uncleanness for their defiling of my tabernacle, which is in their midst.

32 “‘This is the law about the man having a running discharge and the man from whom an emission of semen may go out so that he becomes unclean by it; 33 and the menstruating woman in her uncleanness, and anyone who has a flow of his running discharge, whether a male or a female, and whether a man who lies down with an unclean woman.’”

Leviticus

21 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “Talk to the priests, Aaron’s sons, and you must say to them, ‘For a deceased soul no one may defile himself among his people. 2 But for a blood relation of his who is close to him, for his mother and for his father and for his son and for his daughter and for his brother 3 and for his sister, a virgin who is close to him, who has not become a man’s, for her he may defile himself. 4 He may not defile himself for a woman possessed by an owner among his people so as to make himself profane. 5 They should not produce baldness upon their heads, and the extremity of their beard they should not shave, and on their flesh they should not make an incision. 6 They should prove themselves holy to their God, and they should not profane the name of their God, because they are those presenting Jehovah’s offerings made by fire, the bread of their God; and they must prove themselves holy. 7 A prostitute or a violated woman they should not take; and a woman divorced from her husband they should not take, because he is holy to his God. 8 So you must sanctify him, because he is one presenting the bread of your God. He should prove to be holy to you, because I Jehovah, who am sanctifying YOU, am holy.

9 “‘Now in case the daughter of a priest should make herself profane by committing prostitution, it is her father that she is profaning. She should be burned in the fire.

10 “‘And as for the high priest of his brothers upon whose head the anointing oil would be poured and whose hand was filled with power to wear the garments, he should not let his head go ungroomed, and he should not tear his garments. 11 And he should not come to any dead soul. For his father and his mother he may not defile himself. 12 He should also not go out from the sanctuary and not profane the sanctuary of his God, because the sign of dedication, the anointing oil of his God, is upon him. I am Jehovah.

13 “‘And for his part, he should take a woman in her virginity. 14 As for a widow or a divorced woman and one violated, a prostitute, none of these may he take, but he should take a virgin from his people as a wife. 15 And he should not profane his seed among his people, because I am Jehovah who is sanctifying him.’”

16 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 17 “Speak to Aaron, saying, ‘No man of your seed throughout their generations in whom there proves to be a defect may come near to present the bread of his God. 18 In case there is any man in whom there is a defect, he may not come near: a man blind or lame or with his nose slit or with one member too long, 19 or a man in whom there proves to be a fracture of the foot or a fracture of the hand, 20 or hunchback or thin or diseased in his eyes or scabby or having ringworms or having his testicles broken. 21 Any man of the seed of Aaron the priest in whom there is a defect may not approach to present Jehovah’s offerings made by fire. There is a defect in him. He may not approach to present the bread of his God. 22 He may eat the bread of his God from the most holy things and from the holy things. 23 However, he may not come in near the curtain, and he may not approach the altar, because there is a defect in him; and he should not profane my sanctuary, for I am Jehovah who is sanctifying them.’”

24 Accordingly Moses spoke to Aaron and his sons and all the sons of Israel.

Numbers

7 Now it came about on the day that Moses finished setting up the tabernacle that he proceeded to anoint it and to sanctify it and all its furnishings and the altar and all its utensils. Thus he anointed them and sanctified them. 2 Then the chieftains of Israel, the heads of the house of their fathers, made a presentation, they being the chieftains of the tribes and standing over the ones registered, 3 and they brought their offering before Jehovah, six covered wagons and twelve cattle, a wagon for two chieftains and a bull for each one; and they presented them before the tabernacle. 4 At this Jehovah said to Moses: 5 “Accept them from them, as they must serve for carrying on the service of the tent of meeting, and you must give them to the Levites, each one in proportion to his own service.”

6 So Moses accepted the wagons and the cattle and gave them to the Levites. 7 Two wagons and four cattle he gave to the sons of Ger′shon in proportion to their service, 8 and four wagons and eight cattle he gave to the sons of Me·rar′i in proportion to their service, under the hand of Ith′a·mar the son of Aaron the priest. 9 But to the sons of Ko′hath he gave none, because the service of the holy place was upon them. They did their carrying on the shoulder.

10 Now the chieftains made their presentation at the inauguration of the altar on the day of its being anointed, and the chieftains proceeded with presenting their offering before the altar. 11 So Jehovah said to Moses: “One chieftain on one day and another chieftain on another day is the way they will present their offering for the inauguration of the altar.”

12 Now the one presenting his offering on the first day proved to be Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab of the tribe of Judah. 13 And his offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 14 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 15 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 16 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 17 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab.

18 On the second day Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar, the chieftain of Is′sa·char, made a presentation. 19 He presented as his offering one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 20 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 21 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 22 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 23 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar.

24 On the third day there was the chieftain for the sons of Zeb′u·lun, E·li′ab the son of He′lon. 25 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 26 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 27 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 28 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 29 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of E·li′ab the son of He′lon.

30 On the fourth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Reu′ben, E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur. 31 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 32 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 33 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 34 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 35 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur.

36 On the fifth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Sim′e·on, She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai. 37 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 38 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 39 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 40 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 41 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai.

42 On the sixth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Gad, E·li′a·saph the son of Deu′el. 43 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 44 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 45 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 46 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 47 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of E·li′a·saph the son of Deu′el.

48 On the seventh day there was the chieftain for the sons of E′phra·im, E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud. 49 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 50 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 51 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 52 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 53 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud.

54 On the eighth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Ma·nas′seh, Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur. 55 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 56 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 57 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 58 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 59 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur.

60 On the ninth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Benjamin, Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni. 61 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 62 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 63 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 64 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 65 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni.

66 On the tenth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Dan, A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai. 67 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 68 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 69 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 70 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 71 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai.

72 On the eleventh day there was the chieftain for the sons of Ash′er, Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran. 73 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 74 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 75 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 76 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 77 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran.

78 On the twelfth day there was the chieftain for the sons of Naph′ta·li, A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 79 His offering was one silver dish, its weight being a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels by the shekel of the holy place, both of them full of fine flour moistened with oil for a grain offering; 80 one gold cup of ten shekels, full of incense; 81 one young bull, one ram, one male lamb in its first year, for a burnt offering; 82 one kid of the goats for a sin offering; 83 and for a communion sacrifice two cattle, five rams, five he-goats, five male lambs each a year old. This was the offering of A·hi′ra the son of E′nan.

84 This was the inauguration offering of the altar on the day of its being anointed, on the part of the chieftains of Israel: twelve silver dishes, twelve silver bowls, twelve gold cups; 85 a hundred and thirty shekels to each silver dish, and seventy to each bowl, all the silver of the vessels being two thousand four hundred shekels by the shekel of the holy place; 86 the twelve gold cups full of incense being ten shekels respectively to a cup by the shekel of the holy place, all the gold of the cups being a hundred and twenty shekels; 87 all the cattle for the burnt offering being twelve bulls, twelve rams, twelve male lambs each a year old and their grain offerings, and twelve kids of the goats for a sin offering; 88 and all the cattle of the communion sacrifice being twenty-four bulls, sixty rams, sixty he-goats, sixty male lambs each a year old. This was the inauguration offering of the altar after its being anointed.

89 Now whenever Moses went into the tent of meeting to speak with him, then he would hear the voice conversing with him from above the cover that was upon the ark of the testimony, from between the two cherubs; and he would speak to him.

Numbers

9 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses in the wilderness of Si′nai in the second year of their coming out of the land of Egypt, in the first month, saying: 2 “Now the sons of Israel should prepare the passover sacrifice at its appointed time. 3 On the fourteenth day in this month between the two evenings YOU should prepare it at its appointed time. According to all its statutes and all its regular procedures YOU should prepare it.”

4 So Moses spoke to the sons of Israel to prepare the passover sacrifice. 5 Then they prepared the passover sacrifice in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month between the two evenings, in the wilderness of Si′nai. According to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses, so the sons of Israel did.

6 Now there happened to be men who had become unclean by a human soul so that they were not able to prepare the passover sacrifice on that day. Hence they presented themselves before Moses and Aaron on that day. 7 Then those men said to him: “We are unclean by a human soul. Why should we be restrained from presenting the offering to Jehovah at its appointed time in the midst of the sons of Israel?” 8 At this Moses said to them: “Stand there, and let me hear what Jehovah may command regarding YOU.”

9 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 10 “Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘Although any man of YOU or of YOUR generations should happen to be unclean by a soul or off on a distant journey, he too must prepare the passover sacrifice to Jehovah. 11 In the second month, on the fourteenth day between the two evenings, they should prepare it. Together with unfermented cakes and bitter greens they should eat it. 12 They must not let any of it remain until morning, and they should break no bone in it. According to the whole statute of the passover they should prepare it. 13 But when the man was clean or did not happen to be off on a journey and neglected to prepare the passover sacrifice, that soul must then be cut off from his people, because the offering of Jehovah he did not present at its appointed time. For his sin that man will answer.

14 “‘And in case an alien resident should be residing with YOU as an alien, he also must prepare the passover sacrifice to Jehovah. According to the statute of the passover and according to its regular procedure is the way he should do. There should exist one statute for YOU people, both for the alien resident and for the native of the land.’”

15 Now on the day of setting up the tabernacle the cloud covered the tabernacle of the tent of the Testimony, but in the evening what appeared to be fire continued over the tabernacle until morning. 16 That is the way it went on constantly: The cloud would cover it by day, and the appearance of fire by night. 17 And whenever the cloud would go up from over the tent, the sons of Israel would pull away right afterward, and in the place where the cloud would reside, there is where the sons of Israel would encamp. 18 At the order of Jehovah the sons of Israel would pull away, and at the order of Jehovah they would encamp. All the days that the cloud would reside over the tabernacle, they would remain encamped. 19 And when the cloud prolonged its stay over the tabernacle many days, the sons of Israel also kept their obligation to Jehovah that they should not pull away. 20 And sometimes the cloud would continue a few days over the tabernacle. At the order of Jehovah they would remain encamped, and at the order of Jehovah they would pull away. 21 And sometimes the cloud would continue from evening to morning; and the cloud lifted itself in the morning, and they pulled away. Whether it was by day or by night that the cloud lifted itself, they also pulled away. 22 Whether it was two days or a month or more days during which the cloud prolonged its stay over the tabernacle by residing over it, the sons of Israel remained encamped and would not pull away, but when it lifted itself they would pull away. 23 At the order of Jehovah they would encamp, and at the order of Jehovah they would pull away. They kept their obligation to Jehovah at the order of Jehovah by means of Moses.

Numbers

15 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘When YOU eventually come into the land of YOUR dwelling places, which I am giving YOU, 3 and YOU must render up an offering made by fire to Jehovah, a burnt offering or a sacrifice to perform a special vow or voluntarily or during YOUR seasonal festivals, in order to make a restful odor to Jehovah, from the herd or from the flock; 4 the one presenting his offering must also present to Jehovah a grain offering of fine flour, a tenth of an e′phah, moistened with a fourth of a hin of oil. 5 And you should render up wine as a drink offering, the fourth of a hin, together with the burnt offering or for the sacrifice of each male lamb. 6 Or for a ram you should render up a grain offering of two tenths of fine flour, moistened with a third of a hin of oil. 7 And you should present wine as a drink offering, a third of a hin, as a restful odor to Jehovah.

8 “‘But in case you should render up a male of the herd as a burnt offering or a sacrifice to perform a special vow or communion sacrifices to Jehovah, 9 one must also present together with the male of the herd a grain offering of three tenths of fine flour, moistened with half a hin of oil. 10 And you should present wine as a drink offering, half a hin, as an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah. 11 This is the way it should be done for each bull or for each ram or for one head among the male lambs or among the goats. 12 Whatever may be the number that YOU may render up, that is the way YOU should do for each one according to the number of them. 13 Every native should render up these in this way in presenting an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah.

14 “‘And in case there should be residing as an alien with YOU an alien resident or one who is in YOUR midst for generations of YOU, and he must render up an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah, just as YOU should do, so he should do. 15 YOU who are of the congregation and the alien resident who is residing as an alien will have one statute. It will be a statute to time indefinite for YOUR generations. The alien resident should prove to be the same as YOU before Jehovah. 16 There should prove to be one law and one judicial decision for YOU and for the alien resident who is residing as an alien with YOU.’”

17 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 18 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘On YOUR coming into the land where I am bringing YOU, 19 it must also occur that when YOU eat any of the bread of the land, YOU should make a contribution to Jehovah. 20 YOU should make a contribution of the firstfruits of YOUR coarse meal as ring-shaped cakes. Like the contribution of a threshing floor is the way YOU should contribute it. 21 Some of the firstfruits of YOUR coarse meal YOU should give as a contribution to Jehovah throughout YOUR generations.

22 “‘Now in case YOU should make a mistake and not do all these commandments, which Jehovah has spoken to Moses, 23 all that Jehovah has commanded YOU by means of Moses from the day that Jehovah commanded and onward for YOUR generations, 24 it must then occur that if it has been done far from the eyes of the assembly by mistake, the whole assembly must then render up one young bull as a burnt offering for a restful odor to Jehovah, and its grain offering and its drink offering according to the regular procedure, and one kid of the goats as a sin offering. 25 And the priest must make atonement for the whole assembly of the sons of Israel, and it must be forgiven them; because it was a mistake, and they, for their part, brought as their offering an offering made by fire to Jehovah and their sin offering before Jehovah for their mistake. 26 And it must be forgiven the whole assembly of the sons of Israel and the alien resident who is residing as an alien in their midst, because it was by mistake on the part of all the people.

27 “‘And if any soul should sin by mistake, then he must present a female goat in its first year for a sin offering. 28 And the priest must make atonement for the soul who made a mistake by a sin unintentionally before Jehovah, so as to make atonement for it, and it must be forgiven him. 29 As to the native among the sons of Israel and the alien resident who is residing as an alien in their midst, there should prove to be one law for YOU as respects doing something unintentionally.

30 “‘But the soul that does something deliberately, whether he is a native or an alien resident, he speaking abusively of Jehovah, in that case that soul must be cut off from among his people. 31 Because it is Jehovah’s word that he has despised and his commandment that he has broken, that soul should be cut off without fail. His own error is upon him.’”

32 While the sons of Israel were continuing in the wilderness, they once found a man collecting pieces of wood on the sabbath day. 33 Then those who found him collecting pieces of wood brought him up to Moses and Aaron and the whole assembly. 34 So they committed him into custody, because it had not been distinctly stated what should be done to him.

35 In time Jehovah said to Moses: “Without fail the man should be put to death, the whole assembly pelting him with stones outside the camp.” 36 Accordingly the whole assembly brought him forth outside the camp and pelted him with stones so that he died, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

37 And Jehovah went on to say this to Moses: 38 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them that they must make for themselves fringed edges upon the skirts of their garments throughout their generations, and they must put a blue string above the fringed edge of the skirt, 39 ‘And it must serve as a fringed edge for YOU, and YOU must see it and remember all the commandments of Jehovah and do them, and YOU must not go about following YOUR hearts and YOUR eyes, which YOU are following in immoral intercourse. 40 The purpose is that YOU may remember and may certainly do all my commandments and indeed prove to be holy to YOUR God. 41 I am Jehovah YOUR God, who have brought YOU out of the land of Egypt in order to prove myself YOUR God. I am Jehovah YOUR God.’”

Numbers

19 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “This is a statute of the law that Jehovah has commanded, saying, ‘Speak to the sons of Israel that they should take for you a sound red cow in which there is no defect and upon which no yoke has come. 3 And YOU must give it to El·e·a′zar the priest, and he must lead it forth outside the camp, and it must be slaughtered before him. 4 Then El·e·a′zar the priest must take some of its blood with his finger and spatter some of its blood straight toward the front of the tent of meeting seven times. 5 And the cow must be burned under his eyes. Its skin and its flesh and its blood together with its dung will be burned. 6 And the priest must take cedarwood and hyssop and coccus scarlet material and throw it into the midst of the burning of the cow. 7 And the priest must wash his garments and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he may come into the camp; but the priest must be unclean until the evening.

8 “‘And the one who burned it will wash his garments in water and must bathe his flesh in water, and he must be unclean until the evening.

9 “‘And a clean man must gather up the ashes of the cow and deposit them outside the camp in a clean place; and they must serve the assembly of the sons of Israel as something to be kept for the water for cleansing. It is a sin offering. 10 And the one gathering the ashes of the cow must wash his garments and be unclean until the evening.

“‘And it must serve the sons of Israel and the alien resident who is residing as an alien in their midst as a statute to time indefinite. 11 Anyone touching the corpse of any human soul must also be unclean seven days. 12 Such one should purify himself with it on the third day, and on the seventh day he will be clean. But if he will not purify himself on the third day, then on the seventh day he will not be clean. 13 Everyone touching a corpse, the soul of whatever man may die, and who will not purify himself, has defiled Jehovah’s tabernacle, and that soul must be cut off from Israel. Because the water for cleansing has not been sprinkled upon him, he continues unclean. His uncleanness is still upon him.

14 “‘This is the law in case a man should die in a tent: Everyone coming into the tent, and everyone who is in the tent, will be unclean seven days. 15 And every opened vessel upon which there is no lid tied down is unclean. 16 And everyone who on the open field may touch someone slain with the sword or a corpse or a bone of a man or a burial place will be unclean seven days. 17 And they must take for the unclean one some of the dust of the burning of the sin offering and put running water upon it in a vessel. 18 Then a clean man must take hyssop and dip it into the water and spatter it upon the tent and all the vessels and the souls that happened to be there and upon the one who touched the bone or the slain one or the corpse or the burial place. 19 And the clean person must spatter it upon the unclean one on the third day and on the seventh day and must purify him from sin on the seventh day; and he must wash his garments and bathe in water, and he must be clean in the evening.

20 “‘But the man who may be unclean and who will not purify himself, well, that soul must be cut off from the midst of the congregation, because it is Jehovah’s sanctuary that he has defiled. The water for cleansing was not sprinkled upon him. He is unclean.

21 “‘And it must serve as a statute to time indefinite for them, that the one spattering the water for cleansing should wash his garments, also the one touching the water for cleansing. He will be unclean until the evening. 22 And anything the unclean one may touch will be unclean, and the soul who touches it will be unclean until the evening.’”

Numbers

29 “‘And in the seventh month, on the first of the month, YOU should hold a holy convention. No sort of laborious work must YOU do. It should prove to be a day of the trumpet blast for YOU. 2 And YOU must render up as a burnt offering for a restful odor to Jehovah one young bull, one ram, seven male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 3 and their grain offering of fine flour moistened with oil, three tenth measures for the bull, two tenth measures for the ram, 4 and one tenth measure for each male lamb of the seven male lambs; 5 and one male kid of the goats as a sin offering to make atonement for YOU; 6 aside from the monthly burnt offering and its grain offering and the constant burnt offering and its grain offering, together with their drink offerings, according to the regular procedure for them, as a restful odor, an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

7 “‘And on the tenth of this seventh month YOU should hold a holy convention, and YOU must afflict YOUR souls. No sort of work must YOU do. 8 And YOU must present as a burnt offering to Jehovah, as a restful odor, one young bull, one ram, seven male lambs each a year old. They should prove to be sound ones for YOU. 9 And as their grain offering of fine flour moistened with oil three tenth measures for the bull, two tenth measures for the one ram, 10 a tenth measure respectively for each male lamb of the seven male lambs; 11 one kid of the goats as a sin offering, aside from the sin offering of atonement and the constant burnt offering and its grain offering, together with their drink offerings.

12 “‘And on the fifteenth day of the seventh month YOU should hold a holy convention. No sort of laborious work must YOU do, and YOU must celebrate a festival to Jehovah seven days. 13 And YOU must present as a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah, thirteen young bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old. They should prove to be sound ones. 14 And as their grain offering of fine flour moistened with oil three tenth measures for each bull of the thirteen bulls, two tenth measures for each ram of the two rams, 15 and a tenth measure for each male lamb of the fourteen male lambs; 16 and one kid of the goats as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering, its grain offering and its drink offering.

17 “‘And on the second day twelve young bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 18 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 19 and one kid of the goats as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering and its grain offering, together with their drink offerings.

20 “‘And on the third day eleven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 21 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 22 and one goat as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering and its grain offering and its drink offering.

23 “‘And on the fourth day ten bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 24 their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 25 and one kid of the goats as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering, its grain offering and its drink offering.

26 “‘And on the fifth day nine bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 27 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 28 and one goat as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering and its grain offering and its drink offering.

29 “‘And on the sixth day eight bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 30 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 31 and one goat as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering, its grain offering and its drink offerings.

32 “‘And on the seventh day seven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 33 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, the rams and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure for them; 34 and one goat as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering, its grain offering and its drink offering.

35 “‘And on the eighth day YOU should hold a solemn assembly. No sort of laborious work must YOU do. 36 And YOU must present as a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah, one bull, one ram, seven male lambs each a year old, sound ones; 37 and their grain offering and their drink offerings for the bull, the ram and the male lambs by their number according to the regular procedure; 38 and one goat as a sin offering, aside from the constant burnt offering and its grain offering and its drink offering.

39 “‘These YOU will render up to Jehovah at YOUR seasonal festivals, besides YOUR vow offerings and YOUR voluntary offerings as YOUR burnt offerings and YOUR grain offerings and YOUR drink offerings and YOUR communion sacrifices.’” 40 And Moses proceeded to talk to the sons of Israel according to everything that Jehovah had commanded Moses.

Numbers

30 Then Moses spoke to the heads of the tribes of the sons of Israel, saying: “This is the word that Jehovah has commanded: 2 In case a man makes a vow to Jehovah or swears an oath to bind a vow of abstinence upon his soul, he must not violate his word. According to all that has gone out of his mouth he should do.

3 “And in case a woman makes a vow to Jehovah or she does bind herself with a vow of abstinence in the house of her father in her youth, 4 and her father actually hears her vow or her abstinence vow that she has bound upon her soul and her father does keep silent toward her, all her vows must also stand, and every abstinence vow that she has bound upon her soul will stand. 5 But if her father has forbidden her on the day of his hearing all her vows or her abstinence vows that she has bound upon her soul, it will not stand, but Jehovah will forgive her, because her father forbade her.

6 “However, if she at all happens to belong to a husband, and her vow is upon her or the thoughtless promise of her lips that she has bound upon her soul, 7 and her husband actually hears it and keeps silent toward her on the day of his hearing it, her vows must also stand or her abstinence vows that she has bound upon her soul will stand. 8 But if her husband on the day of hearing it forbids her, he has also annulled her vow that was upon her or the thoughtless promise of her lips that she bound upon her soul, and Jehovah will forgive her.

9 “In the case of the vow of a widow or a divorced woman, everything that she has bound upon her soul will stand against her.

10 “However, if it is in the house of her husband that she has vowed or has bound an abstinence vow upon her soul by an oath, 11 and her husband has heard it and has kept silent toward her, he has not forbidden her; and all her vows must stand or any abstinence vow that she has bound upon her soul will stand. 12 But if her husband has totally annulled them on the day of his hearing any expression of her lips as her vows or as an abstinence vow of her soul, they will not stand. Her husband has annulled them, and Jehovah will forgive her. 13 Any vow or any oath of an abstinence vow to afflict the soul, her husband should establish it or her husband should annul it. 14 But if her husband absolutely keeps silent toward her from day to day, he has also established all her vows or all her abstinence vows that are upon her. He has established them because he kept silent toward her on the day of his hearing them. 15 And if he totally annuls them after his hearing them, he also actually bears her error.

16 “These are the regulations that Jehovah commanded Moses as between a husband and his wife, as between a father and his daughter in her youth in the house of her father.”

Numbers

35 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, saying: 2 “Give the sons of Israel the command that they must give the Levites cities to inhabit out of the inheritance of their possession, and they should give the Levites the pasture ground of the cities all around them. 3 And the cities must serve for them to inhabit, while their pasture grounds will serve for their domestic animals and their goods and for all their wild beasts. 4 And the pasture grounds of the cities, which YOU will give the Levites, will be from the wall of the city and out for a thousand cubits all around. 5 And YOU must measure outside the city on the east side two thousand cubits and on the south side two thousand cubits and on the west side two thousand cubits and on the north side two thousand cubits, with the city in the middle. This will serve them as pasture grounds of the cities.

6 “These are the cities that YOU will give to the Levites: six cities of refuge, which YOU will give for the manslayer to flee there, and besides them YOU will give forty-two other cities. 7 All the cities that YOU will give to the Levites will be forty-eight cities, they together with their pasture grounds. 8 The cities that YOU will give will be from the possession of the sons of Israel. From the many YOU will take many, and from the few YOU will take few. Each one, in proportion to his inheritance that he will take as a possession, will give some of his cities to the Levites.”

9 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 10 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘YOU are crossing the Jordan to the land of Ca′naan. 11 And YOU must choose cities convenient for yourselves. As cities of refuge they will serve for YOU, and the manslayer must flee there who fatally strikes a soul unintentionally. 12 And the cities must serve YOU as a refuge from the blood avenger, that the manslayer may not die until he stands before the assembly for judgment. 13 And the cities that YOU will give, the six cities of refuge, will be at YOUR service. 14 Three cities YOU will give on this side of the Jordan, and three cities YOU will give in the land of Ca′naan. As cities of refuge they will serve. 15 For the sons of Israel and for the alien resident and for the settler in the midst of them these six cities will serve as a refuge, for anyone to flee there that fatally strikes a soul unintentionally.

16 “‘Now if it was with an instrument of iron that he has struck him so that he dies, he is a murderer. Without fail the murderer should be put to death. 17 And if it was with a small stone by which he could die that he has struck him so that he dies, he is a murderer. Without fail the murderer should be put to death. 18 And if it was with a small instrument of wood by which he could die that he has struck him so that he dies, he is a murderer. Without fail the murderer should be put to death.

19 “‘The avenger of blood is the one who will put the murderer to death. When he chances upon him he himself will put him to death. 20 And if in hatred he was pushing him or he has thrown at him while lying in wait that he might die, 21 or in enmity he has struck him with his hand that he might die, without fail the striker should be put to death. He is a murderer. The avenger of blood will put the murderer to death when he chances upon him.

22 “‘But if it was unexpectedly without enmity that he has pushed him or has thrown any article toward him without lying in wait, 23 or any stone by which he could die without seeing him or he should cause it to fall upon him, so that he died, while he was not at enmity with him and was not seeking his injury, 24 the assembly must then judge between the striker and the avenger of blood according to these judgments. 25 And the assembly must deliver the manslayer out of the hand of the avenger of blood, and the assembly must return him to his city of refuge to which he had fled, and he must dwell in it until the death of the high priest who was anointed with the holy oil.

26 “‘But if the manslayer without fail goes out of the boundary of his city of refuge to which he may flee, 27 and the avenger of blood does find him outside the boundary of his city of refuge, and the avenger of blood does slay the manslayer, he has no bloodguilt. 28 For he ought to dwell in his city of refuge until the high priest’s death, and after the high priest’s death the manslayer may return to the land of his possession. 29 And these must serve as a statute of judgment for YOU throughout YOUR generations in all YOUR dwelling places.

30 “‘Every fatal striker of a soul should be slain as a murderer at the mouth of witnesses, and one witness may not testify against a soul for him to die. 31 And YOU must take no ransom for the soul of a murderer who is deserving to die, for without fail he should be put to death. 32 And YOU must not take a ransom for one who has fled to his city of refuge, to resume dwelling in the land before the death of the high priest.

33 “‘And YOU must not pollute the land in which YOU are; because it is blood that pollutes the land, and for the land there may be no atonement respecting the blood that has been spilled upon it except by the blood of the one spilling it. 34 And you must not defile the land in which YOU are dwelling, in the midst of which I am residing; for I Jehovah am residing in the midst of the sons of Israel.’”

Deuteronomy

4 “And now, O Israel, listen to the regulations and the judicial decisions that I am teaching YOU to do, in order that YOU may live and may indeed go in and take possession of the land that Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers is giving YOU. 2 YOU must not add to the word that I am commanding YOU, neither must YOU take away from it, so as to keep the commandments of Jehovah YOUR God that I am commanding YOU.

3 “YOUR own eyes are the ones that saw what Jehovah did in the case of the Ba′al of Pe′or, that every man who walked after the Ba′al of Pe′or was the one whom Jehovah your God annihilated from your midst. 4 But YOU who are cleaving to Jehovah YOUR God are all of YOU alive today. 5 See, I have taught YOU regulations and judicial decisions, just as Jehovah my God has commanded me, for YOU to do that way in the midst of the land to which YOU are going to take possession of it. 6 And YOU must keep and do them, because this is wisdom on YOUR part and understanding on YOUR part before the eyes of the peoples who will hear of all these regulations, and they will certainly say, ‘This great nation is undoubtedly a wise and understanding people.’ 7 For what great nation is there that has gods near to it the way Jehovah our God is in all our calling upon him? 8 And what great nation is there that has righteous regulations and judicial decisions like all this law that I am putting before YOU today?

9 “Only watch out for yourself and take good care of your soul, that you may not forget the things that your eyes have seen and that they may not depart from your heart all the days of your life; and you must make them known to your sons and to your grandsons, 10 the day that you stood before Jehovah your God in Ho′reb, when Jehovah said to me, ‘Congregate the people together to me that I may let them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days that they are alive on the soil and that they may teach their sons.’

11 “So YOU people came near and stood at the base of the mountain, and the mountain was burning with fire up to midheaven; there was darkness, cloud and thick gloom. 12 And Jehovah began to speak to YOU out of the middle of the fire. The sound of words was what YOU were hearing, but no form were YOU seeing—nothing but a voice. 13 And he proceeded to state to YOU his covenant, which he commanded YOU to perform—the Ten Words, after which he wrote them upon two tablets of stone. 14 And it was I whom Jehovah commanded at that particular time to teach YOU regulations and judicial decisions, for YOU to do them in the land to which YOU are passing over to take possession of it.

15 “And YOU must take good care of YOUR souls, because YOU did not see any form on the day of Jehovah’s speaking to YOU in Ho′reb out of the middle of the fire, 16 that YOU may not act ruinously and may not really make for yourselves a carved image, the form of any symbol, the representation of male or female, 17 the representation of any beast that is in the earth, the representation of any winged bird that flies in the heavens, 18 the representation of anything moving on the ground, the representation of any fish that is in the waters under the earth; 19 and that you may not raise your eyes to the heavens and indeed see the sun and the moon and the stars, all the army of the heavens, and actually get seduced and bow down to them and serve them, which Jehovah your God has apportioned to all the peoples under the whole heavens. 20 But YOU are the ones Jehovah took that he might bring YOU out of the iron furnace, out of Egypt, to become a people of private ownership to him as at this day.

21 “And Jehovah got incensed at me on YOUR account, so that he swore that I should not cross the Jordan or go into the good land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance. 22 For I am dying in this land. I am not crossing the Jordan, but YOU are crossing, and YOU must take possession of this good land. 23 Watch out for yourselves that YOU may not forget the covenant of Jehovah YOUR God that he concluded with YOU and that YOU do not make for yourselves a carved image, the form of anything about which Jehovah your God has commanded you. 24 For Jehovah your God is a consuming fire, a God exacting exclusive devotion.

25 “In case you become father to sons and grandsons and YOU have resided a long time in the land and do act ruinously and do make a carved image, a form of anything, and do commit evil in the eyes of Jehovah your God so as to offend him, 26 I do take as witnesses against YOU today the heavens and the earth, that YOU will positively perish in a hurry from off the land to which YOU are crossing the Jordan to take possession of it. YOU will not lengthen YOUR days on it, because YOU will positively be annihilated. 27 And Jehovah will certainly scatter YOU among the peoples, and YOU will indeed be let remain few in number among the nations to which Jehovah will drive YOU away. 28 And there YOU will have to serve gods, the product of the hands of man, wood and stone, which cannot see or hear or eat or smell.

29 “If YOU do look for Jehovah your God from there, you will also certainly find him, because you will inquire for him with all your heart and with all your soul. 30 When you are in sore straits and all these words have found you out at the close of the days, then you will have to return to Jehovah your God and to listen to his voice. 31 For Jehovah your God is a merciful God. He will not desert you or bring you to ruin or forget the covenant of your forefathers that he swore to them.

32 “Now ask, please, concerning the former days that occurred before you, from the day that God created man on the earth and from one end of the heavens clear to the other end of the heavens, Was any great thing brought about like this or was anything heard like it? 33 Has any other people heard the voice of God speaking out of the middle of the fire the way you yourself have heard it, and kept on living? 34 Or did God attempt to come to take a nation to himself out of the midst of another nation with provings, with signs and with miracles and with war and with a strong hand and with an outstretched arm and with great fearsomeness like all that Jehovah YOUR God has done for YOU in Egypt before your eyes? 35 You—you have been shown, so as to know that Jehovah is the true God; there is no other besides him. 36 Out of the heavens he made you hear his voice so as to correct you; and upon the earth he made you see his great fire, and his words you heard from the middle of the fire.

37 “And yet you continue to live, because he loved your forefathers so that he chose their seed after them and brought you out of Egypt in his sight with his great power, 38 to drive away nations greater and mightier than you from before you, so as to bring you in, to give you their land as an inheritance as at this day. 39 And you well know today, and you must call back to your heart that Jehovah is the true God in the heavens above and on the earth beneath. There is no other. 40 And you must keep his regulations and his commandments that I am commanding you today, that it may go well with you and your sons after you, and in order that you may lengthen your days on the soil that Jehovah your God is giving you, always.”

41 At that time Moses proceeded to set apart three cities on the side of the Jordan toward the rising of the sun, 42 for the manslayer to flee there who slays his fellow without knowing it, while he was not hating him formerly; and he must flee to one of these cities and live, 43 namely, Be′zer in the wilderness on the tableland for the Reu′ben·ites, and Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad for the Gad′ites, and Go′lan in Ba′shan for the Ma·nas′sites.

44 Now this is the law that Moses set before the sons of Israel. 45 These are the testimonies and the regulations and the judicial decisions that Moses spoke to the sons of Israel on their coming out of Egypt, 46 in the region of the Jordan in the valley in front of Beth-pe′or, in the land of Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, who was dwelling in Hesh′bon, whom Moses and the sons of Israel defeated on their coming out of Egypt. 47 And they went taking possession of his land and of the land of Og the king of Ba′shan, the two kings of the Am′or·ites who were in the region of the Jordan toward the rising of the sun, 48 from A·ro′er, which is on the bank of the torrent valley of Ar′non, up to Mount Si′on, that is to say, Her′mon, 49 and all the Ar′a·bah in the region of the Jordan toward the east, and as far as the sea of the Ar′a·bah at the base of the slopes of Pis′gah.

Deuteronomy

7 “When Jehovah your God at last brings you into the land to which you are going so as to take possession of it, he must also clear away populous nations from before you, the Hit′tites and the Gir′ga·shites and the Am′or·ites and the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, seven nations more populous and mighty than you are. 2 And Jehovah your God will certainly abandon them to you, and you must defeat them. You should without fail devote them to destruction. You must conclude no covenant with them nor show them any favor. 3 And you must form no marriage alliance with them. Your daughter you must not give to his son, and his daughter you must not take for your son. 4 For he will turn your son from following me, and they will certainly serve other gods; and Jehovah’s anger will indeed blaze against YOU, and he will certainly annihilate you in a hurry.

5 “On the other hand, this is what YOU should do to them: Their altars YOU should pull down, and their sacred pillars YOU should break down, and their sacred poles YOU should cut down, and their graven images YOU should burn with fire. 6 For you are a holy people to Jehovah your God. It is you Jehovah your God has chosen to become his people, a special property, out of all the peoples that are on the surface of the ground.

7 “It was not because of YOUR being the most populous of all the peoples that Jehovah showed affection for YOU so that he chose YOU, for YOU were the least of all the peoples. 8 But it was because of Jehovah’s loving YOU, and because of his keeping the sworn statement that he had sworn to YOUR forefathers, that Jehovah brought YOU out with a strong hand, that he might redeem you from the house of slaves, from the hand of Phar′aoh the king of Egypt. 9 And you well know that Jehovah your God is the true God, the faithful God, keeping covenant and loving-kindness in the case of those who love him and those who keep his commandments to a thousand generations, 10 but repaying to his face the one who hates him by destroying him. He will not hesitate toward the one who hates him; he will repay him to his face. 11 And you must keep the commandment and the regulations and the judicial decisions that I am commanding you today by doing them.

12 “And it must occur that, because YOU continue listening to these judicial decisions and YOU do keep them and do carry them out, Jehovah your God must keep toward you the covenant and the loving-kindness about which he swore to your forefathers. 13 And he will certainly love you and bless you and multiply you and bless the fruit of your belly and the fruit of your soil, your grain and your new wine and your oil, the young of your cows and the progeny of your flock, on the soil that he swore to your forefathers to give to you. 14 The most blessed of all the peoples you will become. There will not prove to be in you a male or a female without offspring, nor among your domestic animals. 15 And Jehovah will certainly remove from you every sickness; and as for all the evil diseases of Egypt that you have known, he will not place them upon you, and he will indeed put them upon all those who hate you. 16 And you must consume all the peoples whom Jehovah your God is giving to you. Your eye must not feel sorry for them; and you must not serve their gods, because that will be a snare to you.

17 “In case you say in your heart, ‘These nations are too populous for me. How shall I be able to drive them away?’ 18 you must not be afraid of them. You should by all means remember what Jehovah your God did to Phar′aoh and all Egypt, 19 the great provings that your eyes saw, and the signs and the miracles and the strong hand and the outstretched arm with which Jehovah your God brought you out. That is the way Jehovah your God will do to all the peoples before whom you are afraid. 20 And Jehovah your God will also send the feeling of dejection upon them, until those perish who were let remain and who were concealing themselves from before you. 21 You must not suffer a shock because of them, for Jehovah your God is in your midst, a great and fear-inspiring God.

22 “And Jehovah your God will certainly push these nations away from before you little by little. You will not be allowed to finish them off quickly, for fear the wild beasts of the field may multiply against you. 23 And Jehovah your God will indeed abandon them to you and rout them with a great rout, until they are annihilated. 24 And he will certainly give their kings into your hand, and you must destroy their names from under the heavens. Nobody will take a firm stand against you, until you have exterminated them. 25 The graven images of their gods YOU should burn in the fire. You must not desire the silver and the gold upon them, nor indeed take it for yourself, for fear you may be ensnared by it; for it is a thing detestable to Jehovah your God. 26 And you must not bring a detestable thing into your house and actually become a thing devoted to destruction like it. You should thoroughly loathe it and absolutely detest it, because it is something devoted to destruction.

Deuteronomy

11 “And you must love Jehovah your God and keep your obligation to him and his statutes and his judicial decisions and his commandments always. 2 And YOU well know today (for I do not address YOUR sons who have not known and who have not seen the discipline of Jehovah YOUR God, his greatness, his strong hand and his outstretched arm, 3 nor his signs and his deeds that he did in the midst of Egypt to Phar′aoh the king of Egypt and to all his land; 4 nor what he did to the military forces of Egypt, to his horses and his war chariots against the faces of which he made the waters of the Red Sea overflow when they were chasing after them, and Jehovah proceeded to destroy them till this day; 5 nor what he has done to YOU in the wilderness until YOUR coming to this place; 6 nor what he did to Da′than and A·bi′ram the sons of E·li′ab the son of Reu′ben, when the earth opened its mouth and proceeded to swallow them up and their households and their tents and every existing thing that stepped after them in the midst of all Israel); 7 for YOUR eyes were the ones seeing all the great deeds of Jehovah that he did.

8 “And YOU must keep the whole commandment that I am commanding you today, in order that YOU may grow strong and may indeed enter in and take possession of the land to which YOU are crossing to take possession of it, 9 and in order that YOU may lengthen YOUR days on the soil that Jehovah swore to YOUR forefathers to give to them and their seed, a land flowing with milk and honey.

10 “For the land to which you are going to take possession of it is not like the land of Egypt out of which YOU came, where you used to sow your seed and you had to do irrigating with your foot, like a garden of vegetables. 11 But the land to which YOU are crossing to take possession of it is a land of mountains and valley plains. Of the rain of the heavens it drinks water; 12 a land that Jehovah your God is caring for. The eyes of Jehovah your God are constantly upon it, from the beginning of the year to the close of the year.

13 “And it must occur that if YOU will without fail obey my commandments that I am commanding YOU today so as to love Jehovah YOUR God and to serve him with all YOUR heart and all YOUR soul, 14 I also shall certainly give rain for YOUR land at its appointed time, autumn rain and spring rain, and you will indeed gather your grain and your sweet wine and your oil. 15 And I shall certainly give vegetation in your field for your domestic animals, and you will indeed eat and be satisfied. 16 Watch out for yourselves for fear YOUR heart may be enticed, and YOU do turn aside and worship other gods and bow down to them, 17 and Jehovah’s anger does blaze against YOU, and he does shut up the heavens so that no rain will occur and the ground will not give its produce and YOU have to perish speedily from off the good land that Jehovah is giving YOU.

18 “And YOU must apply these words of mine to YOUR heart and YOUR soul and bind them as a sign upon YOUR hand, and they must serve as a frontlet band between YOUR eyes. 19 YOU must also teach them to YOUR sons, so as to speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. 20 And you must write them upon the doorposts of your house and on your gates, 21 in order that YOUR days and the days of YOUR sons may be many on the soil that Jehovah swore to YOUR forefathers to give to them, as the days of the heavens over the earth.

22 “For if YOU strictly keep all this commandment that I am commanding YOU so as to do it, to love Jehovah YOUR God, to walk in all his ways and to cling to him, 23 Jehovah also must drive away all these nations on account of YOU, and YOU will certainly dispossess nations greater and more numerous than YOU are. 24 Every place on which the sole of YOUR foot will tread will become YOURS. From the wilderness up to Leb′a·non, from the River, the river Eu·phra′tes, to the western sea YOUR boundary will become. 25 No man will make a firm stand against YOU. The dread of YOU and the fear of YOU Jehovah YOUR God will put before the face of all the land on which YOU will tread, just as he has promised YOU.

26 “See, I am putting before YOU today blessing and malediction: 27 the blessing, provided YOU will obey the commandments of Jehovah YOUR God that I am commanding YOU today; 28 and the malediction, if YOU will not obey the commandments of Jehovah YOUR God and YOU do turn aside from the way about which I am commanding YOU today, so as to walk after other gods whom YOU have not known.

29 “And it must occur that when Jehovah your God brings you into the land to which you are going to take possession of it, you must also give the blessing upon Mount Ger′i·zim and the malediction upon Mount E′bal. 30 Are they not on the side of the Jordan toward the direction of the sunset, in the land of the Ca′naan·ites dwelling in the Ar′a·bah, in front of Gil′gal, beside the big trees of Mo′reh? 31 For YOU are crossing the Jordan to go in and take possession of the land that Jehovah YOUR God is giving YOU, and YOU must take possession of it and dwell in it. 32 And YOU must be careful to carry out all the regulations and the judicial decisions that I am putting before YOU today.

Deuteronomy

12 “These are the regulations and the judicial decisions that YOU should be careful to carry out in the land that Jehovah the God of your forefathers will certainly allow you to take possession of, all the days that YOU are alive on the soil. 2 YOU should absolutely destroy all the places where the nations whom YOU are dispossessing have served their gods, on the tall mountains and the hills and under every luxuriant tree. 3 And YOU must pull down their altars and shatter their sacred pillars, and YOU should burn their sacred poles in the fire and cut down the graven images of their gods, and YOU must destroy their names from that place.

4 “YOU must not do that way to Jehovah YOUR God, 5 but to the place that Jehovah YOUR God will choose out of all YOUR tribes to place his name there, to have it reside, YOU will seek, and there you must come. 6 And there YOU must bring YOUR burnt offerings and YOUR sacrifices and YOUR tenth parts and the contribution of YOUR hand and YOUR vow offerings and YOUR voluntary offerings and the firstborn ones of YOUR herd and of YOUR flock. 7 And there YOU must eat before Jehovah YOUR God and rejoice in every undertaking of YOURS, YOU and YOUR households, because Jehovah your God has blessed you.

8 “YOU must not do according to all that we are doing here today, each one whatever is right in his own eyes, 9 because YOU have not yet come into the resting-place and the inheritance that Jehovah your God is giving you. 10 And YOU must cross the Jordan and dwell in the land that Jehovah YOUR God is giving YOU as a possession, and he will certainly give YOU rest from all YOUR enemies round about, and YOU will indeed dwell in security. 11 And it must occur that the place that Jehovah YOUR God will choose to have his name reside there is where YOU will bring all about which I am commanding YOU, YOUR burnt offerings and YOUR sacrifices, YOUR tenth parts and the contribution of YOUR hand and every choice of YOUR vow offerings that YOU will vow to Jehovah. 12 And YOU must rejoice before Jehovah YOUR God, YOU and YOUR sons and YOUR daughters and YOUR man slaves and YOUR slave girls and the Levite who is inside YOUR gates, because he has no share or inheritance with YOU. 13 Watch out for yourself for fear you may offer up your burnt offerings in any other place you may see. 14 But in the place that Jehovah will choose in one of your tribes is where you should offer up your burnt offerings, and there you should do all that I am commanding you.

15 “Only whenever your soul craves it you may slaughter, and you must eat meat according to the blessing of Jehovah your God that he has given you, inside all your gates. The unclean one and the clean one may eat it, like the gazelle and like the stag. 16 Only the blood YOU must not eat. On the earth you should pour it out as water. 17 You will not be allowed to eat inside your gates the tenth part of your grain or of your new wine or of your oil or the firstborn ones of your herd and of your flock or any of your vow offerings that you will vow or your voluntary offerings or the contribution of your hand. 18 But before Jehovah your God you will eat it, in the place that Jehovah your God will choose, you and your son and your daughter and your man slave and your slave girl and the Levite who is inside your gates; and you must rejoice before Jehovah your God in every undertaking of yours. 19 Watch out for yourself that you may not abandon the Levite all your days on your soil.

20 “When Jehovah your God will widen out your territory, just as he has promised you, and you will be certain to say, ‘Let me eat meat,’ because your soul craves to eat meat, whenever your soul craves it you may eat meat. 21 In case the place that Jehovah your God will choose to put his name there should be far away from you, you must then slaughter some of your herd or some of your flock that Jehovah has given you, just as I have commanded you, and you must eat inside your gates whenever your soul craves it. 22 Only in the way that the gazelle and the stag may be eaten, so you may eat it: the unclean one and the clean one together may eat it. 23 Simply be firmly resolved not to eat the blood, because the blood is the soul and you must not eat the soul with the flesh. 24 You must not eat it. You should pour it out upon the ground as water. 25 You must not eat it, in order that it may go well with you and your sons after you, because you will do what is right in Jehovah’s eyes. 26 Merely your holy things that will become yours, and your vow offerings you should carry, and you must come to the place that Jehovah will choose. 27 And you must render up your burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of Jehovah your God; and the blood of your sacrifices should be poured out against the altar of Jehovah your God, but the flesh you may eat.

28 “Watch, and you must obey all these words that I am commanding you, in order that it may go well with you and your sons after you to time indefinite, because you will do what is good and right in the eyes of Jehovah your God.

29 “When Jehovah your God will cut off from before you the nations to whom you are going to dispossess them, you must also dispossess them and dwell in their land. 30 Watch out for yourself for fear you may be entrapped after them, after they have been annihilated from before you, and for fear you may inquire respecting their gods, saying, ‘How was it these nations used to serve their gods? And I, yes, I, will do the same way.’ 31 You must not do that way to Jehovah your God, for everything detestable to Jehovah that he does hate they have done to their gods, for even their sons and their daughters they regularly burn in the fire to their gods. 32 Every word that I am commanding YOU is what YOU should be careful to do. YOU must not add to it nor take away from it.

Deuteronomy

13 “In case a prophet or a dreamer of a dream arises in your midst and does give you a sign or a portent, 2 and the sign or the portent does come true of which he spoke to you, saying, ‘Let us walk after other gods, whom you have not known, and let us serve them,’ 3 you must not listen to the words of that prophet or to the dreamer of that dream, because Jehovah YOUR God is testing YOU to know whether YOU are loving Jehovah YOUR God with all YOUR heart and all YOUR soul. 4 After Jehovah YOUR God YOU should walk, and him YOU should fear, and his commandments YOU should keep, and to his voice YOU should listen, and him YOU should serve, and to him YOU should cling. 5 And that prophet or that dreamer of the dream should be put to death, because he has spoken of revolt against Jehovah YOUR God, who has brought YOU out of the land of Egypt and has redeemed you from the house of slaves, to turn you from the way in which Jehovah your God has commanded you to walk; and you must clear out what is evil from your midst.

6 “In case your brother, the son of your mother, or your son or your daughter or your cherished wife or your companion who is like your own soul, should try to allure you in secrecy, saying, ‘Let us go and serve other gods,’ whom you have not known, neither you nor your forefathers, 7 some of the gods of the peoples who are all around YOU, the ones near you or those far away from you, from one end of the land to the other end of the land, 8 you must not accede to his wish or listen to him, nor should your eye feel sorry for him, nor must you feel compassion, nor cover him protectively; 9 but you should kill him without fail. Your hand first of all should come upon him to put him to death, and the hand of all the people afterward. 10 And you must stone him with stones, and he must die, because he has sought to turn you away from Jehovah your God, who has brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slaves. 11 Then all Israel will hear and become afraid, and they will not do anything like this bad thing again in your midst.

12 “In case you hear it said in one of your cities, which Jehovah your God is giving you to dwell there, 13 ‘Good-for-nothing men have gone out from your midst that they may try to turn away the inhabitants of their city, saying: “Let us go and serve other gods,” whom YOU have not known,’ 14 you must also search and investigate and inquire thoroughly; and if the thing is established as the truth, this detestable thing has been done in your midst, 15 you should without fail strike the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword. Devote it and everything that is in it, and its domestic animals, to destruction at the edge of the sword. 16 And all its spoil you should collect into the middle of its public square, and you must burn in the fire the city and all its spoil as a whole offering to Jehovah your God, and it must become a heap of ruins to time indefinite. It should never be rebuilt. 17 And nothing at all should stick to your hand of the thing made sacred by ban, in order that Jehovah may turn from his burning anger and may indeed give you mercy and he may certainly show you mercy and multiply you, just as he has sworn to your forefathers. 18 For you should listen to the voice of Jehovah your God by keeping all his commandments that I am commanding you today, so as to do what is right in the eyes of Jehovah your God.

Deuteronomy

14 “Sons YOU are of Jehovah YOUR God. YOU must not make cuttings upon yourselves or impose baldness on YOUR foreheads for a dead person. 2 For you are a holy people to Jehovah your God, and Jehovah has chosen you to become his people, a special property, out of all the peoples who are on the surface of the ground.

3 “You must eat no detestable thing of any sort. 4 This is the sort of beast that YOU may eat: the bull, the sheep and the goat, 5 the stag and gazelle and roebuck and wild goat and antelope and wild sheep and chamois; 6 and every beast that splits the hoof and that forms a cleft into two hoofs, chewing the cud among the beasts. It YOU may eat. 7 Only this sort YOU must not eat out of those that chew the cud or that split the hoof, cloven: the camel and the hare and the rock badger, because they are chewers of the cud but do not split the hoof. They are unclean for YOU. 8 The pig also, because it is a splitter of the hoof but there is no cud. It is unclean for YOU. None of their flesh must YOU eat, and their carcasses YOU must not touch.

9 “This sort out of everything that is in the waters YOU may eat: Everything that has fins and scales YOU may eat. 10 And everything that has no fins and scales YOU must not eat. It is unclean for YOU.

11 “Any clean bird YOU may eat. 12 But these are the ones of which YOU must not eat: the eagle and the osprey and the black vulture, 13 and the red kite and the black kite and the glede according to its kind; 14 and every raven according to its kind; 15 and the ostrich and the owl and the gull and the falcon according to its kind; 16 the little owl and the long-eared owl and the swan, 17 and the pelican and the vulture and the cormorant, 18 and the stork and the heron according to its kind, and the hoopoe and the bat. 19 And every winged swarming creature is unclean for YOU. They should not be eaten. 20 Any clean flying creature YOU may eat.

21 “YOU must not eat any body already dead. To the alien resident who is inside your gates you may give it, and he must eat it; or there may be a selling of it to a foreigner, because you are a holy people to Jehovah your God.

“You must not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.

22 “Without fail you should give a tenth of all the produce of your seed, that which comes forth of the field year by year. 23 And before Jehovah your God, in the place that he will choose to have his name reside there, you must eat the tenth part of your grain, your new wine and your oil and the firstborn ones of your herd and of your flock; in order that you may learn to fear Jehovah your God always.

24 “Now in case the journey should be too long for you, because you will not be able to carry it, since the place that Jehovah your God will choose to place his name there will be too far away for you, (because Jehovah your God will bless you,) 25 you must then turn it into money, and you must wrap the money up in your hand and travel to the place that Jehovah your God will choose. 26 You must also give the money for whatever your soul may crave in the way of cattle and sheep and goats and wine and intoxicating liquor and anything that your soul may ask of you; and you must eat there before Jehovah your God and rejoice, you and your household. 27 And the Levite who is inside your gates, you must not abandon him, for he has no share or inheritance with you.

28 “At the end of three years you will bring out the entire tenth part of your produce in that year, and you must deposit it inside your gates. 29 And the Levite, because he has no share or inheritance with you, and the alien resident and the fatherless boy and the widow, who are inside your gates, must come, and they must eat and satisfy themselves; in order that Jehovah your God may bless you in every deed of your hand that you will do.

Deuteronomy

16 “Let there be an observing of the month of A′bib, and you must celebrate the passover to Jehovah your God, because in the month of A′bib Jehovah your God brought you out of Egypt by night. 2 And you must sacrifice the passover to Jehovah your God, of the flock and of the herd, in the place that Jehovah will choose to have his name reside there. 3 You must eat nothing leavened along with it for seven days. You should eat along with it unfermented cakes, the bread of affliction, because it was in haste that you came out of the land of Egypt, that you may remember the day of your coming out of the land of Egypt all the days of your life. 4 And no sourdough should be seen with you in all your territory seven days, neither should any of the flesh, which you will sacrifice in the evening on the first day, stay all night until the morning. 5 You will not be allowed to sacrifice the passover in any one of your cities that Jehovah your God is giving you. 6 But at the place that Jehovah your God will choose to have his name reside there, you should sacrifice the passover in the evening as soon as the sun sets, at the appointed time of your coming out of Egypt. 7 And you must do the cooking and the eating in the place that Jehovah your God will choose, and in the morning you must turn around and go to your own tents. 8 Six days you should eat unfermented cakes; and on the seventh day there will be a solemn assembly to Jehovah your God. You must do no work.

9 “Seven weeks you should count for yourself. From when the sickle is first put to the standing grain you will start to count seven weeks. 10 Then you must celebrate the festival of weeks to Jehovah your God, according to the voluntary offering of your hand that you will give, just as Jehovah your God may bless you. 11 And you must rejoice before Jehovah your God, you and your son and your daughter and your man slave and your slave girl and the Levite who is inside your gates and the alien resident and the fatherless boy and the widow, who are in your midst, in the place that Jehovah your God will choose to have his name reside there. 12 And you must remember that you became a slave in Egypt, and you must observe and carry out these regulations.

13 “The festival of booths you should celebrate for yourself seven days when you make an ingathering from your threshing floor and your oil and winepress. 14 And you must rejoice during your festival, you and your son and your daughter and your man slave and your slave girl and the Levite and the alien resident and the fatherless boy and the widow, who are inside your gates. 15 Seven days you will celebrate the festival to Jehovah your God in the place that Jehovah will choose, because Jehovah your God will bless you in all your produce and in every deed of your hand, and you must become nothing but joyful.

16 “Three times in the year every male of yours should appear before Jehovah your God in the place that he will choose: in the festival of the unfermented cakes and in the festival of weeks and in the festival of booths, and none should appear before Jehovah empty-handed. 17 The gift of each one’s hand should be in proportion to the blessing of Jehovah your God that he has given you.

18 “You should set judges and officers for yourself inside all your gates that Jehovah your God is giving you by your tribes, and they must judge the people with righteous judgment. 19 You must not pervert judgment. You must not be partial or accept a bribe, for the bribe blinds the eyes of wise ones and distorts the words of righteous ones. 20 Justice—justice you should pursue, in order that you may keep alive and may indeed take possession of the land that Jehovah your God is giving you.

21 “You must not plant for yourself any sort of tree as a sacred pole near the altar of Jehovah your God that you will make for yourself.

22 “Neither should you set up for yourself a sacred pillar, a thing Jehovah your God hates indeed.

Deuteronomy

20 “In case you go out to the battle against your enemies and you actually see horses and war chariots, a people more numerous than you, you must not be afraid of them; for Jehovah your God is with you, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt. 2 And it must occur that when YOU have drawn near to the battle, the priest must also approach and speak to the people. 3 And he must say to them, ‘Hear, O Israel, YOU are drawing near today to the battle against YOUR enemies. Do not let YOUR hearts be timid. Do not be afraid and run in panic or shudder because of them, 4 for Jehovah YOUR God is marching with YOU to fight for YOU against YOUR enemies so as to save YOU.’

5 “The officers too must speak to the people, saying, ‘Who is the man that has built a new house and has not inaugurated it? Let him go and return to his house, for fear he may die in the battle and another man should inaugurate it. 6 And who is the man that has planted a vineyard and not begun to use it? Let him go and return to his house, for fear he may die in the battle and another man should begin to use it. 7 And who is the man that has become engaged to a woman and has not taken her? Let him go and return to his house, for fear he may die in the battle and another man should take her.’ 8 And the officers must speak further to the people and say, ‘Who is the man that is fearful and fainthearted? Let him go and return to his house, that he may not cause the hearts of his brothers to melt as his own heart.’ 9 And it must occur that when the officers have finished speaking to the people, they must also appoint chiefs of the armies at the head of the people.

10 “In case you draw near to a city to fight against it, you must also announce to it terms of peace. 11 And it must occur that if it gives a peaceful answer to you and it has opened up to you, it must even occur that all the people found in it should become yours for forced labor, and they must serve you. 12 But if it does not make peace with you, and it actually makes war with you and you have to besiege it, 13 Jehovah your God also will certainly give it into your hand, and you must strike every male in it with the edge of the sword. 14 Only the women and the little children and the domestic animals and everything that happens to be in the city, all its spoil you will plunder for yourself; and you must eat the spoil of your enemies, whom Jehovah your God has given to you.

15 “That is the way you will do to all the cities very far away from you that are not of the cities of these nations. 16 It is only of the cities of these peoples that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance that you must not preserve any breathing thing alive, 17 because you should without fail devote them to destruction, the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites, the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, just as Jehovah your God has commanded you; 18 in order that they may not teach YOU to do according to all their detestable things, which they have done to their gods, and YOU may indeed sin against Jehovah YOUR God.

19 “In case you lay siege to a city many days by fighting against it so as to capture it, you must not ruin its trees by wielding an ax against them; for you should eat from them, and you must not cut them down, for is the tree of the field a man to be besieged by you? 20 Only a tree that you know is not a tree for food, it is the one you should ruin, and you must cut it down and build siegeworks against the city that is making war with you, until it falls.

Deuteronomy

23 “No man castrated by crushing the testicles or having his male member cut off may come into the congregation of Jehovah.

2 “No illegitimate son may come into the congregation of Jehovah. Even to the tenth generation none of his may come into the congregation of Jehovah.

3 “No Am′mon·ite or Mo′ab·ite may come into the congregation of Jehovah. Even to the tenth generation none of theirs may come into the congregation of Jehovah to time indefinite, 4 for the reason that they did not come to YOUR aid with bread and water in the way when YOU were going out of Egypt, and because they hired against you Ba′laam the son of Be′or from Pe′thor of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a to call down evil upon you. 5 And Jehovah your God did not want to listen to Ba′laam; but Jehovah your God in your behalf changed the malediction into a blessing, because Jehovah your God loved you. 6 You must not work for their peace and their prosperity all your days to time indefinite.

7 “You must not detest an E′dom·ite, for he is your brother.

“You must not detest an Egyptian, for you became an alien resident in his country. 8 The sons that may be born to them as the third generation may come for themselves into the congregation of Jehovah.

9 “In case you go out into camp against your enemies, you must also keep yourself from every bad thing. 10 In case there happens to be in you a man who does not continue clean, because of a pollution that occurs at night, he must also go outside the camp. He may not come into the midst of the camp. 11 And it must occur that at the falling of evening he should wash with water, and at the setting of the sun he may come into the midst of the camp. 12 And a private place should be at your service outside the camp, and you must go out there. 13 And a peg should be at your service along with your implements, and it must occur that when you squat outside, you must also dig a hole with it and turn and cover your excrement. 14 For Jehovah your God is walking about within your camp to deliver you and to abandon your enemies to you; and your camp must prove to be holy, that he may see nothing indecent in you and certainly turn away from accompanying you.

15 “You must not hand over a slave to his master when he escapes from his master to you. 16 With you he will keep on dwelling in among you in whatever place he may choose in one of your cities, wherever he likes. You must not maltreat him.

17 “None of the daughters of Israel may become a temple prostitute, neither may anyone of the sons of Israel become a temple prostitute. 18 You must not bring the hire of a harlot or the price of a dog into the house of Jehovah your God for any vow, because they are something detestable to Jehovah your God, even both of them.

19 “You must not make your brother pay interest, interest on money, interest on food, interest on anything on which one may claim interest. 20 You may make a foreigner pay interest, but your brother you must not make pay interest; in order that Jehovah your God may bless you in every undertaking of yours on the land to which you are going so as to take possession of it.

21 “In case you vow a vow to Jehovah your God, you must not be slow about paying it, because Jehovah your God will without fail require it of you, and it would indeed become a sin on your part. 22 But in case you omit making a vow, it will not become a sin on your part. 23 The utterance of your lips you should keep, and you must do just as you have vowed to Jehovah your God as a voluntary offering that you spoke of with your mouth.

24 “In case you go into the vineyard of your fellowman, you must eat only enough grapes for you to satisfy your soul, but you must not put any into a receptacle of yours.

25 “In case you go into the standing grain of your fellowman, you must pluck off only the ripe ears with your hand, but the sickle you must not swing to and fro upon the standing grain of your fellowman.

Deuteronomy

24 “In case a man takes a woman and does make her his possession as a wife, it must also occur that if she should find no favor in his eyes because he has found something indecent on her part, he must also write out a certificate of divorce for her and put it in her hand and dismiss her from his house. 2 And she must go out of his house and go and become another man’s. 3 If the latter man has come to hate her and has written out a certificate of divorce for her and put it in her hand and dismissed her from his house, or in case the latter man who took her as his wife should die, 4 the first owner of her who dismissed her will not be allowed to take her back again to become his wife after she has been defiled; for that is something detestable before Jehovah, and you must not lead the land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance into sin.

5 “In case a man takes a new wife, he should not go out into the army, nor should anything else be imposed onto him. He should continue exempt at his house for one year, and he must make his wife whom he has taken rejoice.

6 “No one should seize a hand mill or its upper grindstone as a pledge, because it is a soul that he is seizing as a pledge.

7 “In case a man is found kidnapping a soul of his brothers of the sons of Israel, and he has dealt tyrannically with him and sold him, that kidnapper must also die. And you must clear away what is bad from your midst.

8 “Be on your guard in the plague of leprosy to take good care and do according to all that the priests, the Levites, will instruct YOU. Just as I have commanded them, YOU should be careful to do. 9 There should be a remembering of what Jehovah your God did to Mir′i·am in the way when YOU were coming out of Egypt.

10 “In case you lend your fellowman a loan of any sort, you must not enter into his house to take from him what he has pledged. 11 You should stand on the outside, and the man to whom you are making a loan should bring the pledge outside to you. 12 And if the man is in trouble, you must not go to bed with his pledge. 13 You should by all means return the pledge to him as soon as the sun sets, and he must go to bed in his garment, and he must bless you; and it will mean righteousness for you before Jehovah your God.

14 “You must not defraud a hired laborer who is in trouble and poor, whether of your brothers or of your alien residents who are in your land, within your gates. 15 In his day you should give him his wages, and the sun should not set upon them, because he is in trouble and is lifting up his soul to his wages; that he may not cry out to Jehovah against you, and it must become sin on your part.

16 “Fathers should not be put to death on account of children, and children should not be put to death on account of fathers. Each one should be put to death for his own sin.

17 “You must not pervert the judgment of the alien resident or of the fatherless boy, and you must not seize the garment of a widow as a pledge. 18 And you must remember that you became a slave in Egypt, and Jehovah your God proceeded to redeem you from there. That is why I am commanding you to do this thing.

19 “In case you reap your harvest in your field, and you have forgotten a sheaf in the field, you must not go back to get it. It should stay for the alien resident, for the fatherless boy and for the widow; in order that Jehovah your God may bless you in every deed of your hand.

20 “In case you beat your olive tree, you must not go over its boughs following up yourself. It should stay for the alien resident, for the fatherless boy and for the widow.

21 “In case you gather the grapes of your vineyard, you must not gather the leftovers following up yourself. They should stay for the alien resident, for the fatherless boy and for the widow. 22 And you must remember that you became a slave in the land of Egypt. That is why I am commanding you to do this thing.

Deuteronomy

26 “And it must occur that when at last you enter into the land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance, and you have taken possession of it and dwelt in it, 2 you must also take some of the firstfruits of all the fruitage of the soil, which you will bring in from the land of yours that Jehovah your God is giving you, and you must put them in a basket and go to the place that Jehovah your God will choose to have his name reside there. 3 And you must come to the priest who will be acting in those days and say to him, ‘I must report today to Jehovah your God that I have come into the land that Jehovah swore to our forefathers to give to us.’

4 “And the priest must take the basket out of your hand and deposit it before the altar of Jehovah your God. 5 And you must answer and say before Jehovah your God, ‘My father was a perishing Syrian; and he proceeded to go down to Egypt and to reside there as an alien with very few in number; but there he became a great nation, mighty and numerous. 6 And the Egyptians went treating us badly and afflicting us and putting hard slavery upon us. 7 And we began to cry out to Jehovah the God of our forefathers, and Jehovah proceeded to hear our voice and to look on our affliction and our trouble and our oppression. 8 Finally Jehovah brought us out of Egypt with a strong hand and an outstretched arm and with great fearsomeness and with signs and miracles. 9 Then he brought us to this place and gave us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey. 10 And now here I have brought the firstfruits of the fruitage of the ground that Jehovah has given me.’

“You must also deposit it before Jehovah your God and bow down before Jehovah your God. 11 And you must rejoice over all the good that Jehovah your God has given you and your household, you and the Levite and the alien resident who is in your midst.

12 “When you finish with tithing the entire tenth of your produce in the third year, the year of the tenth, you must also give it to the Levite, the alien resident, the fatherless boy and the widow, and they must eat it within your gates and satisfy themselves. 13 And you must say before Jehovah your God, ‘I have cleared away what is holy from the house and I have also given it to the Levite and the alien resident, the fatherless boy and the widow, in accord with all your commandment that you have commanded me. I have not overstepped your commandments, nor have I forgotten. 14 I have not eaten of it during my mourning, nor have I removed any of it while unclean, nor have I given any of it for anyone dead. I have listened to the voice of Jehovah my God. I have done in accord with all that you have commanded me. 15 Do look down from your holy dwelling, the heavens, and bless your people Israel and the soil that you have given us, just as you swore to our forefathers, the land flowing with milk and honey.’

16 “This day Jehovah your God is commanding you to carry out these regulations and judicial decisions; and you must observe and carry them out with all your heart and all your soul. 17 Jehovah you have induced to say today that he will become your God while you walk in his ways and observe his regulations and his commandments and his judicial decisions and listen to his voice. 18 As for Jehovah, he has induced you to say today that you will become his people, a special property, just as he has promised you, and that you will observe all his commandments, 19 and that he will put you high above all the other nations that he has made, resulting in praise and reputation and beauty, while you prove yourself a people holy to Jehovah your God, just as he has promised.”

Deuteronomy

28 “And it must occur that if you will without fail listen to the voice of Jehovah your God by being careful to do all his commandments that I am commanding you today, Jehovah your God also will certainly put you high above all other nations of the earth. 2 And all these blessings must come upon you and overtake you, because you keep listening to the voice of Jehovah your God:

3 “Blessed will you be in the city, and blessed will you be in the field.

4 “Blessed will be the fruit of your belly and the fruit of your ground and the fruit of your domestic beast, the young of your cattle and the progeny of your flock.

5 “Blessed will be your basket and your kneading trough.

6 “Blessed will you be when you come in, and blessed will you be when you go out.

7 “Jehovah will cause your enemies who rise up against you to be defeated before you. By one way they will come out against you, but by seven ways they will flee before you. 8 Jehovah will decree for you the blessing on your stores of supply and every undertaking of yours, and he will certainly bless you in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you. 9 Jehovah will establish you as a holy people to himself, just as he swore to you, because you continue to keep the commandments of Jehovah your God, and you have walked in his ways. 10 And all the peoples of the earth will have to see that Jehovah’s name has been called upon you, and they will indeed be afraid of you.

11 “Jehovah will also make you overflow indeed with prosperity in the fruit of your belly and the fruit of your domestic animals and the fruitage of your ground, on the ground that Jehovah swore to your forefathers to give you. 12 Jehovah will open up to you his good storehouse, the heavens, to give the rain on your land in its season and to bless every deed of your hand; and you will certainly lend to many nations, while you yourself will not borrow. 13 And Jehovah will indeed put you at the head and not at the tail; and you must come to be only on top, and you will not come to be on the bottom, because you keep obeying the commandments of Jehovah your God, which I am commanding you today to observe and to do. 14 And you must not turn aside from all the words that I am commanding YOU today, to the right or to the left, to walk after other gods to serve them.

15 “And it must occur that if you will not listen to the voice of Jehovah your God by taking care to do all his commandments and his statutes that I am commanding you today, all these maledictions must also come upon you and overtake you:

16 “Cursed will you be in the city, and cursed will you be in the field.

17 “Cursed will be your basket and your kneading trough.

18 “Cursed will be the fruit of your belly and the fruitage of your ground, the young of your cattle and the progeny of your flock.

19 “Cursed will you be when you come in, and cursed will you be when you go out.

20 “Jehovah will send upon you the curse, confusion and rebuke in every undertaking of yours that you try to carry out, until you have been annihilated and have perished in a hurry, because of the badness of your practices in that you have forsaken me. 21 Jehovah will cause the pestilence to cling to you until he has exterminated you from off the ground to which you are going to take possession of it. 22 Jehovah will strike you with tuberculosis and burning fever and inflammation and feverish heat and the sword and scorching and mildew, and they will certainly pursue you until you have perished. 23 Your skies that are over your head must also become copper, and the earth that is beneath you iron. 24 Jehovah will give powder and dust as the rain of your land. From the heavens it will come down upon you until you have been annihilated. 25 Jehovah will cause you to be defeated before your enemies. By one way you will go out against them, but by seven ways you will flee before them; and you must become a frightful object to all the earth’s kingdoms. 26 And your dead body must become food for every flying creature of the heavens and to the beast of the field, with no one to make them tremble.

27 “Jehovah will strike you with the boil of Egypt and piles and eczema and skin eruption, from which you will not be able to be healed. 28 Jehovah will strike you with madness and loss of sight and bewilderment of heart. 29 And you will indeed become one who gropes about at midday, just as a blind man gropes about in the gloom, and you will not make your ways successful; and you must become only one who is always defrauded and robbed, with no one to save you. 30 You will become engaged to a woman, but another man will rape her. You will build a house, but you will not dwell in it. You will plant a vineyard, but you will not begin to use it. 31 Your bull slaughtered there before your eyes—but you will not eat any of it. Your ass taken in robbery from before your face—but it will not return to you. Your sheep given to your enemies—but you will have no savior. 32 Your sons and your daughters given to another people and your eyes looking on and yearning for them always—but your hands will be without power. 33 The fruitage of your ground and all your production a people will eat whom you have not known; and you must become one who is only defrauded and crushed always. 34 And you will certainly become maddened at the sight of your eyes that you will see.

35 “Jehovah will strike you with a malignant boil upon both knees and both legs, from which you will not be able to be healed, from the sole of your foot to the crown of your head. 36 Jehovah will march you and your king whom you will set up over you to a nation whom you have not known, neither you nor your forefathers; and there you will have to serve other gods, of wood and of stone. 37 And you must become an object of astonishment, a proverbial saying and a taunt among all the peoples to whom Jehovah will lead you away.

38 “A lot of seed you will take out to the field, but little will you gather, because the locust will devour it. 39 Vineyards you will plant and certainly cultivate, but you will drink no wine and gather nothing in, because the worm will eat it up. 40 You will come to have olive trees in all your territory, but you will rub yourself with no oil, because your olives will drop off. 41 Sons and daughters you will bring forth, but they will not continue yours, because they will go off into captivity. 42 All your trees and the fruitage of your ground whirring insects will take in possession. 43 The alien resident who is in your midst will keep ascending higher and higher above you, while you—you will keep descending lower and lower. 44 He will be the one to lend to you, while you—you will not lend to him. He will become the head, while you—you will become the tail.

45 “And all these maledictions will certainly come upon you and pursue you and overtake you until you have been annihilated, because you did not listen to the voice of Jehovah your God by keeping his commandments and his statutes that he commanded you. 46 And they must continue on you and your offspring as a sign and a portent to time indefinite, 47 due to the fact that you did not serve Jehovah your God with rejoicing and joy of heart for the abundance of everything. 48 And you will have to serve your enemies whom Jehovah will send against you with hunger and thirst and nakedness and the want of everything; and he will certainly put an iron yoke upon your neck until he has annihilated you.

49 “Jehovah will raise up against you a nation far away, from the end of the earth, just as an eagle pounces, a nation whose tongue you will not understand, 50 a nation fierce in countenance, who will not be partial to an old man or show favor to a young man. 51 And they will certainly eat the fruit of your domestic animals and the fruitage of your ground until you have been annihilated, and they will let no grain, new wine or oil, no young of your cattle or progeny of your flock, remain for you until they have destroyed you. 52 And they will indeed besiege you within all your gates until your high and fortified walls in which you are trusting fall in all your land, yes, they will certainly besiege you within all your gates in all your land, which Jehovah your God has given you. 53 Then you will have to eat the fruit of your belly, the flesh of your sons and your daughters, whom Jehovah your God has given you, because of the tightness and stress with which your enemy will hem you in.

54 “As for the very delicate and dainty man among you, his eye will be evil-inclined toward his brother and his cherished wife and the remainder of his sons whom he has remaining, 55 so as not to give one of them any of the flesh of his sons that he will eat, because he has nothing at all remaining to him because of the tightness and stress with which your enemy will hem you in within all your gates. 56 As for the delicate and dainty woman among you who never attempted to set the sole of her foot upon the earth for being of dainty habit and for delicateness, her eye will be evil-inclined toward her cherished husband and her son and her daughter, 57 even toward her afterbirth that comes out from between her legs and toward her sons whom she proceeded to bear, because she will eat them in secrecy for the want of everything because of the tightness and stress with which your enemy will hem you in within your gates.

58 “If you will not take care to carry out all the words of this law that are written in this book so as to fear this glorious and fear-inspiring name, even Jehovah, your God, 59 Jehovah also will certainly make your plagues and the plagues of your offspring especially severe, great and long-lasting plagues, and malignant and long-lasting sicknesses. 60 And he will indeed bring back upon you all the diseases of Egypt before which you got scared, and they will certainly hang onto you. 61 Also, any sickness and any plague that is not written in the book of this law, Jehovah will bring them upon you until you have been annihilated. 62 And YOU will indeed be left with very few in number, although YOU have become like the stars of the heavens for multitude, because you did not listen to the voice of Jehovah your God.

63 “And it must occur that just as Jehovah exulted over YOU to do YOU good and to multiply YOU, so Jehovah will exult over YOU to destroy YOU and to annihilate YOU; and YOU will simply be torn away from off the soil to which you are going to take possession of it.

64 “And Jehovah will certainly scatter you among all the peoples from the one end of the earth to the other end of the earth, and there you will have to serve other gods whom you have not known, neither you nor your forefathers, wood and stone. 65 And among those nations you will have no ease, nor will there prove to be any resting-place for the sole of your foot; and Jehovah will indeed give you there a trembling heart and a failing of the eyes and despair of soul. 66 And you will certainly be in the greatest peril for your life and be in dread night and day, and you will not be sure of your life. 67 In the morning you will say, ‘If it only were evening!’ and in the evening you will say, ‘If it only were morning!’ because of the dread of your heart with which you will be in dread and because of the sight of your eyes that you will see. 68 And Jehovah will certainly bring you back to Egypt by ships by the way about which I have said to you, ‘You will never see it again,’ and YOU will have to sell yourselves there to your enemies as slave men and maidservants, but there will be no buyer.”

Deuteronomy

29 These are the words of the covenant that Jehovah commanded Moses to conclude with the sons of Israel in the land of Mo′ab aside from the covenant that he had concluded with them in Ho′reb.

2 And Moses proceeded to call all Israel and to say to them: “YOU were the ones seeing all that Jehovah did before YOUR eyes in the land of Egypt to Phar′aoh and all his servants and all his land, 3 the great provings that your eyes saw, those great signs and miracles. 4 And yet Jehovah has not given YOU a heart to know and eyes to see and ears to hear down to this day. 5 ‘While I kept guiding YOU forty years in the wilderness, YOUR garments did not wear out upon YOU, and your sandal did not wear out upon your foot. 6 Bread YOU did not eat, and wine and intoxicating liquor YOU did not drink, in order that YOU might know that I am Jehovah YOUR God.’ 7 Eventually YOU came to this place, and Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon and Og the king of Ba′shan proceeded to come out to meet us in battle, but we defeated them. 8 After that we took their land and gave it as an inheritance to the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites and half the tribe of the Ma·nas′sites. 9 So YOU must keep the words of this covenant and do them, in order that YOU may make everything YOU will do turn out well.

10 “YOU are all of YOU stationed today before Jehovah YOUR God, the heads of YOUR tribes, YOUR older men and YOUR officers, every man of Israel, 11 YOUR little ones, YOUR wives, and your alien resident who is in the midst of your camp, from the gatherer of your wood to the drawer of your water, 12 in order for you to enter into the covenant of Jehovah your God and his oath, which Jehovah your God is concluding with you today; 13 for the purpose of establishing you today as his people and that he may prove himself your God, just as he has promised you and just as he has sworn to your forefathers Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.

14 “Now it is not with YOU alone that I am concluding this covenant and this oath, 15 but it is with him who is here standing with us today before Jehovah our God and with those who are not here with us today; 16 (for YOU yourselves well know how we dwelt in the land of Egypt and how we passed through the midst of the nations through whom YOU passed. 17 And YOU used to see their disgusting things and their dungy idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, that were with them;) 18 that there may not be among YOU a man or a woman or a family or a tribe whose heart is turning today away from Jehovah our God to go and serve the gods of those nations; that there may not be among YOU a root bearing the fruit of a poisonous plant and wormwood.

19 “And it must occur that when someone has heard the words of this oath, and he has blessed himself in his heart, saying, ‘I shall come to have peace, although I shall walk in the stubbornness of my heart,’ with the intention of sweeping away the well-watered one along with the thirsty one, 20 Jehovah will not want to forgive him, but then Jehovah’s anger and his ardor will smoke against that man, and all the oath written in this book will certainly settle down on him, and Jehovah will indeed wipe out his name from under the heavens. 21 So Jehovah will have to separate him for calamity from all the tribes of Israel in accord with all the oath of the covenant that is written in this book of the law.

22 “And the future generation, YOUR sons who will rise up after YOU, will be bound to say, also the foreigner who will come from a distant land, even when they have seen the plagues of that land and its maladies with which Jehovah has sickened it, 23 sulphur and salt and burning, so that its whole land will not be sown, nor sprout, nor will any vegetation spring up in it, like the overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah, Ad′mah and Ze·boi′im, which Jehovah overthrew in his anger and in his wrath; 24 yes, all the nations will be bound to say, ‘Why did Jehovah do like this to this land? Why the heat of this great anger?’ 25 Then they will have to say, ‘It was because they abandoned the covenant of Jehovah the God of their forefathers, which he concluded with them when he brought them out of the land of Egypt. 26 And they proceeded to go and serve other gods and to bow down to them, gods that they had not known and he had not apportioned to them. 27 Then Jehovah’s anger blazed against that land by bringing upon it the whole malediction written in this book. 28 Hence Jehovah uprooted them from off their soil in anger and rage and great indignation and threw them into another land as at this day.’

29 “The things concealed belong to Jehovah our God, but the things revealed belong to us and to our sons to time indefinite, that we may carry out all the words of this law.

Deuteronomy

30 “And it must occur that when all these words will come upon you, the blessing and the malediction, which I have put before you, and you have brought them back to your heart among all the nations where Jehovah your God has dispersed you, 2 and you have returned to Jehovah your God and listened to his voice according to all that I am commanding you today, you and your sons, with all your heart and all your soul, 3 Jehovah your God must also bring back your captives and show you mercy and collect you again from all the peoples where Jehovah your God has scattered you. 4 If your dispersed people should be at the end of the heavens, from there Jehovah your God will collect you and from there he will take you. 5 Jehovah your God will indeed bring you into the land of which your fathers took possession, and you will certainly take possession of it; and he will indeed do you good and multiply you more than your fathers. 6 And Jehovah your God will have to circumcise your heart and the heart of your offspring, that you may love Jehovah your God with all your heart and all your soul for the sake of your life. 7 And Jehovah your God will certainly put all these oaths upon your enemies and those who hate you, who have persecuted you.

8 “As for you, you will turn and certainly listen to the voice of Jehovah and do all his commandments that I am commanding you today. 9 And Jehovah your God will indeed make you have more than enough in every work of your hand, in the fruit of your belly and the fruit of your domestic animals and the fruitage of your soil, resulting in prosperity; because Jehovah will again exult over you for good, just as he exulted over your forefathers; 10 for you will listen to the voice of Jehovah your God so as to keep his commandments and his statutes written in this book of the law, because you will return to Jehovah your God with all your heart and all your soul.

11 “For this commandment that I am commanding you today is not too difficult for you, nor is it far away. 12 It is not in the heavens, so as to result in saying, ‘Who will ascend for us into the heavens and get it for us, that he may let us hear it that we may do it?’ 13 Neither is it on the other side of the sea, so as to result in saying, ‘Who will pass over for us to the other side of the sea and get it for us, that he may let us hear it that we may do it?’ 14 For the word is very near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart, that you may do it.

15 “See, I do put before you today life and good, and death and bad. 16 If you will listen to the commandments of Jehovah your God, which I am commanding you today, so as to love Jehovah your God, to walk in his ways and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his judicial decisions, then you will be bound to keep alive and to multiply, and Jehovah your God must bless you in the land to which you are going to take possession of it.

17 “But if your heart turns away and you do not listen, and you are actually seduced and bow down to other gods and serve them, 18 I do tell YOU today that YOU will positively perish. YOU will not lengthen YOUR days on the ground to which you are crossing the Jordan to go to take possession of it. 19 I do take the heavens and the earth as witnesses against YOU today, that I have put life and death before you, the blessing and the malediction; and you must choose life in order that you may keep alive, you and your offspring, 20 by loving Jehovah your God, by listening to his voice and by sticking to him; for he is your life and the length of your days, that you may dwell upon the ground that Jehovah swore to your forefathers Abraham, Isaac and Jacob to give to them.”

Deuteronomy

32 “Give ear, O heavens, and let me speak;

And let the earth hear the sayings of my mouth.

2 My instruction will drip as the rain,

My saying will trickle as the dew,

As gentle rains upon grass

And as copious showers upon vegetation.

3 For I shall declare the name of Jehovah.

Do YOU attribute greatness to our God!

4 The Rock, perfect is his activity,

For all his ways are justice.

A God of faithfulness, with whom there is no injustice;

Righteous and upright is he.

5 They have acted ruinously on their own part;

They are not his children, the defect is their own.

A generation crooked and twisted!

6 Is it to Jehovah that YOU keep doing this way,

O people stupid and not wise?

Is he not your Father who has produced you,

He who made you and proceeded to give you stability?

7 Remember the days of old,

CONSIDER the years back from generation to generation;

Ask your father, and he can tell you;

Your old men, and they can say it to you.

8 When the Most High gave the nations an inheritance,

When he parted the sons of Adam from one another,

He proceeded to fix the boundary of the peoples

With regard for the number of the sons of Israel.

9 For Jehovah’s share is his people;

Jacob is the allotment that he inherits.

10 He came to find him in a wilderness land,

And in an empty, howling desert.

He began to encircle him, to take care of him,

To safeguard him as the pupil of his eye.

11 Just as an eagle stirs up its nest,

Hovers over its fledglings,

Spreads out its wings, takes them,

Carries them on its pinions,

12 Jehovah alone kept leading him,

And there was no foreign god along with him.

13 He kept making him ride upon earth’s high places,

So that he ate the produce of the field.

And he kept making him suck honey out of a crag,

And oil out of a flinty rock;

14 Butter of the herd and milk of the flock

Together with the fat of rams,

And male sheep, the breed of Ba′shan, and he-goats

Together with the kidney fat of wheat;

And the blood of the grape you kept drinking as wine.

15 When Jesh′u·run began to grow fat, then he kicked.

You have grown fat, you have become thick, you have become gorged.

So he forsook God, who made him,

And despised the Rock of his salvation.

16 They began inciting him to jealousy with strange gods;

With detestable things they kept offending him.

17 They went sacrificing to demons, not to God,

Gods whom they had not known,

New ones who recently came in,

With whom YOUR forefathers were not acquainted.

18 The Rock who fathered you, you proceeded to forget,

And you began to leave God out of memory, the One bringing you forth with childbirth pains.

19 When Jehovah saw it, then he came to disrespect them,

Because of the vexation his sons and his daughters gave.

20 So he said, ‘Let me conceal my face from them,

Let me see what their end will be afterward.

For they are a generation of perverseness,

Sons in whom there is no faithfulness.

21 They, for their part, have incited me to jealousy with what is no god;

They have vexed me with their vain idols;

And I, for my part, shall incite them to jealousy with what is no people;

With a stupid nation I shall offend them.

22 For a fire has been ignited in my anger

And it will burn down to She′ol, the lowest place,

And it will consume the earth and its produce

And will set ablaze the foundations of mountains.

23 I shall increase calamities upon them;

My arrows I shall spend upon them.

24 Exhausted from hunger they will be and eaten up by burning fever

And bitter destruction.

And the teeth of beasts I shall send upon them,

With the venom of reptiles of the dust.

25 Outdoors a sword will bereave them,

And indoors fright,

Of both young man and virgin,

Suckling together with gray-haired man.

26 I should have said: “I shall disperse them,

I will make the mention of them cease from mortal men,”

27 Were it not that I was afraid of vexation from the enemy,

That their adversaries might misconstrue it,

That they might say: “Our hand has proved superior,

And it was not Jehovah who worked all this out.”

28 For they are a nation on whom counsel perishes,

And among them there is no understanding.

29 O that they were wise! Then they would ponder over this.

They would consider their end afterward.

30 How could one pursue a thousand,

And two put ten thousand to flight?

Not unless their Rock had sold them

And Jehovah had surrendered them.

31 For their rock is not like our Rock,

Even our enemies being the ones to decide.

32 For their vine is from the vine of Sod′om

And from the terraces of Go·mor′rah.

Their grapes are grapes of poison,

Their clusters are bitter.

33 Their wine is the venom of big snakes

And the cruel poison of cobras.

34 Is it not laid up with me,

With a seal affixed to it in my storehouse?

35 Vengeance is mine, and retribution.

At the appointed time their foot will move unsteadily,

For the day of their disaster is near,

And the events in readiness for them do make haste.’

36 For Jehovah will judge his people

And he will feel regret over his servants,

Because he will see that support has disappeared

And there is only a helpless and worthless one.

37 And he will certainly say, ‘Where are their gods,

The rock in whom they sought refuge,

38 Who used to eat the fat of their sacrifices,

To drink the wine of their drink offerings?

Let them get up and help YOU.

Let them become a concealment place for YOU.

39 SEE now that I—I am he

And there are no gods together with me.

I put to death, and I make alive.

I have severely wounded, and I—I will heal,

And there is no one snatching out of my hand.

40 For I raise my hand to heaven in an oath,

And I do say: “As I am alive to time indefinite,”

41 If I do indeed sharpen my glittering sword,

And my hand takes hold on judgment,

I will pay back vengeance to my adversaries

And render retribution to those who intensely hate me.

42 I shall intoxicate my arrows with blood,

While my sword will eat flesh,

With the blood of the slain and the captives,

With the heads of the leaders of the enemy.’

43 Be glad, YOU nations, with his people,

For he will avenge the blood of his servants,

And he will pay back vengeance to his adversaries

And will indeed make atonement for the ground of his people.”

44 Thus Moses came and spoke all the words of this song in the hearing of the people, he and Ho·she′a the son of Nun. 45 After Moses finished speaking all these words to all Israel, 46 he went on to say to them: “Apply YOUR hearts to all the words that I am speaking in warning to YOU today, that YOU may command YOUR sons to take care to do all the words of this law. 47 For it is no valueless word for YOU, but it means YOUR life, and by this word YOU may lengthen YOUR days upon the soil to which YOU are crossing the Jordan to take possession of it.”

48 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses on this same day, saying: 49 “Go up into this mountain of Ab′a·rim, Mount Ne′bo, which is in the land of Mo′ab, which fronts toward Jer′i·cho, and see the land of Ca′naan, which I am giving to the sons of Israel as a possession. 50 Then die on the mountain into which you are going up, and be gathered to your people, just as Aaron your brother died on Mount Hor and got to be gathered to his people; 51 for the reason that YOU men acted undutifully toward me in the middle of the sons of Israel at the waters of Mer′i·bah of Ka′desh in the wilderness of Zin; for the reason that YOU men did not sanctify me in the middle of the sons of Israel. 52 For from a distance you will see the land, but you will not go there into the land that I am giving to the sons of Israel.”

Joshua

2 Then Joshua the son of Nun sent two men out secretly from Shit′tim as spies, saying: “Go, take a look at the land and Jer′i·cho.” So they went and came to the house of a prostitute woman whose name was Ra′hab, and they took up lodging there. 2 In time it was said to the king of Jer′i·cho: “Look! Men from the sons of Israel have come in here tonight to search out the land.” 3 At that the king of Jer′i·cho sent to Ra′hab, saying: “Bring out the men that came to you, that have come into your house, for it is to search out all the land that they have come.”

4 Meantime the woman took the two men and concealed them. And she proceeded to say: “Yes, the men did come to me, and I did not know from where they were. 5 And it came about at the closing of the gate by dark that the men went out. I just do not know where the men have gone. Chase after them quickly, for YOU will overtake them.” 6 (She, though, had taken them up to the roof, and she kept them out of sight among stalks of flax laid in rows for her upon the roof.) 7 And the men chased after them in the direction of the Jordan at the fords, and they shut the gate immediately after those chasing after them had gone out.

8 As for these, before they could lie down, she herself came up to them on the roof. 9 And she went on to say to the men: “I do know that Jehovah will certainly give YOU the land, and that the fright of YOU has fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants of the land have become disheartened because of YOU. 10 For we have heard how Jehovah dried up the waters of the Red Sea from before YOU when YOU came out of Egypt, and what YOU did to the two kings of the Am′or·ites who were on the other side of the Jordan, namely, Si′hon and Og, whom YOU devoted to destruction. 11 When we got to hear it, then our hearts began to melt, and no spirit has arisen yet in anybody because of YOU, for Jehovah YOUR God is God in the heavens above and on the earth beneath. 12 And now, please, swear to me by Jehovah that, because I have exercised loving-kindness toward YOU, YOU also will certainly exercise loving-kindness toward the household of my father, and YOU must give me a trustworthy sign. 13 And YOU must preserve alive my father and my mother and my brothers and my sisters and all who belong to them, and YOU must deliver our souls from death.”

14 At that the men said to her: “Our souls are to die instead of YOU people! If YOU will not tell about this matter of ours, it must also occur that when Jehovah gives us the land, we also shall certainly exercise loving-kindness and trustworthiness toward you.” 15 After that she had them descend by a rope through the window, for her house was on a side of the wall, and it was on the wall that she was dwelling. 16 And she proceeded to say to them: “Go to the mountainous region, that those in pursuit may not come in contact with YOU; and YOU must keep hid there three days, until those in pursuit have come back, and afterward YOU may go in YOUR own direction.”

17 In turn the men said to her: “We are free from guilt respecting this oath of yours that you have made us swear. 18 Look! We are coming into the land. This cord of scarlet thread you should tie in the window by which you have had us descend, and your father and your mother and your brothers and all the household of your father you should gather to yourself into the house. 19 And it must occur that anyone who goes out of the doors of your house into the open, his blood will be upon his own head, and we shall be free from guilt; and everyone who continues with you in the house, his blood will be on our heads if a hand should come upon him. 20 And if you should report this matter of ours, we shall also have become free from guilt respecting this oath of yours that you have made us swear.” 21 To this she said: “According to YOUR words so let it be.”

With that she sent them off, and they went their way. After that she tied the scarlet cord in the window. 22 So they went and came to the mountainous region and kept dwelling there three days, until the pursuers had come back. Now the pursuers were looking for them on every road, and they did not find them. 23 And the two men proceeded to descend again from the mountainous region and to cross over and come to Joshua the son of Nun, and they began to relate to him all the things that had happened to them. 24 And they went on to say to Joshua: “Jehovah has given all the land into our hand. Consequently all the inhabitants of the land have also grown disheartened because of us.”

Joshua

6 Now Jer′i·cho was tightly shut up because of the sons of Israel, no one going out and no one entering.

2 And Jehovah went on to say to Joshua: “See, I have given Jer′i·cho and its king, the valiant mighty men, into your hand. 3 And all YOU men of war must march round the city, going round the city once. That is the way you should do for six days. 4 And seven priests should carry seven rams’ horns, before the Ark, and on the seventh day YOU should march round the city seven times and the priests should blow the horns. 5 And it must occur that when they sound with the horn of the ram, when YOU hear the sound of the horn, all the people should shout a great war cry; and the wall of the city must fall down flat, and the people must go up, each one straight before him.”

6 Accordingly Joshua the son of Nun called the priests and said to them: “Take up the ark of the covenant, and seven priests should carry seven rams’ horns before the ark of Jehovah.” 7 And he went on to say to the people: “Pass on and march round the city, and the war-equipped force should pass on ahead of the ark of Jehovah.” 8 So it came about just as Joshua said to the people; and seven priests carrying seven rams’ horns before Jehovah passed on and blew the horns, and the ark of the covenant of Jehovah was following them. 9 And the war-equipped force was going ahead of the priests blowing the horns, while the rear guard was following the Ark with a continual blowing on the horns.

10 Now Joshua had commanded the people, saying: “YOU must neither shout nor let YOUR voices be heard, and no word should come out of YOUR mouths until the day when I say to YOU, ‘Shout!’ Then YOU must shout.” 11 And he had the ark of Jehovah go marching round the city, going round once, after which they went to the camp and stayed overnight in the camp.

12 Then Joshua got up early in the morning, and the priests went carrying the ark of Jehovah, 13 and seven priests carrying seven rams’ horns before the ark of Jehovah were walking, continually blowing the horns, and the war-equipped force was walking ahead of them, while the rear guard was following the ark of Jehovah with a continual blowing on the horns. 14 And they went marching round the city on the second day once, after which they returned to the camp. That was the way they did for six days.

15 And it came about on the seventh day that they proceeded to get up early, as soon as the dawn ascended, and they went marching round the city in this manner seven times. Just on that day they marched round the city seven times. 16 And it came about on the seventh time that the priests blew the horns, and Joshua proceeded to say to the people: “Shout; for Jehovah has given YOU the city. 17 And the city must become a thing devoted to destruction; it with everything that is in it belongs to Jehovah. Only Ra′hab the prostitute may keep on living, she and all who are with her in the house, because she hid the messengers whom we sent out. 18 As for YOU people, only keep away from the thing devoted to destruction, for fear YOU may get a desire and YOU do take some of the thing devoted to destruction and do constitute the camp of Israel a thing devoted to destruction and bring ostracism upon it. 19 But all the silver and the gold and the articles of copper and iron are something holy to Jehovah. Into the treasure of Jehovah it should go.”

20 Then the people shouted, when they proceeded to blow the horns. And it came about that as soon as the people heard the sound of the horn and the people began to shout a great war cry, then the wall began to fall down flat. After that the people went up into the city, each one straight before him, and captured the city. 21 And they went devoting all that was in the city, from man to woman, from young man to old man and to bull and sheep and ass, to destruction by the edge of the sword.

22 And to the two men who had done the spying on the land, Joshua said: “Go into the house of the woman, the prostitute, and bring out of there the woman and all who belong to her, just as YOU have sworn to her.” 23 So the young men who had done the spying went in and brought out Ra′hab and her father and her mother and her brothers and all who belonged to her, yes, all her family relationship they brought out; and they proceeded to set them down outside the camp of Israel.

24 And they burned the city with fire and everything that was in it. Only the silver and the gold and the articles of copper and iron they gave to the treasure of Jehovah’s house. 25 And Ra′hab the prostitute and the household of her father and all who belonged to her, Joshua preserved alive; and she dwells in the midst of Israel down to this day, because she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent out to spy on Jer′i·cho.

26 Then Joshua had an oath pronounced at that particular time, saying: “Cursed may the man be before Jehovah who gets up and does build this city, even Jer′i·cho. At the forfeit of his firstborn let him lay the foundation of it, and at the forfeit of his youngest let him put up its doors.”

27 So Jehovah proved to be with Joshua, and his fame came to be in all the earth.

Judges

2 Then Jehovah’s angel went up from Gil′gal to Bo′chim and said: “I proceeded to bring YOU up out of Egypt and to bring YOU into the land about which I swore to YOUR forefathers. Furthermore, I said, ‘Never shall I break my covenant with YOU. 2 And for YOUR part, YOU must not conclude a covenant with the inhabitants of this land. Their altars YOU should pull down.’ But YOU have not listened to my voice. Why have YOU done this? 3 So I, in turn, have said, ‘I shall not drive them away from before YOU, and they must become snares to YOU, and their gods will serve as a lure to YOU.’”

4 And it came about that as soon as Jehovah’s angel had spoken these words to all the sons of Israel, the people began to raise their voices and weep. 5 Hence they called the name of that place Bo′chim. And they proceeded to sacrifice there to Jehovah.

6 When Joshua sent the people away, then the sons of Israel went their way, each to his inheritance, to take possession of the land. 7 And the people continued to serve Jehovah all the days of Joshua and all the days of the older men who extended their days after Joshua and who had seen all of Jehovah’s great work that he did for Israel. 8 Then Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Jehovah, died at the age of a hundred and ten years. 9 So they buried him in the territory of his inheritance in Tim′nath-he′res in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, on the north of Mount Ga′ash. 10 And all that generation too were gathered to their fathers, and another generation began to rise after them that did not know Jehovah or the work that he had done for Israel.

11 And the sons of Israel fell to doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and serving the Ba′als. 12 Thus they abandoned Jehovah the God of their fathers who had brought them out of the land of Egypt and went following other gods from among the gods of the peoples who were all around them and they began bowing down to them, so that they offended Jehovah. 13 Thus they abandoned Jehovah and took up serving Ba′al and the Ash′to·reth images. 14 At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, so that he gave them into the hands of the pillagers, and they began to pillage them; and he proceeded to sell them into the hand of their enemies round about, and they were no longer able to stand before their enemies. 15 Everywhere that they went out, the hand of Jehovah proved to be against them for calamity, just as Jehovah had spoken and just as Jehovah had sworn to them; and they got to be in very sore straits. 16 So Jehovah would raise up judges, and they would save them out of the hand of their pillagers.

17 And even to their judges they did not listen, but they had immoral intercourse with other gods and went bowing down to them. They quickly turned aside from the way in which their forefathers had walked by obeying the commandments of Jehovah. They did not do like that. 18 And when Jehovah did raise up judges for them, Jehovah proved to be with the judge, and he saved them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge; for Jehovah would feel regret over their groaning because of their oppressors and those who were shoving them around.

19 And it occurred that when the judge died they would turn around and act more ruinously than their fathers by walking after other gods to serve them and bow down to them. They did not refrain from their practices and their stubborn behavior. 20 Finally Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel and he said: “For the reason that this nation have overstepped my covenant that I commanded their forefathers and have not listened to my voice, 21 I too, for my part, shall not drive out again from before them a single one of the nations that Joshua left behind when he died, 22 in order by them to test Israel, whether they will be keepers of Jehovah’s way by walking in it just as their fathers kept it, or not.” 23 Accordingly Jehovah let these nations stay by not driving them out quickly, and he did not give them into Joshua’s hand.

1 Samuel

2 And Han′nah went on to pray and say:

“My heart does exult in Jehovah,

My horn is indeed exalted in Jehovah.

My mouth is widened against my enemies,

For I do rejoice in the salvation from you.

2 There is no one holy like Jehovah, for there is no one but you;

And there is no rock like our God.

3 Do not YOU people speak very haughtily so much,

Let nothing go forth unrestrained from YOUR mouth,

For a God of knowledge Jehovah is,

And by him deeds are rightly estimated.

4 The mighty men of the bow are filled with terror,

But those that are stumbling do gird on vital energy.

5 The satisfied must hire themselves out for bread,

But the hungry actually cease to hunger.

Even the barren has given birth to seven,

But she that was abundant in sons has faded away.

6 Jehovah is a Killer and a Preserver of life,

A Bringer down to She′ol, and He brings up.

7 Jehovah is an Impoverisher and an Enricher,

An Abaser, also an Exalter,

8 A Raiser of a lowly one from the dust;

From the ashpit he lifts up a poor one,

To make them sit with nobles; and a throne of glory he gives to them as a possession.

For to Jehovah belong earth’s supports,

And he places upon them the productive land.

9 The feet of his loyal ones he guards;

As for the wicked ones, they are silenced in darkness,

For not by power does a man prove superior.

10 As for Jehovah, those contending against him will be terrified;

Against them he will thunder in the heavens.

Jehovah himself will judge the ends of the earth,

That he may give strength to his king,

That he may exalt the horn of his anointed one.”

11 Then El·ka′nah went to Ra′mah to his house; and as for the boy, he became a minister of Jehovah before E′li the priest.

12 Now the sons of E′li were good-for-nothing men; they did not acknowledge Jehovah. 13 As for the due right of the priests from the people, whenever any man was offering a sacrifice, an attendant of the priest came with the three-pronged fork in his hand, just when the meat was boiling, 14 and made a thrust into the basin or the two-handled cooking pot or the caldron or the one-handled cooking pot. Anything that the fork might bring up the priest would take for himself. That is the way they would do in Shi′loh to all the Israelites coming there. 15 Also, before ever they could make the fat smoke, an attendant of the priest came and said to the man sacrificing: “Do give meat to roast for the priest so that he may receive from you, not boiled meat, but raw.” 16 When the man would say to him: “Let them be sure to make the fat smoke first of all. Then take for yourself just whatever your soul may crave,” he actually said: “No, but you should give it now; and, if not, I shall have to take it by force!” 17 And the sin of the attendants came to be very great before Jehovah; for the men treated the offering of Jehovah with disrespect.

18 And Samuel was ministering before Jehovah, as a boy, having a linen eph′od girded on. 19 Also, a little sleeveless coat his mother would make for him, and she brought it up to him from year to year when she came up with her husband to sacrifice the yearly sacrifice. 20 And E′li blessed El·ka′nah and his wife and said: “May Jehovah appoint to you an offspring from this wife in place of the thing lent, that was lent to Jehovah.” And they went to their place. 21 Accordingly Jehovah turned his attention to Han′nah, so that she had pregnancy and gave birth to three sons and two daughters. And the boy Samuel continued growing up with Jehovah.

22 And E′li was very old, and he had heard of all that his sons kept doing to all Israel and how they would lie down with the women that were serving at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 23 And he used to say to them: “Why do YOU keep doing things like these? For the things I am hearing about YOU from all the people are bad. 24 No, my sons, because the report is not good that I am hearing, that the people of Jehovah are causing to circulate. 25 If a man should sin against a man, God will arbitrate for him; but if it is against Jehovah that a man should sin, who is there to pray for him?” But they would not listen to the voice of their father, because Jehovah was now pleased to put them to death. 26 All the while the boy Samuel was growing bigger and more likable both from Jehovah’s standpoint and from that of men.

27 And a man of God proceeded to come to E′li and say to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Did I not for a fact reveal myself to the house of your forefather while they happened to be in Egypt as slaves to the house of Phar′aoh? 28 And there was a choosing of him out of all the tribes of Israel for me, to act as priest and go up upon my altar to make sacrificial smoke billow up, to bear an eph′od before me, that I might give to the house of your forefather all the offerings made by fire of the sons of Israel. 29 Why do YOU men keep kicking at my sacrifice and at my offering that I have commanded in my dwelling, and you keep honoring your sons more than me by fattening yourselves from the best of every offering of Israel my people?

30 “‘That is why the utterance of Jehovah the God of Israel is: “I did indeed say, As for your house and the house of your forefather, they will walk before me to time indefinite.” But now the utterance of Jehovah is: “It is unthinkable, on my part, because those honoring me I shall honor, and those despising me will be of little account.” 31 Look! Days are coming when I shall certainly chop off your arm and the arm of the house of your forefather, so that there will not come to be an old man in your house. 32 And you will actually look upon an adversary in my dwelling amid all the good that is done to Israel; and never will there come to be an old man in your house. 33 And yet there is a man of yours that I shall not cut off from being at my altar so as to cause your eyes to fail and to make your soul pine away; but the greater number of your house will all die by the sword of men. 34 And this is the sign for you that will come to your two sons, Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has: On one day both of them will die. 35 And I shall certainly raise up for myself a faithful priest. In harmony with what is in my heart and in my soul he will do; and I shall certainly build for him a lasting house, and he will certainly walk before my anointed one always. 36 And it must occur that anyone left over in your house will come and bow down to him for the payment of money and a round loaf of bread, and will certainly say: “Attach me, please, to one of the priestly offices to eat a piece of bread.”’”

1 Samuel

8 And it came about that as soon as Samuel had grown old he made appointments of his sons as judges for Israel. 2 Now the name of his firstborn son happened to be Joel, and the name of his second A·bi′jah; they were judging in Be′er-she′ba. 3 And his sons did not walk in his ways, but they were inclined to follow unjust profit and would accept a bribe and pervert judgment.

4 In time all the older men of Israel collected themselves together and came to Samuel at Ra′mah 5 and said to him: “Look! You yourself have grown old, but your own sons have not walked in your ways. Now do appoint for us a king to judge us like all the nations.” 6 But the thing was bad in the eyes of Samuel inasmuch as they had said: “Do give us a king to judge us,” and Samuel began to pray to Jehovah. 7 Then Jehovah said to Samuel: “Listen to the voice of the people as respects all that they say to you; for it is not you whom they have rejected, but it is I whom they have rejected from being king over them. 8 In accord with all their doings that they have done from the day of my bringing them up out of Egypt until this day in that they kept leaving me and serving other gods, that is the way they are doing also to you. 9 And now listen to their voice. Only this, that you should solemnly warn them, and you must tell them the rightful due of the king who will reign over them.”

10 So Samuel said all the words of Jehovah to the people who were asking a king of him. 11 And he proceeded to say: “This will become the rightful due of the king that will reign over YOU: YOUR sons he will take and put them as his in his chariots and among his horsemen, and some will have to run before his chariots; 12 and to appoint for himself chiefs over thousands and chiefs over fifties, and some to do his plowing and to reap his harvest and to make his war instruments and his chariot instruments. 13 And YOUR daughters he will take for ointment mixers and cooks and bakers. 14 And YOUR fields and YOUR vineyards and YOUR olive groves, the best ones, he will take and actually give to his servants. 15 And of YOUR fields of seed and of YOUR vineyards he will take the tenth, and he will certainly give them to his court officials and his servants. 16 And YOUR menservants and YOUR maidservants and YOUR best herds, and YOUR asses he will take, and he will have to use them for his work. 17 Of YOUR flocks he will take the tenth, and YOU yourselves will become his as servants. 18 And YOU will certainly cry out in that day by reason of YOUR king, whom YOU have chosen for yourselves, but Jehovah will not answer YOU in that day.”

19 However, the people refused to listen to the voice of Samuel and said: “No, but a king is what will come to be over us. 20 And we must become, we also, like all the nations, and our king must judge us and go out before us and fight our battles.” 21 And Samuel gave a hearing to all the words of the people; then he spoke them in the ears of Jehovah. 22 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Samuel: “Listen to their voice, and you must cause a king to reign for them.” Accordingly Samuel said to the men of Israel: “Go each one to his city.”

1 Samuel

31 Now the Phi·lis′tines were fighting against Israel, and the men of Israel took to flight from before the Phi·lis′tines, and they kept falling down slain in Mount Gil·bo′a. 2 And the Phi·lis′tines kept in close range of Saul and his sons; and the Phi·lis′tines at last struck down Jon′a·than and A·bin′a·dab and Mal′chi-shu′a, Saul’s sons. 3 And the fighting became heavy against Saul, and the shooters, the bowmen, finally found him, and he got severely wounded by the shooters. 4 Then Saul said to his armor-bearer: “Draw your sword and run me through with it, that these uncircumcised men may not come and certainly run me through and deal abusively with me.” And his armor-bearer was unwilling, because he was very much afraid. So Saul took the sword and fell upon it. 5 When his armor-bearer saw that Saul had died, then he too fell upon his own sword and died with him. 6 Thus Saul and his three sons and his armor-bearer, even all his men, came to die together on that day. 7 When the men of Israel that were in the region of the low plain and that were in the region of the Jordan saw that the men of Israel had fled, and that Saul and his sons had died, then they began to leave the cities and flee, after which the Phi·lis′tines came on in and took up dwelling in them.

8 And it came about the next day that, when the Phi·lis′tines came to strip the slain, they got to find Saul and his three sons fallen upon Mount Gil·bo′a. 9 And they proceeded to cut off his head and strip off his armor and send into the land of the Phi·lis′tines all around to inform the houses of their idols and the people. 10 Finally they put his armor in the house of the Ash′to·reth images, and his corpse they fastened on the wall of Beth-shan. 11 And as regards him, the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad got to hear what the Phi·lis′tines had done to Saul. 12 Immediately all the valiant men rose up and went all night long and took the corpse of Saul and the corpses of his sons off the wall of Beth-shan and came to Ja′besh and burned them there. 13 Then they took their bones and buried them under the tamarisk tree in Ja′besh, and they went fasting for seven days.

1 Kings

6 And it came about in the four hundred and eightieth year after the sons of Israel came out from the land of Egypt, in the fourth year, in the month of Ziv, that is, the second month, after Sol′o·mon became king over Israel, that he proceeded to build the house to Jehovah. 2 And the house that King Sol′o·mon built to Jehovah was sixty cubits in its length, and twenty in its width, and thirty cubits in its height. 3 And the porch in front of the temple of the house was twenty cubits in its length, in front of the width of the house. Ten cubits it was in its depth, in front of the house.

4 And for the house he went on to make windows of narrowing frames. 5 Further, he built against the wall of the house a side structure all around, against the walls of the house all around the temple and the innermost room, and made side chambers all around. 6 The lowest side chamber was five cubits in its width, and the middle one was six cubits in its width, and the third one was seven cubits in its width; for there were cutbacks that he gave to the house all around outside, that it might not have a hold in the walls of the house.

7 As for the house, while it was being built, it was of quarry stone already completed that it was built; and as for hammers and axes or any tools of iron, they were not heard in the house while it was being built. 8 The entrance of the lowest side chamber was on the right side of the house, and by a winding staircase they would go up to the middle one, and from the middle one up to the third one. 9 Further, he continued building the house that he might finish it, and covered in the house with beams and rows in cedarwood. 10 Moreover, he built the side chambers against the whole house five cubits in their height, and they had a hold on the house by timbers of cedar trees.

11 Meantime, the word of Jehovah came to Sol′o·mon, saying: 12 “As regards this house that you are building, if you will walk in my statutes and perform my judicial decisions and actually keep all my commandments by walking in them, I also shall certainly carry out my word with you that I spoke to David your father; 13 and I shall indeed reside in the middle of the sons of Israel, and I shall not leave my people Israel.”

14 And Sol′o·mon continued building the house that he might finish it. 15 And he proceeded to build the walls of the house inside it with boards of cedar. From the floor of the house up to the rafters of the ceiling he overlaid it with timber inside; and he went on to overlay the floor of the house with boards of juniper. 16 Further, he built twenty cubits at the rear sides of the house with boards of cedar, from the floor up to the rafters, and built for it inside the innermost room, the Most Holy. 17 And it was forty cubits that the house proved to be, that is, the temple in front of it. 18 And the cedarwood on the house inside was with carvings of gourd-shaped ornaments and garlands of blossoms. All of it was cedarwood; there was no stone to be seen.

19 And the innermost room in the interior of the house he prepared inside, to put there the ark of the covenant of Jehovah. 20 And the innermost room was twenty cubits in length, and twenty cubits in width, and twenty cubits in its height; and he proceeded to overlay it with pure gold, and to overlay the altar with cedarwood. 21 And Sol′o·mon went on to overlay the house inside with pure gold, and to make chainwork of gold pass across in front of the innermost room, and to overlay it with gold. 22 And the whole house he overlaid with gold, until all the house was completed; and all the altar that was toward the innermost room he overlaid with gold.

23 Further, he made in the innermost room two cherubs of oil-tree wood, ten cubits being the height of each one. 24 And five cubits was the one wing of the cherub, and five cubits was the other wing of the cherub. Ten cubits it was from the tip of his wing to the tip of his wing. 25 And the second cherub was ten cubits. The two cherubs had the same measure and the same shape. 26 The height of the one cherub was ten cubits, and that was so of the other cherub. 27 Then he put the cherubs inside the inner house, so that they spread out the wings of the cherubs. Thus the wing of the one reached to the wall and the wing of the other cherub was reaching to the other wall; and their wings were toward the middle of the house, reaching wing to wing. 28 Moreover, he overlaid the cherubs with gold.

29 And all the walls of the house round about he carved with engraved carvings of cherubs and palm-tree figures and engravings of blossoms, inside and outside; 30 and the floor of the house he overlaid with gold, inside and outside. 31 And the entrance of the innermost room he made with doors of oil-tree wood: side pillars, doorposts and a fifth. 32 And the two doors were of oil-tree wood, and he carved upon them carvings of cherubs and palm-tree figures and the engravings of blossoms, and he overlaid them with gold; and he proceeded to beat the gold down upon the cherubs and the palm-tree figures. 33 And that was the way he made for the entrance of the temple, the doorposts of oil-tree wood, foursquare. 34 And the two doors were of juniper wood. The two leaves of the one door turned on pivots, and the two leaves of the other door turned on pivots. 35 And he carved cherubs and palm-tree figures and engravings of blossoms, and overlaid gold foil upon the representations.

36 And he went on to build the inner courtyard with three rows of hewn stone and a row of beams of cedarwood.

37 In the fourth year the house of Jehovah had its foundation laid, in the lunar month of Ziv; 38 and in the eleventh year, in the lunar month of Bul, that is, the eighth month, the house was finished as regards all its details and all its plan; so that he was seven years at building it.

1 Kings

8 At that time Sol′o·mon proceeded to congregate the older men of Israel, all the heads of the tribes, the chieftains of the fathers, of the sons of Israel, to King Sol′o·mon at Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of the City of David, that is to say, Zion. 2 So all the men of Israel congregated themselves to King Sol′o·mon in the lunar month of Eth′a·nim in the festival, that is, the seventh month. 3 So all the older men of Israel came, and the priests began to carry the Ark. 4 And they came bringing up the ark of Jehovah and the tent of meeting and all the holy utensils that were in the tent; and the priests and the Levites came bringing them up. 5 And King Sol′o·mon and with him all the assembly of Israel, those keeping their appointment with him, were before the Ark, sacrificing sheep and cattle that could not be counted or numbered for multitude.

6 Then the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of Jehovah to its place, to the innermost room of the house, the Most Holy, to underneath the wings of the cherubs.

7 For the cherubs were spreading out their wings over the place of the Ark, so that the cherubs kept the Ark and its poles screened over from above. 8 But the poles proved to be long, so that the tips of the poles were visible from the Holy in front of the innermost room, but they were not visible outside. And there they continue down to this day. 9 There was nothing in the Ark but the two stone tablets which Moses had deposited there in Ho′reb, when Jehovah had covenanted with the sons of Israel while they were coming out from the land of Egypt.

10 And it came about that when the priests came out from the holy place, the cloud itself filled the house of Jehovah. 11 And the priests were unable to stand to do their ministering because of the cloud, for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah. 12 At that time Sol′o·mon said: “Jehovah himself said he was to reside in the thick gloom. 13 I have successfully built a house of lofty abode for you, an established place for you to dwell in to time indefinite.”

14 Then the king turned his face and began to bless all the congregation of Israel, while all the congregation of Israel were standing up. 15 And he went on to say: “Blessed is Jehovah the God of Israel, who spoke by his own mouth with David my father and by his own hand has given fulfillment, saying, 16 ‘From the day that I brought my people Israel out from Egypt I have not chosen a city out of all the tribes of Israel to build a house for my name to continue there; but I shall choose David to come to be over my people Israel.’ 17 And it came to be close to the heart of David my father to build a house to the name of Jehovah the God of Israel. 18 But Jehovah said to David my father, ‘For the reason that it proved to be close to your heart to build a house to my name, you did well, because it proved to be close to your heart. 19 Only you yourself will not build the house, but your son who is coming forth from your loins is the one that will build the house to my name.’ 20 And Jehovah proceeded to carry out his word that he had spoken, that I might rise up in the place of David my father and sit upon the throne of Israel, just as Jehovah had spoken, and that I might build the house to the name of Jehovah the God of Israel, 21 and that I might locate a place there for the Ark where the covenant of Jehovah is that he concluded with our forefathers when he was bringing them out from the land of Egypt.”

22 And Sol′o·mon began standing before the altar of Jehovah in front of all the congregation of Israel, and he now spread his palms out to the heavens; 23 and he went on to say: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, there is no God like you in the heavens above or on the earth beneath, keeping the covenant and the loving-kindness toward your servants who are walking before you with all their heart, 24 you who have kept toward your servant David my father that which you promised him, so that you made the promise with your own mouth, and with your own hand you have made the fulfillment, as at this day. 25 And now, O Jehovah the God of Israel, keep toward your servant David my father that which you promised him, saying, ‘There will not be cut off a man of yours from before me to sit upon the throne of Israel, if only your sons will take care of their way by walking before me just as you have walked before me.’ 26 And now, O God of Israel, let your promise that you have promised to your servant David my father prove trustworthy, please.

27 “But will God truly dwell upon the earth? Look! The heavens, yes, the heaven of the heavens, themselves cannot contain you; how much less, then, this house that I have built! 28 And you must turn toward the prayer of your servant and to his request for favor, O Jehovah my God, to listen to the entreating cry and to the prayer with which your servant is praying before you today; 29 that your eyes may prove to be opened toward this house night and day, toward the place of which you said, ‘My name will prove to be there,’ to listen to the prayer with which your servant prays toward this place. 30 And you must listen to the request for favor on the part of your servant and of your people Israel with which they pray toward this place; and may you yourself hear at the place of your dwelling, in the heavens, and you must hear and forgive.

31 “When a man sins against his fellowman, and he actually lays a cursing upon him to bring him under liability to the curse, and he actually comes within the curse before your altar in this house, 32 then may you yourself hear from the heavens, and you must act and judge your servants by pronouncing the wicked one wicked by putting his way upon his own head, and by pronouncing the righteous one righteous by giving to him according to his own righteousness.

33 “When your people Israel are defeated before the enemy, because they kept sinning against you, and they indeed return to you and laud your name and pray and make request for favor toward you in this house, 34 then may you yourself hear from the heavens, and you must forgive the sin of your people Israel and you must bring them back to the ground that you gave to their forefathers.

35 “When heaven is shut up so that no rain occurs, because they kept sinning against you, and they actually pray toward this place and laud your name, and from their sin they turn back, because you kept afflicting them, 36 then may you yourself hear from the heavens, and you must forgive the sin of your servants, even of your people Israel, because you teach them the good way in which they should walk; and you must give rain upon your land that you have given to your people as a hereditary possession.

37 “In case a famine occurs in the land, in case a pestilence occurs, in case scorching, mildew, locusts, cockroaches occur; in case their enemy besieges them in the land of their gates—any sort of plague, any sort of malady— 38 whatever prayer, whatever request for favor there may occur on the part of any man or of all your people Israel, because they know each one the plague of his own heart, and they actually spread out their palms to this house, 39 then may you yourself hear from the heavens, your established place of dwelling, and you must forgive and act and give to each one according to all his ways, because you know his heart (for you yourself alone well know the heart of all the sons of mankind); 40 to the end that they may fear you all the days that they are alive upon the surface of the ground that you gave to our forefathers.

41 “And also to the foreigner, who is no part of your people Israel and who actually comes from a distant land by reason of your name 42 (for they shall hear of your great name and of your strong hand and of your stretched-out arm), and he actually comes and prays toward this house, 43 may you yourself listen from the heavens, your established place of dwelling, and you must do according to all that for which the foreigner calls to you; in order that all the peoples of the earth may get to know your name so as to fear you the same as your people Israel do, and so as to know that your name itself has been called upon this house that I have built.

44 “In case your people go out to the war against their enemy in the way that you send them, and they indeed pray to Jehovah in the direction of the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built to your name, 45 you must also hear from the heavens their prayer and their request for favor, and you must execute judgment for them.

46 “In case they sin against you (for there is no man that does not sin), and you have to be incensed at them and abandon them to the enemy, and their captors actually carry them off captive to the land of the enemy distant or nearby; 47 and they indeed come to their senses in the land where they have been carried off captive, and they actually return and make request to you for favor in the land of their captors, saying, ‘We have sinned and erred, we have acted wickedly’; 48 and they indeed return to you with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their enemies who carried them off captive, and they indeed pray to you in the direction of their land that you gave to their forefathers, the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built to your name; 49 you must also hear from the heavens, your established place of dwelling, their prayer and their request for favor, and you must execute judgment for them, 50 and you must forgive your people who had sinned against you and all their transgressions with which they transgressed against you; and you must make them objects of pity before their captors and they must pity them 51 (for they are your people and your inheritance, whom you brought out from Egypt, from inside the iron furnace), 52 that your eyes may prove to be opened to the request for favor of your servant and to the request for favor of your people Israel, by listening to them in all for which they call to you. 53 For you yourself separated them as your inheritance out of all the peoples of the earth, just as you have spoken by means of Moses your servant when you were bringing our forefathers out from Egypt, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

54 And it came about that, as soon as Sol′o·mon finished praying to Jehovah with all this prayer and request for favor, he rose up from before the altar of Jehovah, from bending down upon his knees with his palms spread out to the heavens; 55 and he began to stand and bless all the congregation of Israel with a loud voice, saying: 56 “Blessed be Jehovah, who has given a resting-place to his people Israel according to all that he has promised. There has not failed one word of all his good promise that he has promised by means of Moses his servant. 57 May Jehovah our God prove to be with us just as he proved to be with our forefathers. May he neither leave us nor forsake us, 58 so as to incline our heart to himself to walk in all his ways and to keep his commandments and his regulations and his judicial decisions, which he gave in command to our forefathers. 59 And may these words of mine with which I have made request for favor before Jehovah prove to be near to Jehovah our God by day and night, that he may execute judgment for his servant and judgment for his people Israel as it may require day by day; 60 to the end that all the peoples of the earth may know that Jehovah is the true God. There is no other. 61 And YOUR heart must prove to be complete with Jehovah our God by walking in his regulations and by keeping his commandments as at this day.”

62 And the king and all Israel with him were offering a grand sacrifice before Jehovah. 63 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to offer the communion sacrifices that he had to offer to Jehovah, twenty-two thousand cattle and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep, that the king and all the sons of Israel might inaugurate the house of Jehovah. 64 On that day the king had to sanctify the middle of the courtyard that is before the house of Jehovah, because there he had to render up the burnt sacrifice and the grain offering and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices; for the copper altar that is before Jehovah was too small to contain the burnt sacrifice and the grain offering and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices. 65 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to carry on at that time the festival, and all Israel with him, a great congregation from the entering in of Ha′math down to the torrent valley of Egypt, before Jehovah our God seven days and another seven days, fourteen days. 66 On the eighth day he sent the people away; and they began to bless the king and to go to their homes, rejoicing and feeling merry of heart over all the goodness that Jehovah had performed for David his servant and for Israel his people.

1 Chronicles

10 And the Phi·lis′tines, for their part, made war upon Israel; and the men of Israel went fleeing from before the Phi·lis′tines and kept falling slain in Mount Gil·bo′a. 2 And the Phi·lis′tines kept in close range of Saul and his sons; and the Phi·lis′tines got to strike down Jon′a·than and A·bin′a·dab and Mal′chi-shu′a, sons of Saul. 3 And the fighting became heavy against Saul; and those shooting with the bow finally found him, and he got wounded by the shooters. 4 Then Saul said to his armor-bearer: “Draw your sword and run me through with it, that these uncircumcised men may not come and certainly deal abusively with me.” And his armor-bearer was unwilling, because he was very much afraid. So Saul took the sword and fell upon it. 5 When his armor-bearer saw that Saul had died, then he too fell upon the sword and died. 6 Thus Saul and three sons of his died, and all those of his house died together. 7 When all the men of Israel that were in the low plain saw that they had fled and that Saul and his sons had died, then they began to leave their cities and flee; after which the Phi·lis′tines came on in and took up dwelling in them.

8 And it came about the next day that, when the Phi·lis′tines came to strip the slain, they got to find Saul and his sons fallen upon Mount Gil·bo′a. 9 And they proceeded to strip him and take off his head and his armor and send into the land of the Phi·lis′tines all around to inform their idols and the people. 10 Finally they put his armor in the house of their god, and his skull they fastened to the house of Da′gon.

11 And all those of Ja′besh in Gil′e·ad got to hear of all that the Phi·lis′tines had done to Saul. 12 So all the valiant men rose up and carried off the corpse of Saul and the corpses of his sons and brought them to Ja′besh and buried their bones under the big tree in Ja′besh; and they went fasting for seven days.

13 Thus Saul died for his unfaithfulness with which he had acted faithlessly against Jehovah concerning the word of Jehovah that he had not kept and also for asking of a spirit medium to make inquiry. 14 And he did not inquire of Jehovah. Consequently he put him to death and turned the kingship over to David the son of Jes′se.

1 Chronicles

29 David the king now said to all the congregation: “Sol′o·mon my son, the one whom God has chosen, is young and delicate, but the work is great; for the castle is not for man, but for Jehovah God. 2 And according to all my power I have prepared for the house of my God the gold for the goldwork, and the silver for the silverwork, and the copper for the copperwork, the iron for the ironwork, and the timbers for the timberwork; onyx stones, and stones to be set with hard mortar, and mosaic pebbles, and every precious stone, and alabaster stones in great quantity. 3 And since I am taking pleasure in the house of my God, there is yet a special property of mine, gold and silver; I do give it to the house of my God over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house: 4 three thousand talents of gold of the gold of O′phir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, for coating the walls of the houses; 5 of the gold for the goldwork, and of the silver for the silverwork and for all the work by the hand of the craftsmen. And who is there volunteering to fill his hand today with a gift for Jehovah?”

6 And the princes of the paternal houses and the princes of the tribes of Israel and the chiefs of thousands and of hundreds and the chiefs of the business of the king proceeded to volunteer. 7 Accordingly they gave to the service of the house of the true God gold worth five thousand talents and ten thousand darics and silver worth ten thousand talents and copper worth eighteen thousand talents and iron worth a hundred thousand talents. 8 And what stones were found with any persons they gave to the treasure of the house of Jehovah under the control of Je·hi′el the Ger′shon·ite. 9 And the people gave way to rejoicing over their making voluntary offerings, for it was with a complete heart that they made voluntary offerings to Jehovah; and even David the king himself rejoiced with great joy.

10 Consequently David blessed Jehovah before the eyes of all the congregation and David said: “Blessed may you be, O Jehovah the God of Israel our father, from time indefinite even to time indefinite. 11 Yours, O Jehovah, are the greatness and the mightiness and the beauty and the excellency and the dignity; for everything in the heavens and in the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, O Jehovah, the One also lifting yourself up as head over all. 12 The riches and the glory are on account of you, and you are dominating everything; and in your hand there are power and mightiness, and in your hand is ability to make great and to give strength to all. 13 And now, O our God, we are thanking you and praising your beauteous name.

14 “And yet, who am I and who are my people, that we should retain power to make voluntary offerings like this? For everything is from you, and out of your own hand we have given to you. 15 For we are alien residents before you and settlers the same as all our forefathers. Like a shadow our days are upon the earth and there is no hope. 16 O Jehovah our God, all this abundance that we have prepared to build for you a house for your holy name, from your hand it is, and to you it all belongs. 17 And I well know, O my God, that you are an examiner of the heart, and that it is in rectitude that you take pleasure. I, for my part, in the uprightness of my heart have voluntarily offered all these things, and now your people who are on hand here I have enjoyed seeing make offerings voluntarily to you. 18 O Jehovah the God of Abraham, Isaac and Israel our forefathers, do keep this to time indefinite as the inclination of the thoughts of the heart of your people, and direct their heart to you. 19 And to Sol′o·mon my son give a complete heart to keep your commandments, your testimonies and your regulations, and to do everything, and to build the castle for which I have made preparation.”

20 And David went on to say to all the congregation: “Bless, now, Jehovah YOUR God.” And all the congregation proceeded to bless Jehovah the God of their forefathers and bow low and prostrate themselves to Jehovah and to the king. 21 And they continued to sacrifice sacrifices to Jehovah and offer up burnt offerings to Jehovah on the day following that day, a thousand young bulls, a thousand rams, a thousand male lambs and their drink offerings, even sacrifices in great number for all Israel. 22 And they continued eating and drinking before Jehovah on that day with great rejoicing; and they proceeded a second time to make Sol′o·mon the son of David king and to anoint him to Jehovah as leader and also Za′dok as priest. 23 And Sol′o·mon began to sit upon Jehovah’s throne as king in place of David his father and to make a success of it, and all the Israelites were obedient to him. 24 As for all the princes and the mighty men and also all the sons of King David, they submitted themselves to Sol′o·mon the king. 25 And Jehovah continued to make Sol′o·mon surpassingly great before the eyes of all Israel and to put upon him such royal dignity as had not come to be upon any king before him over Israel.

26 As for David the son of Jes′se, he reigned over all Israel; 27 and the days that he reigned over Israel were forty years. In He′bron he reigned for seven years, and in Jerusalem he reigned for thirty-three years. 28 And gradually he died in a good old age, satisfied with days, riches and glory; and Sol′o·mon his son began to reign in place of him. 29 As for the affairs of David the king, the first ones and the last, there they are written among the words of Samuel the seer and among the words of Nathan the prophet and among the words of Gad the visionary, 30 together with all his kingship and his mightiness and the times that had passed over him and over Israel and over all the kingdoms of the lands.

The Second of Chronicles

1 And Sol′o·mon the son of David continued to get strength in his kingship, and Jehovah his God was with him and kept making him surpassingly great.

2 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to say the word to all Israel, to the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds and to the judges and to all the chieftains of all Israel, the heads of the paternal houses. 3 Then Sol′o·mon and all the congregation with him went to the high place that was at Gib′e·on; for there was where the tent of meeting of the true God, which Moses the servant of Jehovah had made in the wilderness, happened to be. 4 However, the ark of the true God David had brought up from Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim to the place that David had prepared for it, for he had pitched a tent for it in Jerusalem. 5 And the copper altar that Bez′al·el the son of U′ri the son of Hur had made had been put before the tabernacle of Jehovah; and Sol′o·mon and the congregation applied as usual to it. 6 Sol′o·mon now made offerings there before Jehovah upon the copper altar that belonged to the tent of meeting, and he proceeded to offer upon it a thousand burnt offerings.

7 During that night God appeared to Sol′o·mon and then said to him: “Ask! What shall I give you?” 8 At that Sol′o·mon said to God: “You are the One that exercised great loving-kindness toward David my father and that have made me king in place of him. 9 Now, O Jehovah God, let your promise with David my father prove faithful, for you yourself have made me king over a people as numerous as the dust particles of the earth. 10 Give me now wisdom and knowledge that I may go out before this people and that I may come in, for who could judge this great people of yours?”

11 Then God said to Sol′o·mon: “For the reason that this has proved to be close to your heart and you have not asked for wealth, riches and honor or for the soul of those hating you, neither is it even many days that you have asked for, but you ask for wisdom and knowledge for yourself that you may judge my people over whom I have made you king, 12 the wisdom and the knowledge are being given you; also wealth and riches and honor I shall give you such as no kings that were prior to you happened to have, and such as no one after you will come to have.”

13 So Sol′o·mon came from the high place that was at Gib′e·on, from before the tent of meeting, to Jerusalem and continued to reign over Israel. 14 And Sol′o·mon kept gathering chariots and steeds so that he came to have a thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand steeds, and he kept them stationed in chariot cities and close by the king at Jerusalem. 15 And the king came to make the silver and the gold in Jerusalem like the stones; and cedarwood he made like the sycamore trees that are in the She·phe′lah for great quantity. 16 And there was the export of the horses that Sol′o·mon had from Egypt, and the company of the king’s merchants would themselves take the horse drove for a price. 17 And they customarily brought up and exported from Egypt a chariot for six hundred silver pieces and a horse for a hundred and fifty; and that was the way it was for all the kings of the Hit′tites and the kings of Syria. It was by means of them that they did the exporting.

2 Chronicles

2 Sol′o·mon now gave the word to build a house to Jehovah’s name and a house for his kingship. 2 Accordingly Sol′o·mon counted off seventy thousand men as burden bearers and eighty thousand men as cutters in the mountain, and as overseers over them three thousand six hundred. 3 Further, Sol′o·mon sent to Hi′ram the king of Tyre, saying: “Just as you dealt with David my father and you kept sending him cedarwood to build himself a house in which to dwell,— 4 here I am building a house to the name of Jehovah my God to sanctify it to him, to burn perfumed incense before him, with the constant layer bread and burnt offerings in the morning and in the evening, on the sabbaths and on the new moons and at the festival seasons of Jehovah our God. To time indefinite this will be upon Israel. 5 And the house that I am building will be great, for our God is greater than all the other gods. 6 And who could retain power to build him a house? For the heavens and the heaven of the heavens cannot contain him, and who am I that I should build him a house except for making sacrificial smoke before him? 7 And now send me a skillful man to work in gold and in silver and in copper and in iron and in wool dyed reddish purple and crimson and blue thread, and knowing how to cut engravings, along with the skillful ones that are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father has prepared. 8 And send me timbers of cedar, juniper and algum from Leb′a·non, for I myself well know that your servants are experienced at cutting down the trees of Leb′a·non, (and here my servants are together with your servants,) 9 even for preparing timbers for me in great number, for the house that I am building will be great, yes, in a wonderful way. 10 And, look! to the gatherers of wood, the cutters of the trees, I do give wheat as food for your servants, twenty thousand cors, and barley twenty thousand cors, and wine twenty thousand baths, and oil twenty thousand baths.”

11 At that Hi′ram the king of Tyre said the word in writing and sent it to Sol′o·mon: “Because Jehovah loved his people he has constituted you king over them.” 12 And Hi′ram went on to say: “Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel, who made the heavens and the earth, because he has given to David the king a wise son, experienced in discretion and understanding, who will build a house to Jehovah and a house for his kingship. 13 And now I do send a skillful man, experienced in understanding, belonging to Hi′ram-a′bi, 14 the son of a woman of the sons of Dan but whose father was a man of Tyre, experienced, to work in gold and in silver, in copper, in iron, in stones and in timbers, in wool dyed reddish purple, in blue thread and in fine fabric and in crimson and at cutting every sort of engraving and at designing every sort of device that may be given to him along with your own skillful men and the skillful men of my lord David your father. 15 And now the wheat and the barley, the oil and the wine that my lord has promised, let him send to his servants. 16 As for ourselves, we shall cut down trees from Leb′a·non according to all your need, and we shall bring them to you as rafts by sea to Jop′pa, and you, for your part, will take them up to Jerusalem.”

17 Then Sol′o·mon took a count of all the men that were alien residents, who were in the land of Israel, after the census that David his father had taken of them; and there came to be found a hundred and fifty-three thousand six hundred. 18 So he made seventy thousand of them burden bearers and eighty thousand cutters in the mountain and three thousand six hundred overseers for keeping the people in service.

2 Chronicles

3 Finally Sol′o·mon started to build the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem on Mount Mo·ri′ah, where Jehovah had appeared to David his father, in the place that David had prepared on the threshing floor of Or′nan the Jeb′u·site. 2 Accordingly he started to build in the second month on the second day, in the fourth year of his reign. 3 And these things Sol′o·mon laid as a foundation for building the house of the true God, the length in cubits by the former measurement being sixty cubits, and the width twenty cubits. 4 And the porch that was in front of the length was twenty cubits in front of the width of the house, and its height was a hundred and twenty; and he proceeded to overlay it inside with pure gold. 5 And the great house he covered with juniper wood, after which he covered it with good gold, and then he brought up upon it palm-tree figures and chains. 6 Further, he overlaid the house with precious stone for beauty; and the gold was gold from the gold country. 7 And he went on to cover the house, the rafters, the thresholds and its walls and its doors with gold; and he engraved cherubs upon the walls.

8 And he proceeded to make the house of the Most Holy, its length in relation to the width of the house being twenty cubits, and its own width being twenty cubits; and then he covered it with good gold to the amount of six hundred talents. 9 And the weight for the nails was fifty gold shekels; and the roof chambers he covered with gold.

10 Then he made in the house of the Most Holy two cherubs in the workmanship of images, and overlaid them with gold. 11 As for the wings of the cherubs, their length was twenty cubits, the one wing of five cubits reaching to the wall of the house, and the other wing of five cubits reaching to the wing of the other cherub. 12 And the wing of the one cherub of five cubits was reaching to the wall of the house, and the other wing of five cubits was in contact with the wing of the other cherub. 13 The wings of these cherubs were spread out twenty cubits; and they were standing upon their feet with their faces inward.

14 Further, he made the curtain of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and crimson and fine fabric, and worked in cherubs upon it.

15 Then he made before the house two pillars, thirty-five cubits in length, and the capital that was upon the top of each one was five cubits. 16 Further, he made chains in necklace style and put them upon the tops of the pillars, and made a hundred pomegranates and put them on the chains. 17 And he proceeded to set up the pillars in front of the temple, one to the right and one to the left, after which he called the name of the right-hand one Ja′chin and the name of the left-hand one Bo′az.

2 Chronicles

5 Finally all the work that Sol′o·mon had to do for the house of Jehovah was at its completion, and Sol′o·mon began to bring in the things made holy by David his father; and the silver and the gold and all the utensils he put in the treasures of the house of the true God. 2 It was then that Sol′o·mon proceeded to congregate the older men of Israel and all the heads of the tribes, the chieftains of the paternal houses of the sons of Israel, to Jerusalem, to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah up from the City of David, that is to say, Zion. 3 So all the men of Israel congregated themselves to the king at the festival, that of the seventh month.

4 So all the older men of Israel came, and the Levites began to carry the Ark. 5 And they came bringing up the Ark and the tent of meeting and all the holy utensils that were in the tent. The priests the Levites brought them up. 6 And King Sol′o·mon and all the assembly of Israelites that were keeping their appointment with him before the Ark were sacrificing sheep and cattle that could not be counted or numbered for multitude. 7 Then the priests brought the ark of the covenant of Jehovah into its place, into the innermost room of the house, into the Most Holy, to underneath the wings of the cherubs. 8 Thus the cherubs were continually spreading out their wings over the place of the Ark, so that the cherubs covered over the Ark and its poles from above. 9 But the poles were long, so that the tips of the poles were visible at the Holy in front of the innermost room, but they were not visible outside, and they continue there down to this day. 10 There was nothing in the Ark but the two tablets that Moses had given at Ho′reb, when Jehovah covenanted with the sons of Israel while they were coming out from Egypt.

11 And it came about when the priests came out from the holy place (for all the priests that were to be found had, for their part, sanctified themselves—there was no need to observe the divisions); 12 and the Levites that were singers belonging to all of them, namely, to A′saph, to He′man, to Je·du′thun and to their sons and to their brothers clothed in fine fabric with cymbals and with stringed instruments and harps, were standing to the east of the altar and along with them priests to the number of a hundred and twenty sounding the trumpets; 13 and it came about that as soon as the trumpeters and the singers were as one in causing one sound to be heard in praising and thanking Jehovah, and as soon as they lifted up the sound with the trumpets and with the cymbals and with the instruments of song and with praising Jehovah, “for he is good, for to time indefinite is his loving-kindness,” the house itself was filled with a cloud, the very house of Jehovah, 14 and the priests were not able to stand to minister because of the cloud; for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of the true God.

2 Chronicles

15 Now for Az·a·ri′ah the son of O′ded, the spirit of God came to be upon him. 2 Consequently he went out before A′sa and said to him: “Hear me, O A′sa and all Judah and Benjamin! Jehovah is with YOU as long as YOU prove to be with him; and if YOU search for him, he will let himself be found by YOU, but if YOU leave him he will leave YOU. 3 And many were the days that Israel had been without a true God and without a priest teaching and without Law. 4 But when in their distress they returned to Jehovah the God of Israel and looked for him, then he let himself be found by them. 5 And in those times there was no peace for one going out or for one coming in, because there were many disorders among all the inhabitants of the lands. 6 And they were crushed to pieces, nation against nation and city against city, because God himself kept them in disorder with every sort of distress. 7 And YOU, be courageous and do not let YOUR hands drop down, because there exists a reward for YOUR activity.”

8 And as soon as A′sa heard these words and the prophecy of O′ded the prophet, he took courage and proceeded to cause the disgusting things to vanish from all the land of Judah and Benjamin and from the cities that he had captured from the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and to renew Jehovah’s altar that was before the porch of Jehovah. 9 And he began to collect together all Judah and Benjamin and the alien residents with them from E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh and Sim′e·on, for they had deserted to him from Israel in great number when they saw that Jehovah his God was with him. 10 So they were collected together at Jerusalem in the third month of the fifteenth year of A′sa’s reign. 11 Then they sacrificed to Jehovah on that day from the spoil they had brought, seven hundred cattle and seven thousand sheep. 12 Furthermore, they entered into a covenant to search for Jehovah the God of their forefathers with all their heart and with all their soul; 13 that anyone that would not search for Jehovah the God of Israel should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. 14 So they swore to Jehovah with a loud voice and with joyful shouting and with the trumpets and with horns. 15 And all Judah gave way to rejoicing over the thing sworn; for it was with all their heart that they had sworn and with full pleasure on their part that they had looked for him, so that he let himself be found by them; and Jehovah continued to give them rest all around.

16 As for even Ma′a·cah his grandmother, A′sa the king himself removed her from being lady, because she had made a horrible idol for the sacred pole; and then A′sa cut down her horrible idol and pulverized it and burned it in the torrent valley of Kid′ron. 17 And the high places themselves did not disappear from Israel. Only A′sa’s heart itself proved to be complete all his days. 18 And he proceeded to bring the things made holy by his father and the things made holy by himself into the house of the true God, silver and gold and utensils. 19 As for war, it did not occur down to the thirty-fifth year of A′sa’s reign.

2 Chronicles

17 And Je·hosh′a·phat his son began to reign in place of him and to make his position strong over Israel. 2 And he proceeded to put military forces in all the fortified cities of Judah and to put garrisons in the land of Judah and in the cities of E′phra·im that A′sa his father had captured. 3 And Jehovah continued with Je·hosh′a·phat, because he walked in the former ways of David his forefather and did not search for the Ba′als. 4 For it was for the God of his father that he searched and in his commandment he walked, and not according to the doing of Israel. 5 And Jehovah kept the kingdom firmly established in his hand; and all Judah continued to give presents to Je·hosh′a·phat, and he came to have riches and glory in abundance. 6 And his heart became bold in the ways of Jehovah, and he even removed the high places and the sacred poles from Judah.

7 And in the third year of his reigning he sent for his princes, namely, Ben-ha′il and O·ba·di′ah and Zech·a·ri′ah and Ne·than′el and Mi·cai′ah, to teach in the cities of Judah, 8 and with them the Levites, She·mai′ah and Neth·a·ni′ah and Zeb·a·di′ah and As′a·hel and She·mir′a·moth and Je·hon′a·than and Ad·o·ni′jah and To·bi′jah and Tob-ad·o·ni′jah the Levites, and with them E·lish′a·ma and Je·ho′ram the priests. 9 And they began teaching in Judah, and with them there was the book of Jehovah’s law; and they kept going around through all the cities of Judah and teaching among the people.

10 And the dread of Jehovah came to be upon all the kingdoms of the lands that were all around Judah, and they did not fight against Je·hosh′a·phat. 11 And from the Phi·lis′tines they were bringing to Je·hosh′a·phat presents and money as tribute. The Arabs also were bringing to him flocks, seven thousand seven hundred rams and seven thousand seven hundred he-goats.

12 And Je·hosh′a·phat continued advancing and growing great to a superior degree; and he went on building fortified places and storage cities in Judah. 13 And there were many interests that became his in the cities of Judah; and warriors, valiant, mighty men, were in Jerusalem. 14 And these were their offices by the house of their forefathers: Of Judah the chiefs of thousands, Ad′nah the chief, and with him there were three hundred thousand valiant, mighty men. 15 And under his control there was Je·ho·ha′nan the chief, and with him there were two hundred and eighty thousand. 16 And under his control there was Am·a·si′ah the son of Zich′ri the volunteer for Jehovah, and with him there were two hundred thousand valiant, mighty men. 17 And out of Benjamin there was the valiant, mighty man E·li′a·da, and with him there were two hundred thousand men equipped with the bow and shield. 18 And under his control there was Je·hoz′a·bad, and with him there were a hundred and eighty thousand men outfitted for the army. 19 These were the ones ministering to the king apart from those whom the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.

2 Chronicles

36 Then the people of the land took Je·ho′a·haz the son of Jo·si′ah and made him king in the place of his father in Jerusalem. 2 Twenty-three years old was Je·ho′a·haz when he began to reign, and for three months he reigned in Jerusalem. 3 However, the king of Egypt removed him in Jerusalem and fined the land a hundred silver talents and a gold talent. 4 Furthermore, the king of Egypt made E·li′a·kim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem and changed his name to Je·hoi′a·kim; but his brother Je·ho′a·haz, Ne′cho took and brought to Egypt.

5 Twenty-five years old was Je·hoi′a·kim when he began to reign, and for eleven years he reigned in Jerusalem; and he continued to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah his God. 6 Against him Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon came up that he might bind him with two fetters of copper to carry him off to Babylon. 7 And some of the utensils of the house of Jehovah Neb·u·chad·nez′zar brought to Babylon and then put them in his palace in Babylon. 8 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·hoi′a·kim and his detestable things that he did and what was to be found against him, there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and Judah; and Je·hoi′a·chin his son began to reign in place of him.

9 Eighteen years old was Je·hoi′a·chin when he began to reign, and for three months and ten days he reigned in Jerusalem; and he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 10 And at the return of the year King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar sent and proceeded to bring him to Babylon with desirable articles of the house of Jehovah. Further, he made Zed·e·ki′ah his father’s brother king over Judah and Jerusalem.

11 Twenty-one years old was Zed·e·ki′ah when he began to reign, and for eleven years he reigned in Jerusalem. 12 And he continued to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah his God. He did not humble himself on account of Jeremiah the prophet at the order of Jehovah. 13 And even against King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar he rebelled, who had made him swear by God; and he kept stiffening his neck and hardening his heart so as not to return to Jehovah the God of Israel. 14 Even all the chiefs of the priests and the people themselves committed unfaithfulness on a large scale, according to all the detestable things of the nations, so that they defiled the house of Jehovah which he had sanctified in Jerusalem.

15 And Jehovah the God of their forefathers kept sending against them by means of his messengers, sending again and again, because he felt compassion for his people and for his dwelling. 16 But they were continually making jest at the messengers of the true God and despising his words and mocking at his prophets, until the rage of Jehovah came up against his people, until there was no healing.

17 So he brought up against them the king of the Chal·de′ans, who proceeded to kill their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, neither did he feel compassion for young man or virgin, old or decrepit. Everything He gave into his hand. 18 And all the utensils, great and small, of the house of the true God and the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king and of his princes, everything he brought to Babylon. 19 And he proceeded to burn the house of the true God and pull down the wall of Jerusalem; and all its dwelling towers they burned with fire and also all its desirable articles, so as to cause ruin. 20 Furthermore, he carried off those remaining from the sword captive to Babylon, and they came to be servants to him and his sons until the royalty of Persia began to reign; 21 to fulfill Jehovah’s word by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had paid off its sabbaths. All the days of lying desolated it kept sabbath, to fulfill seventy years.

22 And in the first year of Cyrus the king of Persia, that Jehovah’s word by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Jehovah roused the spirit of Cyrus the king of Persia, so that he caused a cry to pass through all his kingdom, and also in writing, saying: 23 “This is what Cyrus the king of Persia has said, ‘All the kingdoms of the earth Jehovah the God of the heavens has given me, and he himself has commissioned me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whoever there is among YOU of all his people, Jehovah his God be with him. So let him go up.’”

Ezra

7 And after these things in the reign of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king of Persia, Ez′ra the son of Se·rai′ah the son of Az·a·ri′ah the son of Hil·ki′ah 2 the son of Shal′lum the son of Za′dok the son of A·hi′tub 3 the son of Am·a·ri′ah the son of Az·a·ri′ah the son of Me·ra′ioth 4 the son of Zer·a·hi′ah the son of Uz′zi the son of Buk′ki 5 the son of Ab·i·shu′a the son of Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the chief priest— 6 the said Ez′ra himself went up from Babylon; and he was a skilled copyist in the law of Moses, which Jehovah the God of Israel had given, so that the king granted him, according to the hand of Jehovah his God upon him, all his request.

7 Consequently some of the sons of Israel and of the priests and the Levites and the singers and the gatekeepers and the Neth′i·nim went up to Jerusalem in the seventh year of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king. 8 At length he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, that is, in the seventh year of the king. 9 For on the first day of the first month he himself appointed the going up from Babylon, and on the first day of the fifth month he came to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him. 10 For Ez′ra himself had prepared his heart to consult the law of Jehovah and to do it and to teach in Israel regulation and justice.

11 And this is a copy of the letter that King Ar·ta·xerx′es gave Ez′ra the priest the copyist, a copyist of the words of the commandments of Jehovah and of his regulations toward Israel:

12 “Ar·ta·xerx′es, the king of kings, to Ez′ra the priest, the copyist of the law of the God of the heavens: Peace be perfected. And now 13 by me an order has been put through that everyone in my realm of the people of Israel and their priests and Levites that is willing to go to Jerusalem with you should go. 14 Inasmuch as from before the king and his seven counselors an order was sent to investigate concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the law of your God that is in your hand, 15 and to bring the silver and the gold that the king and his counselors have voluntarily given to the God of Israel, whose residence is in Jerusalem, 16 with all the silver and the gold that you find in all the jurisdictional district of Babylon along with the gift of the people and the priests who are voluntarily giving to the house of their God, which is in Jerusalem; 17 accordingly you will promptly buy with this money bulls, rams, lambs and their grain offerings and their drink offerings and you will present them upon the altar of the house of YOUR God, which is in Jerusalem.

18 “And whatever it seems good to you and to your brothers to do with the rest of the silver and gold, according to the will of YOUR God, YOU men will do. 19 And the vessels that are being given to you for the service of the house of your God deliver in full before God at Jerusalem. 20 And the rest of the necessities of the house of your God that it devolves upon you to give, you will give out of the king’s house of treasures.

21 “And by me myself, Ar·ta·xerx′es the king, an order has been put through to all the treasurers that are beyond the River, that everything that Ez′ra the priest, the copyist of the law of the God of the heavens, requests of YOU men it will be done promptly, 22 even to a hundred talents of silver and a hundred cor measures of wheat and a hundred bath measures of wine and a hundred bath measures of oil, and salt without limit. 23 Let all that is by the order of the God of the heavens be done with zeal for the house of the God of the heavens, that there may occur no wrath against the king’s realm and his sons. 24 And to YOU men it is being made known that, as respects any of the priests and the Levites, the musicians, the doorkeepers, the Neth′i·nim, and the workers of this house of God, no tax, tribute or toll is allowed to be imposed upon them.

25 “And you, Ez′ra, according to the wisdom of your God that is in your hand appoint magistrates and judges that they may continually judge all the people that are beyond the River, even all those knowing the laws of your God; and anyone that has not known them YOU men will instruct. 26 And as for everyone that does not become a doer of the law of your God and the law of the king, let judgment be promptly executed upon him, whether for death or for banishment, or for money fine or for imprisonment.”

27 Blessed be Jehovah the God of our forefathers, who has put such a thing into the heart of the king, to beautify the house of Jehovah, which is in Jerusalem! 28 And toward me he has extended loving-kindness before the king and his counselors and as respects all the mighty princes of the king. And I, for my part, strengthened myself according to the hand of Jehovah my God upon me, and I proceeded to collect out of Israel the head ones to go up with me.

Nehemiah

4 Now it came about that, as soon as San·bal′lat heard that we were rebuilding the wall, he became angry and highly offended, and he kept deriding the Jews. 2 And he began to say before his brothers and the military force of Sa·mar′i·a, yes, he began to say: “What are the feeble Jews doing? Will they depend upon themselves? Will they sacrifice? Will they finish up in a day? Will they bring the stones to life out of the heaps of dusty rubbish when they are burned?”

3 Now To·bi′ah the Am′mon·ite was alongside him, and he went on to say: “Even what they are building, if a fox went up against it, he would certainly break down their wall of stones.”

4 Hear, O our God, for we have become an object of contempt; and make their reproach return upon their own head, and give them to the plunder in the land of captivity. 5 And do not cover over their error and their sin from before you. Let it not be wiped out, for they have committed offense against the builders.

6 So we kept building the wall, and the entire wall came to be joined together clear to half its height, and the people continued to have a heart for working.

7 Now it came about that, as soon as San·bal′lat and To·bi′ah and the Arabians and the Am′mon·ites and the Ash′dod·ites heard that the repairing of the walls of Jerusalem had gone forward, for the gaps had started to be stopped up, they became very angry. 8 And all of them began to conspire together to come and fight against Jerusalem and cause me disturbance. 9 But we prayed to our God and kept a guard posted against them day and night on account of them.

10 And Judah began to say: “The power of the burden bearer has stumbled, and there is a great deal of rubbish; and we ourselves are not able to build on the wall.”

11 Moreover, our adversaries kept saying: “They will not know and they will not see until we come right in among them, and we shall certainly kill them and put a stop to the work.”

12 And it came about that, whenever the Jews dwelling close by them came in, they proceeded to say to us ten times: “They will come up from all the places where YOU people will return to us.”

13 So I kept men posted at the lowest parts of the place behind the wall at the open places, and I kept the people posted by families with their swords, their lances and their bows. 14 When I saw their fear I immediately rose and said to the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the people: “Do not be afraid on their account. Jehovah the great and the fear-inspiring One keep in YOUR mind; and fight for YOUR brothers, YOUR sons and YOUR daughters, YOUR wives and YOUR homes.”

15 Now it came about that as soon as our enemies heard that it had become known to us, so that the true God had frustrated their counsel and we had all of us gone back to the wall, each one to his work, 16 yes, it came about that from that day forward half of my young men were active in the work and half of them were holding the lances, the shields and the bows and the coats of mail; and the princes were behind the whole house of Judah. 17 As for the builders on the wall and those who were carrying the burden of load bearers, each one was active in the work with his one hand while the other hand was holding the missile. 18 And the builders were girded, each one with his sword upon his hip, while building; and the one to blow the horn was alongside me.

19 And I proceeded to say to the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the people: “The work is large and extensive, and we are spread about upon the wall far apart from one another. 20 In the place where YOU hear the sound of the horn, there is where YOU will collect yourselves together to us. Our God himself will fight for us.”

21 While we were active in the work, the other half of them also were holding the lances, from the ascending of the dawn until the stars came out. 22 Besides, at that time I said to the people: “Let the men spend the night, each one with his attendant, in the midst of Jerusalem, and they must become for us a guard by night and workers by day.” 23 As for me and my brothers and my attendants and the men of the guard who were behind me, we were not taking off our garments, each one having his missile in his right hand.

Job

3 It was after this that Job opened his mouth and began to call down evil upon his day. 2 Job now answered and said:

3 “Let the day perish on which I came to be born,

Also the night that someone said, ‘An able-bodied man has been conceived!’

4 As for that day, let it become darkness.

Let not God look for it from above,

Nor let daylight beam upon it.

5 Let darkness and deep shadow reclaim it.

Let a rain cloud reside over it.

Let the things that darken a day terrorize it.

6 That night—let gloom take it;

Let it not feel glad among the days of a year;

Among the number of the lunar months let it not enter.

7 Look! That night—let it become sterile;

Let no joyful cry come in it.

8 Let cursers of the day execrate it,

Those ready to awaken Le·vi′a·than.

9 Let the stars of its twilight grow dark;

Let it wait for the light and there be none;

And let it not see the beams of dawn.

10 For it did not close the doors of my mother’s belly,

And so conceal trouble from my eyes.

11 Why from the womb did I not proceed to die?

Why did I not come forth from the belly itself and then expire?

12 Why was it that knees confronted me,

And why breasts that I should take suck?

13 For by now I should have lain down that I might be undisturbed;

I should have slept then; I should be at rest

14 With kings and counselors of the earth,

Those building desolate places for themselves,

15 Or with princes who have gold,

Those who fill their houses with silver;

16 Or, like a hidden miscarriage, I should not come to be,

Like children that have seen no light.

17 There the wicked themselves have ceased from agitation,

And there those weary in power are at rest.

18 Together prisoners themselves are at ease;

They actually do not hear the voice of one driving them to work.

19 Small and great are there the same,

And the slave is set free from his master.

20 Why does he give light to one having trouble,

And life to those bitter of soul?

21 Why are there those waiting for death, and it is not,

Although they keep digging for it more than for hidden treasures?

22 Those who are rejoicing to gleefulness,

They exult because they find a burial place.

23 Why does he give light to able-bodied man, whose way has been concealed,

And whom God hedges in?

24 For before my food my sighing comes,

And like waters my roaring cries pour forth;

25 Because a dreadful thing I have dreaded, and it comes upon me;

And what I have been scared of comes to me.

26 I have not been carefree, nor have I been undisturbed,

Nor been at rest, and yet agitation comes.”

Job

4 And El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite proceeded to reply and say:

2 “If one does try out a word to you, will you become weary?

But to put a restraint on words who is able?

3 Look! You have corrected many,

And the weak hands you used to strengthen.

4 Anyone stumbling, your words would raise up;

And knees giving way you would make firm.

5 But this time it comes to you, and you become weary;

It touches even you, and you get disturbed.

6 Is not your reverence the basis of your confidence?

Is not your hope even the integrity of your ways?

7 Remember, please: Who that is innocent has ever perished?

And where have the upright ever been effaced?

8 According to what I have seen, those devising what is hurtful

And those sowing trouble will themselves reap it.

9 Through the breath of God they perish,

And through the spirit of his anger they come to an end.

10 There is the roaring of a lion, and the voice of a young lion,

But the teeth of maned young lions do get broken down.

11 A lion is perishing from there being no prey,

And the cubs of a lion are separated from one another.

12 Now to me a word was stealthily brought,

And my ear proceeded to get a whisper of it,

13 In disquieting thoughts from visions of the night,

When deep sleep falls upon men.

14 A dread came over me, and a trembling,

And the multitude of my bones it filled with dread.

15 And a spirit itself went passing over my face;

The hair of my flesh began to bristle.

16 It began to stand still,

But I did not recognize its appearance;

A form was in front of my eyes;

There was a calm, and I now heard a voice:

17 ‘Mortal man—can he be more just than God himself?

Or can able-bodied man be cleaner than his own Maker?’

18 Look! In his servants he has no faith,

And his messengers he charges with faultiness.

19 How much more so with those dwelling in houses of clay,

Whose foundation is in the dust!

One crushes them more quickly than a moth.

20 From morning to evening they are crushed to pieces;

Without anyone’s taking it to heart they perish forever.

21 Has not their tent cord within them been pulled out?

They die for lack of wisdom.

Job

8 And Bil′dad the Shu′hite proceeded to answer and say:

2 “How long will you keep uttering these things,

When the sayings of your mouth are but a powerful wind?

3 Will God himself pervert judgment,

Or will the Almighty himself pervert righteousness?

4 If your own sons have sinned against him,

So that he lets them go into the hand of their revolt,

5 If you yourself will look for God,

And if of the Almighty you will implore favor,

6 If you are pure and upright,

By now he would awake for you

And he would certainly restore your righteous abiding place.

7 Also, your beginning may have proved to be a small thing,

But your own end afterward would grow very great.

8 Indeed, ask, please, of the former generation,

And direct your attention to the things searched out by their fathers.

9 For we were only yesterday, and we know nothing,

Because our days on earth are a shadow.

10 Will not they themselves instruct you, tell you,

And from their heart will they not bring forth words?

11 Will a papyrus plant grow tall without a swampy place?

Will a reed grow big without water?

12 While it is yet in its bud, not plucked off,

Even ahead of all other grass it will dry up.

13 Thus are the pathways of all those forgetting God,

And the very hope of an apostate will perish,

14 Whose confidence is cut off,

And whose trust is a spider’s house.

15 He will lean upon his house, but it will not keep standing;

He will take hold of it, but it will not last.

16 He is full of sap before the sun,

And in his garden his own twig goes forth.

17 In a stone heap his roots become interwoven,

A house of stones he beholds.

18 If one swallows him up from his place,

It will also certainly deny him, saying, ‘I have not seen you.’

19 Look! That is the dissolving of his way;

And from the dust others spring up.

20 Look! God himself will not reject anyone blameless,

Neither will he take hold of the hand of evildoers,

21 Until he fills your mouth with laughter,

And your lips with joyful shouting.

22 The very ones hating you will be clothed with shame,

And the tent of wicked ones will not be.”

Job

9 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “For a fact I do know that it is so.

But how can mortal man be in the right in a case with God?

3 If he should find delight in contending with him,

He cannot answer him once out of a thousand.

4 He is wise in heart and strong in power.

Who can show stubbornness to him and come off uninjured?

5 He is moving mountains away, so that people do not even know of them,

He who has overthrown them in his anger.

6 He is making the earth go quaking from its place,

So that its very pillars shudder.

7 He is saying to the sun that it should not shine forth,

And around stars he puts a seal,

8 Stretching out the heavens by himself

And treading upon the high waves of the sea;

9 Making the Ash constellation, the Ke′sil constellation,

And the Ki′mah constellation and the interior rooms of the South;

10 Doing great things unsearchable,

And wonderful things without number.

11 Look! He passes by me and I do not see him,

And he moves on and I do not discern him.

12 Look! He snatches away. Who can resist him?

Who will say to him, ‘What are you doing?’

13 God himself will not turn back his anger;

Beneath him the helpers of a stormer must bow down.

14 How much more so in case I myself answer him!

I will choose my words with him,

15 Whom I would not answer, even though I were really in the right.

Of my opponent-at-law I would implore favor.

16 If I called him, would he answer me?

I do not believe that he would give ear to my voice;

17 Who with a storm bruises me

And certainly makes my wounds many for no reason.

18 He will not grant me my taking of a fresh breath,

For he keeps glutting me with bitter things.

19 If in power anyone is strong, there he is;

And if in justice anyone is strong, O that I may be summoned!

20 If I were in the right, my own mouth would pronounce me wicked;

Were I blameless, then he would declare me crooked.

21 Were I blameless, I would not know my soul;

I would refuse my life.

22 One thing there is. That is why I do say,

‘One blameless, also a wicked one, he is bringing to their end.’

23 If a flash flood itself should cause death suddenly,

At the very despair of the innocent ones he would mock.

24 Earth itself has been given into the hand of the wicked one;

The face of its judges he covers.

If not, who, then, is it?

25 Also my own days have become swifter than a runner;

They have run away, they will certainly not see good.

26 They have moved on like reed boats,

Like an eagle that darts to and fro for something to eat.

27 If I have said, ‘Let me forget my concern,

Let me alter my countenance and brighten up,’

28 I have been scared of all my pains;

I do know that you will not hold me innocent.

29 I myself am to become wicked.

Why is it that I toil merely in vain?

30 If I actually washed myself in snow water,

And I actually cleansed my hands in potash,

31 Then in a pit you would dip me,

And my garments would certainly detest me.

32 For he is not a man like me that I should answer him,

That we should come together in judgment.

33 There exists no person to decide between us,

That he should put his hand upon both of us.

34 Let him remove his rod from upon me,

And his frightfulness, let it not terrify me.

35 Let me speak and not be afraid of him,

For I am not so disposed in myself.

Job

14 “Man, born of woman,

Is short-lived and glutted with agitation.

2 Like a blossom he has come forth and is cut off,

And he runs away like the shadow and does not keep existing.

3 Yes, upon this one you have opened your eye,

And me you bring into judgment with you.

4 Who can produce someone clean out of someone unclean?

There is not one.

5 If his days are decided,

The number of his months is with you;

A decree for him you have made that he may not go beyond.

6 Turn your gaze from upon him that he may have rest,

Until he finds pleasure as a hired laborer does in his day.

7 For there exists hope for even a tree.

If it gets cut down, it will even sprout again,

And its own twig will not cease to be.

8 If its root grows old in the earth

And in the dust its stump dies,

9 At the scent of water it will sprout

And it will certainly produce a bough like a new plant.

10 But an able-bodied man dies and lies vanquished;

And an earthling man expires, and where is he?

11 Waters do disappear from a sea,

And a river itself drains off and dries up.

12 Man also has to lie down and does not get up.

Until heaven is no more they will not wake up,

Nor will they be aroused from their sleep.

13 O that in She′ol you would conceal me,

That you would keep me secret until your anger turns back,

That you would set a time limit for me and remember me!

14 If an able-bodied man dies can he live again?

All the days of my compulsory labor I shall wait,

Until my relief comes.

15 You will call, and I myself shall answer you.

For the work of your hands you will have a yearning.

16 For now you keep counting my very steps;

You watch for nothing but my sin.

17 Sealed up in a bag is my revolt,

And you apply glue over my error.

18 However, a mountain itself, falling, will fade away,

And even a rock will be moved away from its place.

19 Water certainly rubs away even stones;

Its outpouring washes off earth’s dust.

So you have destroyed the very hope of mortal man.

20 You overpower him forever so that he goes away;

You are disfiguring his face so that you send him away.

21 His sons get honored, but he does not know it;

And they become insignificant, but he does not consider them.

22 Only his own flesh while upon him will keep aching,

And his own soul while within him will keep mourning.”

Job

15 And El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite proceeded to answer and say:

2 “Will a wise person himself answer with windy knowledge,

Or will he fill his belly with the east wind?

3 Merely reproving with a word will be of no use,

And mere utterances will be of no benefit by themselves.

4 However, you yourself make fear before God to have no force,

And you diminish the having of any concern before God.

5 For your error trains your mouth,

And you choose the tongue of shrewd people.

6 Your mouth pronounces you wicked, and not I;

And your own lips answer against you.

7 Were you the very first man to be born,

Or before the hills were you brought forth with labor pains?

8 To the confidential talk of God do you listen,

And do you limit wisdom to yourself?

9 What do you actually know that we do not know?

What do you understand that is not also with us?

10 Both the gray-headed and the aged one are with us,

The one greater than your father in days.

11 Are the consolations of God not enough for you,

Or a word spoken gently with you?

12 Why does your heart carry you away,

And why do your eyes flash?

13 For you turn your spirit against God himself,

And you have caused words to go forth from your own mouth.

14 What is mortal man that he should be clean,

Or that anyone born of a woman should be in the right?

15 Look! In his holy ones he has no faith,

And the heavens themselves are actually not clean in his eyes.

16 How much less so when one is detestable and corrupt,

A man who is drinking in unrighteousness just like water!

17 I shall declare it to you. Listen to me!

Even this I have beheld, so let me relate it,

18 That which wise ones themselves tell

And which they did not hide, it being from their fathers.

19 To them alone the land was given,

And no stranger passed through the midst of them.

20 All his days a wicked one is suffering torture,

Even the very number of years that have been reserved for the tyrant.

21 The sound of dreadful things is in his ears;

During peace a despoiler himself comes upon him.

22 He does not believe that he will come back out of darkness,

And he is reserved for a sword.

23 He is straying about in search of bread—where is it?

He well knows that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.

24 Distress and anguish keep terrifying him;

They overpower him like a king in readiness for the assault.

25 Because he stretches out his hand against God himself,

And over the Almighty he tries to show himself superior;

26 Because he runs against him stiff-neckedly,

With the thick bosses of his shields;

27 Because he actually covers his face with his fattiness

And he puts on fat upon his loins,

28 He merely resides in cities that are to be effaced;

In houses in which people will not keep dwelling,

Which certainly prove destined for heaps of stones.

29 He will not grow rich and his wealth will not mount up,

Nor will he spread out the acquisition of them over the earth.

30 He will not turn away from darkness;

His twig a flame will dry up,

And he will turn aside by a blast of His mouth.

31 Let him put no faith in worthlessness, being led astray,

For mere worthlessness will prove to be what he gets in exchange;

32 Before his day will it be fulfilled.

And his shoot itself will certainly not grow luxuriantly.

33 He will thrust away his unripe grapes just like a vine,

And cast off his blossoms just like an olive tree.

34 For the assembly of apostates is sterile,

And fire itself must eat up the tents of bribery.

35 There is a conceiving of trouble and a giving birth to what is hurtful,

And their belly itself prepares deceit.”

Job

16 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “I have heard many things like these.

All of YOU are troublesome comforters!

3 Is there an end to windy words?

Or what galls you, that you answer?

4 I myself also could well speak as YOU men do.

If only YOUR souls existed where my soul is,

Would I be brilliant in words against YOU,

And would I wag my head against YOU?

5 I would strengthen YOU with the words of my mouth,

And the consolation of my own lips would hold back—.

6 If I do speak, my own pain is not held back,

And if I do cease doing so, what goes away from me?

7 Only now he has made me weary;

He has made all those assembling with me desolate.

8 You also seize me. It has become a witness,

So that my leanness rises up against me. In my face it testifies.

9 His very anger has torn me to pieces, and he harbors animosity against me.

He actually grinds his teeth against me.

My adversary himself sharpens his eyes against me.

10 They have opened their mouth wide against me,

With reproach they have struck my cheeks,

In large number they mass themselves against me.

11 God hands me over to young boys,

And into the hands of wicked ones he throws me headlong.

12 I had come to be at ease, but he proceeded to shake me up;

And he grabbed me by the back of the neck and proceeded to smash me,

And he sets me up as a target for himself.

13 His archers encircle me;

He splits open my kidneys and feels no compassion;

He pours out my gallbladder to the very earth.

14 He keeps breaking through me with breach after breach;

He runs at me like a mighty one.

15 Sackcloth I have sewed together over my skin,

And I have thrust my horn in the very dust.

16 My face itself has become reddened from weeping,

And upon my eyelids there is deep shadow,

17 Although there is no violence upon my palms,

And my prayer is pure.

18 O earth, do not cover my blood!

And let there prove to be no place for my outcry!

19 Also now, look! in the heavens is one testifying about me,

And my witness is in the heights.

20 My companions are spokesmen against me;

To God my eye has looked sleeplessly.

21 And the decision is to be made between an able-bodied man and God,

The same as between a son of man and his fellow.

22 For just a few years are to come,

And by the path by which I shall not return I shall go away.

Job

20 And Zo′phar the Na′a·ma·thite proceeded to reply and say:

2 “Therefore do my own disquieting thoughts themselves answer me,

Even on account of my inward excitement.

3 An insulting exhortation to me I hear;

And a spirit without the understanding that I have replies to me.

4 Have you at all times known this very thing,

Since man was put upon the earth,

5 That the joyful cry of wicked people is short

And the rejoicing of an apostate is for a moment?

6 Although his excellency ascends to heaven itself

And his very head reaches to the clouds,

7 Like his manure cakes he perishes forever;

The very ones seeing him will say, ‘Where is he?’

8 Like a dream he will fly off, and they will not find him;

And he will be chased away like a vision of the night.

9 The eye that has caught sight of him will not do so again,

And no more will his place behold him.

10 His own sons will seek the favor of lowly people,

And his own hands will give back his valuable things.

11 His own bones have been full of his youthful vigor,

But with him it will lie down in mere dust.

12 If what is bad tastes sweet in his mouth,

If he causes it to melt away under his tongue,

13 If he has compassion upon it and does not leave it,

And if he keeps holding it back in the midst of his palate,

14 His food itself will certainly be changed in his own intestines;

It will be the gall of cobras within him.

15 Wealth he has swallowed down, but he will vomit it up;

God will drive it out from his very belly.

16 The venom of cobras he will suck;

The tongue of a viper will kill him.

17 He will never see the watercourses,

Torrential streams of honey and butter.

18 He will be giving back his acquired property and will not swallow it down;

Like wealth from his trade, but which he will not enjoy.

19 For he has crushed to pieces, he has left lowly ones;

He has snatched away a house itself that he did not proceed to build.

20 For he will certainly know no ease in his belly;

By means of his desirable things he will not escape.

21 There is nothing left over for him to devour;

That is why his well-being will not endure.

22 While his plenty is at its peak he will be feeling anxious;

All the power of misfortune itself will come against him.

23 Let it occur that, to fill his belly,

He will send his burning anger upon him

And will rain it upon him, into his bowels.

24 He will run away from armor of iron;

A bow of copper will cut him up.

25 A missile itself will even go out through his back,

And a glittering weapon out through his gall;

Frightful objects will go against him.

26 All darkness will be reserved for his treasured things;

A fire that no one fanned will eat him up;

It will go badly with a survivor in his tent.

27 Heaven will uncover his error,

And earth will be in revolt against him.

28 A heavy shower will roll his house away;

There will be things poured forth on the day of his anger.

29 This is the share of the wicked man from God,

Even his stated inheritance from God.”

Job

21 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “Listen, YOU men, attentively to my word,

And let this become YOUR consolation.

3 Put up with me, and I myself shall speak;

And after my speaking you may each deride.

4 As for me, is my concern expressed to man?

Or why is it that my spirit does not get impatient?

5 Turn YOUR faces to me and stare in amazement,

And put YOUR hand upon YOUR mouth.

6 And if I have remembered, I have also become disturbed,

And shuddering has taken hold of my flesh.

7 Why is it that the wicked themselves keep living,

Have grown old, also have become superior in wealth?

8 Their offspring are firmly established with them in their sight,

And their descendants before their eyes.

9 Their houses are peace itself, free from dread,

And the rod of God is not upon them.

10 His own bull actually impregnates, and it does not waste semen;

His cow brings forth and suffers no abortion.

11 They keep sending out their young boys just like a flock,

And their own male children go skipping about.

12 They continue raising their voice with the tambourine and harp,

And keep rejoicing at the sound of the pipe.

13 They spend their days in good times,

And in a moment down to She′ol they descend.

14 And they say to the true God, ‘Turn away from us!

And in the knowledge of your ways we have found no delight.

15 What does the Almighty amount to, that we should serve him,

And how do we benefit ourselves in that we have come in touch with him?’

16 Look! Their well-being is not in their own power.

The very counsel of wicked ones has kept far from me.

17 How many times is the lamp of the wicked ones extinguished,

And how many times does their disaster come upon them?

How many times in his anger does he apportion destruction?

18 Do they become like straw before a wind,

And like chaff that a storm wind has stolen away?

19 God himself will store up one’s hurtfulness for one’s own sons;

He will reward him that he may know it.

20 His eyes will see his decay,

And from the rage of the Almighty he will drink.

21 For what will his delight be in his house after him,

When the number of his months will really be cut in two?

22 Will he teach knowledge even to God,

When that One himself judges high ones?

23 This very one will die during his full self-sufficiency,

When he is altogether carefree and at ease;

24 When his own thighs have become full of fat

And the very marrow of his bones is being kept moist.

25 And this other one will die with a bitter soul

When he has not eaten of good things.

26 Together in the dust they will lie down

And maggots themselves will form a cover over them.

27 Look! I well know the thoughts of YOU men

And the schemes with which YOU would act violently against me.

28 For YOU say, ‘Where is the house of the noble one,

And where is the tent, the tabernacles of wicked ones?’

29 Have YOU not asked those traveling over the roads?

And do YOU not carefully inspect their very signs,

30 That at the day of disaster an evil one is spared,

At the day of fury he is delivered?

31 Who will tell him of his way to his very face?

And for what he himself has done who will reward him?

32 As for him, to the graveyard he will be brought,

And over a tomb a vigil will be kept.

33 To him the clods of earth of a torrent valley will certainly become sweet,

And after him he will drag all mankind,

And those before him were without number.

34 So how vainly YOU men try to comfort me,

And YOUR very replies do remain as unfaithfulness!”

Job

22 And El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite proceeded to answer and say:

2 “Can an able-bodied man be of use to God himself,

That anyone having insight should be of use toward him?

3 Does the Almighty have any delight in that you are righteous,

Or any gain in that you make your way blameless?

4 For your reverence will he reprove you,

Will he come with you into the judgment?

5 Is not your own badness too much already,

And will there be no end to your errors?

6 For you seize a pledge from your brothers without cause,

And you strip off even the garments of naked people.

7 You do not give the tired one a drink of water,

And from the hungry one you hold back bread.

8 As for a man of strength, the land is his,

And one who is treated with partiality himself dwells in it.

9 Widows you have sent away empty-handed,

And the arms of fatherless boys are crushed.

10 That is why bird traps are all around you,

And sudden dread disturbs you;

11 Or darkness, so that you cannot see,

And a heaving mass of water itself covers you.

12 Is not God the height of heaven?

Also see the sum total of the stars, that they are high.

13 And yet you have said: ‘What does God really know?

Through thick gloom can he judge?

14 Clouds are a concealment place for him so that he does not see,

And on the vault of heaven he walks about.’

15 Will you keep to the very way of long ago

That hurtful men have trodden,

16 Men who have been snatched away before their time,

Whose foundation is poured away just as a river,

17 Who are saying to the true God: ‘Turn away from us!

And what can the Almighty accomplish against us?’

18 Yet he himself has filled their houses with good things;

And the very counsel of wicked ones has kept far from me.

19 The righteous ones will see and rejoice,

And the innocent one himself will hold them in derision:

20 ‘Truly our antagonists have been effaced;

And what is left of them a fire will certainly eat up.’

21 Acquaint yourself, please, with him, and keep peace;

Thereby good things will come to you.

22 Take, please, the law from his own mouth,

And put his sayings in your heart.

23 If you return to the Almighty, you will be built up;

If you will keep unrighteousness far from your tent,

24 And if there is a placing of precious ore in the dust

And gold of O′phir in the rock of torrent valleys,

25 The Almighty also will indeed become your precious ores,

And silver, the choicest, to you.

26 For then in the Almighty you will find your exquisite delight,

And you will raise your face to God himself.

27 You will make entreaty to him, and he will hear you;

And your vows you will pay.

28 And you will decide on something, and it will stand for you;

And upon your ways light will certainly shine.

29 For there must be a humiliation when you speak arrogantly;

But one with downcast eyes he will save.

30 He will rescue an innocent man,

And you will certainly be rescued for the cleanness of your hands.”

Job

23 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “Even today my state of concern is rebelliousness;

My own hand is heavy on account of my sighing.

3 O that I really knew where I might find him!

I would come clear to his fixed place.

4 I would present before him a case of justice,

And my mouth I would fill with counterarguments;

5 I would know the words with which he answers me,

And I would consider what he says to me.

6 Would he with an abundance of power contend with me?

O no! Surely he himself would pay heed to me.

7 There the upright one himself will certainly set matters straight with him,

And I would go safe forever from my judge.

8 Look! To the east I go, and he is not there;

And back again, and I cannot discern him;

9 To the left where he is working, but I cannot behold him;

He turns aside to the right, but I do not see him.

10 For he well knows the way I take.

After he has tested me out, I shall come forth as gold itself.

11 Of his steps my foot has laid hold;

His way I have kept, and I do not deviate.

12 From the commandment of his lips I do not move away.

I have treasured up the sayings of his mouth more than what is prescribed for me.

13 And he is in one mind, and who can resist him?

And his own soul has a desire, and he will do it.

14 For he will carry out completely what is prescribed for me,

And things like these are many with him.

15 That is why I feel disturbed because of him;

I show myself attentive and am in dread of him.

16 Even God himself has made my heart timid,

And the Almighty himself has disturbed me.

17 For I have not been put to silence because of darkness,

Nor because gloom has covered my own face.

Job

26 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “O how much help you have been to one without power!

O how you have saved an arm that is without strength!

3 How much you have advised one that is without wisdom,

And you have made practical wisdom itself known to the multitude!

4 To whom have you told words,

And whose breath has come forth from you?

5 Those impotent in death keep trembling

Beneath the waters and those residing in them.

6 She′ol is naked in front of him,

And the place of destruction has no covering.

7 He is stretching out the north over the empty place,

Hanging the earth upon nothing;

8 Wrapping up the waters in his clouds,

So that the cloud mass is not split under them;

9 Enclosing the face of the throne,

Spreading out over it his cloud.

10 He has described a circle upon the face of the waters,

To where light ends in darkness.

11 The very pillars of heaven shake,

And they are amazed because of his rebuke.

12 By his power he has stirred up the sea,

And by his understanding he has broken the stormer to pieces.

13 By his wind he has polished up heaven itself,

His hand has pierced the gliding serpent.

14 Look! These are the fringes of his ways,

And what a whisper of a matter has been heard of him!

But of his mighty thunder who can show an understanding?”

Job

34 And E·li′hu continued to answer and say:

2 “Listen, YOU wise ones, to my words;

And YOU who know, give ear to me.

3 For the ear itself makes a test of words,

Just as the palate tastes when eating.

4 Judgment let us choose for ourselves;

Let us know among ourselves what is good.

5 For Job has said, ‘I certainly am in the right,

But God himself has turned aside the judgment of me.

6 Against my own judgment do I tell lies?

My severe wound is incurable though there is no transgression.’

7 What able-bodied man is like Job,

Who drinks up derision like water?

8 And he is certainly on his way to companionship with practicers of what is hurtful

And to walking with men of wickedness.

9 For he has said, ‘An able-bodied man does not profit

By his taking pleasure in God.’

10 Therefore, YOU men of heart, listen to me.

Far be it from the true God to act wickedly,

And the Almighty to act unjustly!

11 For according to the way earthling man acts he will reward him,

And according to the path of man he will cause it to come upon him.

12 Yes, for a fact, God himself does not act wickedly,

And the Almighty himself does not pervert judgment.

13 Who has assigned to him the earth,

And who has appointed to him the productive land, even all of it?

14 If he sets his heart upon anyone,

If that one’s spirit and breath he gathers to himself,

15 All flesh will expire together,

And earthling man himself will return to the very dust.

16 So if you have understanding, do listen to this;

Do give ear to the sound of my words.

17 Really will anyone hating justice control,

And if a powerful one is righteous will you pronounce him wicked?

18 Shall one say to a king, ‘You are good for nothing’?

To nobles, ‘You are wicked’?

19 There is One who has not shown partiality to princes

And has not given more consideration to the noble one than to the lowly one,

For all of them are the work of his hands.

20 In a moment they die, even in the middle of the night;

The people shake back and forth and pass away,

And powerful ones depart by no hand.

21 For his eyes are upon the ways of man,

And all his steps he sees.

22 There is no darkness nor any deep shadow

For those practicing what is hurtful to conceal themselves there.

23 For he sets no appointed time for any man

To go to God in judgment.

24 He breaks powerful ones without any investigation,

And he makes others stand up instead of them.

25 Therefore he recognizes what their works are,

And he does overthrow them at night, and they get crushed.

26 As wicked ones he does slap them

In the place of onlookers;

27 For the reason that they have turned aside from following him,

And none of his ways have they considered,

28 So as to cause the outcry of the lowly one to come to him;

And so he hears the outcry of the afflicted ones.

29 When he himself causes quietness, who, then, can condemn?

And when he conceals his face, who can behold him,

Whether it is toward a nation or toward a man, it being the same thing?

30 So that an apostate man may not reign,

Nor there be snares of the people.

31 For will anyone actually say to God himself,

‘I have borne, although I do not act corruptly;

32 Although I behold nothing, instruct me yourself;

If any unrighteousness I have committed,

I shall not do it again’?

33 Will he make good for it from your standpoint because you do refuse judgment,

Because you yourself choose, and not I?

Even what you well know, speak.

34 Men of heart themselves will say to me—

Even a wise able-bodied man that is listening to me,

35 ‘Job himself speaks without knowledge,

And his words are without his having insight.’

36 My father, let Job be tested out to the limit

Over his replies among men of hurtfulness.

37 For on top of his sin he adds revolt;

Among us he claps his hands and multiplies his sayings against the true God!”

Job

38 And Jehovah proceeded to answer Job out of the windstorm and say:

2 “Who is this that is obscuring counsel

By words without knowledge?

3 Gird up your loins, please, like an able-bodied man,

And let me question you, and you inform me.

4 Where did you happen to be when I founded the earth?

Tell me, if you do know understanding.

5 Who set its measurements, in case you know,

Or who stretched out upon it the measuring line?

6 Into what have its socket pedestals been sunk down,

Or who laid its cornerstone,

7 When the morning stars joyfully cried out together,

And all the sons of God began shouting in applause?

8 And who barricaded the sea with doors,

Which began to go forth as when it burst out from the womb;

9 When I put the cloud as its garment

And thick gloom as its swaddling band,

10 And I proceeded to break up my regulation upon it

And to set a bar and doors,

11 And I went on to say, ‘This far you may come, and no farther;

And here your proud waves are limited’?

12 Was it from your days onward that you commanded the morning?

Did you cause the dawn to know its place,

13 To take hold on the extremities of the earth,

That the wicked ones might be shaken out from it?

14 It transforms itself like clay under a seal,

And things take their station as in clothing.

15 And from the wicked ones their light is held back,

And the high arm itself gets broken.

16 Have you come to the sources of the sea,

Or in search of the watery deep have you walked about?

17 Have the gates of death been uncovered to you,

Or the gates of deep shadow can you see?

18 Have you intelligently considered the broad spaces of the earth?

Tell, if you have come to know it all.

19 Where, now, is the way to where light resides?

As for darkness, where, now, is its place,

20 That you should take it to its boundary

And that you should understand the roadways to its house?

21 Have you come to know because at that time you were being born,

And because in number your days are many?

22 Have you entered into the storehouses of the snow,

Or do you see even the storehouses of the hail,

23 Which I have kept back for the time of distress,

For the day of fight and war?

24 Where, now, is the way by which the light distributes itself,

And the east wind scatters about upon the earth?

25 Who has divided a channel for the flood

And a way for the thunderous storm cloud,

26 To make it rain upon the land where there is no man,

Upon the wilderness in which there is no earthling man,

27 To satisfy storm-stricken and desolate places

And to cause the growth of grass to sprout?

28 Does there exist a father for the rain,

Or who gave birth to the dewdrops?

29 Out of whose belly does the ice actually come forth,

And as for the hoarfrost of heaven, who indeed brings it to birth?

30 The very waters keep themselves hidden as by stone,

And the surface of the watery deep makes itself compact.

31 Can you tie fast the bonds of the Ki′mah constellation,

Or can you loosen the very cords of the Ke′sil constellation?

32 Can you bring forth the Maz′za·roth constellation in its appointed time?

And as for the Ash constellation alongside its sons, can you conduct them?

33 Have you come to know the statutes of the heavens,

Or could you put its authority in the earth?

34 Can you raise your voice even to the cloud,

So that a heaving mass of water itself may cover you?

35 Can you send forth lightnings that they may go

And say to you, ‘Here we are!’?

36 Who put wisdom in the cloud layers,

Or who gave understanding to the sky phenomenon?

37 Who can exactly number the clouds in wisdom,

Or the water jars of heaven—who can tip them over,

38 When the dust pours out as into a molten mass,

And the clods of earth themselves get stuck together?

39 Can you hunt prey for a lion itself

And can you satisfy the lively appetite of young lions,

40 When they crouch in the hiding places,

Or keep lying in the covert for an ambush?

41 Who prepares for the raven its food

When its own young ones cry to God for help,

When they keep wandering about because there is nothing to eat?

Job

39 “Have you come to know the appointed time for the mountain goats of the crag to give birth?

Do you observe just when the hinds bring forth with birth pangs?

2 Do you count the lunar months that they fulfill,

Or have you come to know the appointed time that they give birth?

3 They bow down when they cast forth their young ones,

When they get rid of their pangs.

4 Their sons become robust, they get big in the open field;

They actually go forth and do not return to them.

5 Who sent forth the zebra free,

And who loosened the very bands of the wild ass,

6 Whose house I have appointed the desert plain

And whose dwelling places the salt country?

7 It laughs at the turmoil of a town;

The noises of a stalker it does not hear.

8 It explores mountains for its pasturage

And after every sort of green plant it seeks.

9 Does a wild bull want to serve you,

Or will it spend the night by your manger?

10 Will you bind a wild bull fast with its ropes in the furrow,

Or will it harrow low plains after you?

11 Will you trust in it because its power is abundant,

And will you leave your toil to it?

12 Will you rely on it that it will bring back your seed

And that it will gather to your threshing floor?

13 Has the wing of the female ostrich flapped joyously,

Or has she the pinions of a stork and the plumage?

14 For she leaves her eggs to the earth itself

And in the dust she keeps them warm,

15 And she forgets that some foot may crush them

Or even a wild beast of the field may tread on them.

16 She does treat her sons roughly, as if not hers—

In vain is her toil because she has no dread.

17 For God has made her forget wisdom,

And he has not given her a share in understanding.

18 At the time she flaps her wings on high,

She laughs at the horse and at its rider.

19 Can you give to the horse mightiness?

Can you clothe its neck with a rustling mane?

20 Can you cause it to leap like a locust?

The dignity of its snorting is frightful.

21 It paws in the low plain and exults in power;

It goes forth to meet armor.

22 It laughs at dread, and is not terrified;

Nor does it turn back on account of a sword.

23 Against it a quiver rattles,

The blade of a spear and a javelin.

24 With pounding and excitement it swallows up the earth,

And it does not believe that it is the sound of a horn.

25 As soon as the horn blows it says Aha!

And from far off it smells the battle,

The uproar of chiefs and the war cry.

26 Is it owing to your understanding that the falcon soars up,

That it spreads its wings to the south wind?

27 Or is it at your order that an eagle flies upward

And that it builds its nest high up,

28 That on a crag it resides and stays during the night

Upon the tooth of a crag and an inaccessible place?

29 From there it has to search for food;

Far into the distance its eyes keep looking.

30 And its young ones themselves keep sipping up blood;

And where the slain are, there it is.”

Job

41 “Can you draw out Le·vi′a·than with a fishhook,

Or with a rope can you hold down its tongue?

2 Can you put a rush in its nostrils,

Or with a thorn can you bore its jaws?

3 Will it make many entreaties to you,

Or will it say soft words to you?

4 Will it conclude a covenant with you,

That you may take it as a slave to time indefinite?

5 Will you play with it as with a bird,

Or will you tie it for your young girls?

6 Will partners barter for it?

Will they divide it up among tradesmen?

7 Will you fill its skin with harpoons,

Or its head with fish spears?

8 Put your hand upon it.

Remember the battle. Do not do it again.

9 Look! One’s expectation about it will certainly be disappointed.

One will also be hurled down at the mere sight of it.

10 None is so audacious that he should stir it up.

And who is it that can hold his ground before me?

11 Who has given me something first, that I ought to reward him?

Under the whole heavens it is mine.

12 I shall not keep silent about its parts

Or the matter of its mightiness and the grace of its proportions.

13 Who has uncovered the face of its clothing?

Into its double jaw who will enter?

14 The doors of its face who has opened?

Its teeth round about are frightful.

15 Furrows of scales are its haughtiness,

Closed as with a tight seal.

16 One to the other they fit closely,

And not even air can come in between them.

17 Each one to the other they are stuck together;

They grasp one another and cannot be separated.

18 Its very sneezings flash forth light,

And its eyes are like the beams of dawn.

19 Out of its mouth there go lightning flashes,

Even sparks of fire make their escape.

20 Out of its nostrils smoke goes forth,

Like a furnace set aflame even with rushes.

21 Its soul itself sets coals ablaze,

And even a flame goes forth out of its mouth.

22 In its neck lodges strength,

And before it despair leaps.

23 The folds of its flesh do cling together;

They are as a casting upon it, immovable.

24 Its heart is cast like stone,

Yes, cast like a lower millstone.

25 Due to its rising up the strong get frightened;

Due to consternation they get bewildered.

26 Overtaking it, the sword itself does not prove equal,

Nor spear, dart or arrowhead.

27 It regards iron as mere straw,

Copper as mere rotten wood.

28 An arrow does not chase it away;

The slingstones have been changed for it into mere stubble.

29 A club has been regarded by it as mere stubble,

And it laughs at the rattling of a javelin.

30 As pointed earthenware fragments are its underparts;

It spreads out a threshing instrument upon the mire.

31 It causes the depths to boil just like a pot;

It makes the very sea like an ointment pot.

32 Behind itself it makes a pathway shine;

One would regard the watery deep as gray-headedness.

33 Upon the dust there is not the like of it,

The one made to be without terror.

34 Everything high it sees.

It is king over all majestic wild beasts.”

Psalms

2 Why have the nations been in tumult

And the national groups themselves kept muttering an empty thing?

2 The kings of earth take their stand

And high officials themselves have massed together as one

Against Jehovah and against his anointed one,

3 Saying: “Let us tear their bands apart

And cast their cords away from us!”

4 The very One sitting in the heavens will laugh;

Jehovah himself will hold them in derision.

5 At that time he will speak to them in his anger

And in his hot displeasure he will disturb them,

6 Saying: “I, even I, have installed my king

Upon Zion, my holy mountain.”

7 Let me refer to the decree of Jehovah;

He has said to me: “You are my son;

I, today, I have become your father.

8 Ask of me, that I may give nations as your inheritance

And the ends of the earth as your own possession.

9 You will break them with an iron scepter,

As though a potter’s vessel you will dash them to pieces.”

10 And now, O kings, exercise insight;

Let yourselves be corrected, O judges of the earth.

11 Serve Jehovah with fear

And be joyful with trembling.

12 Kiss the son, that He may not become incensed

And YOU may not perish from the way,

For his anger flares up easily.

Happy are all those taking refuge in him.

Psalms

To the director on stringed instruments on the lower octave. A melody of David.

6 O Jehovah, do not in your anger reprove me,

And do not in your rage correct me.

2 Show me favor, O Jehovah, for I am fading away.

Heal me, O Jehovah, for my bones have been disturbed.

3 Yes, my own soul has been very much disturbed;

And you, O Jehovah—how long?

4 Do return, O Jehovah, do rescue my soul;

Save me for the sake of your loving-kindness.

5 For in death there is no mention of you;

In She′ol who will laud you?

6 I have grown weary with my sighing;

All night long I make my couch swim;

With my tears I make my own divan overflow.

7 From vexation my eye has become weak,

It has grown old because of all those showing hostility to me.

8 Get away from me, all YOU practicers of what is hurtful,

For Jehovah will certainly hear the sound of my weeping.

9 Jehovah will indeed hear my request for favor;

Jehovah himself will accept my own prayer.

10 All my enemies will be very much ashamed and disturbed;

They will turn back, they will be ashamed instantly.

Psalms

ל [La′medh]

10 Why, O Jehovah, do you keep standing afar off?

Why do you keep yourself hid in times of distress?

2 In his haughtiness the wicked one hotly pursues the afflicted one;

They get caught by the ideas that they have thought up.

3 For the wicked has praised himself over the selfish longing of his soul,

And the one making undue profit has blessed himself;

נ [Nun]

He has disrespected Jehovah.

4 The wicked one according to his superciliousness makes no search;

All his ideas are: “There is no God.”

5 His ways keep prospering all the time.

Your judicial decisions are high up out of his range;

As for all those showing hostility to him, he puffs at them.

6 He has said in his heart: “I shall not be made to totter;

For generation after generation I shall be one who is in no calamity.”

פ [Peʼ]

7 His mouth is full of oaths and of deceptions and of oppression.

Under his tongue are trouble and what is hurtful.

8 He sits in an ambush of settlements;

From concealed places he will kill someone innocent.

ע [ʽA′yin]

His eyes are on the lookout for someone unfortunate.

9 He keeps lying in wait in the concealed place like a lion in his covert.

He keeps lying in wait to carry off some afflicted one by force.

He carries off the afflicted one by force when he draws his net shut.

10 He is crushed, he bows down,

And the army of dejected ones has to fall into his strong claws.

11 He has said in his heart: “God has forgotten.

He has concealed his face.

He will certainly never see it.”

ק [Qohph]

12 Do arise, O Jehovah. O God, lift up your hand.

Do not forget the afflicted ones.

13 Why is it that the wicked one has disrespected God?

He has said in his heart: “You will not require an accounting.”

ר [Rehsh]

14 For you yourself have seen trouble and vexation.

You keep looking on, to get them into your hand.

To you the unfortunate one, the fatherless boy, commits himself.

You yourself have become his helper.

ש [Shin]

15 Break the arm of the wicked and bad one.

May you search after his wickedness until you find no more.

16 Jehovah is King to time indefinite, even forever.

The nations have perished out of his earth.

ת [Taw]

17 The desire of the meek ones you will certainly hear, O Jehovah.

You will prepare their heart.

You will pay attention with your ear,

18 To judge the fatherless boy and the crushed one,

That mortal man who is of the earth may no more cause trembling.

Psalms

To the director. Of Jehovah’s servant, of David, who spoke to Jehovah the words of this song in the day that Jehovah had delivered him out of the palm of all his enemies and out of the hand of Saul. And he proceeded to say:

18 I shall have affection for you, O Jehovah my strength.

2 Jehovah is my crag and my stronghold and the Provider of escape for me.

My God is my rock. I shall take refuge in him,

My shield and my horn of salvation, my secure height.

3 On the One to be praised, Jehovah, I shall call,

And from my enemies I shall be saved.

4 The ropes of death encircled me;

Flash floods of good-for-nothing men also kept terrifying me.

5 The very ropes of She′ol surrounded me;

The snares of death confronted me.

6 In my distress I kept calling upon Jehovah,

And to my God I kept crying for help.

Out of his temple he proceeded to hear my voice,

And my own cry before him for help now came into his ears.

7 And the earth began to shake and rock,

And the foundations of the mountains themselves became agitated,

And they kept shaking back and forth because he had been angered.

8 Smoke went up at his nostrils, and fire itself from his mouth kept devouring;

Coals themselves blazed forth from him.

9 And he proceeded to bend the heavens down and descend.

And thick gloom was beneath his feet.

10 And he came riding upon a cherub and came flying,

And he came darting upon the wings of a spirit.

11 He then made darkness his concealment place,

All around him as his booth,

Dark waters, thick clouds.

12 Out of the brightness in front of him there were his clouds that passed by,

Hail and burning coals of fire.

13 And in the heavens Jehovah began to thunder,

And the Most High himself began to give his voice,

Hail and burning coals of fire.

14 And he kept sending out his arrows, that he might scatter them;

And lightnings he shot out, that he might throw them into confusion.

15 And the streambeds of waters became visible,

And the foundations of the productive land became uncovered

From your rebuke, O Jehovah, from the blast of the breath of your nostrils.

16 He was sending from on high, he was taking me,

He was drawing me out of great waters.

17 He was delivering me from my strong enemy,

And from those hating me; because they were stronger than I was.

18 They kept confronting me in the day of my disaster,

But Jehovah came to be as a support for me.

19 And he proceeded to bring me out into a roomy place;

He was rescuing me, because he had found delight in me.

20 Jehovah rewards me according to my righteousness;

According to the cleanness of my hands he repays me.

21 For I have kept the ways of Jehovah,

And I have not wickedly departed from my God.

22 For all his judicial decisions are in front of me,

And his statutes I shall not remove from myself.

23 And I will prove myself faultless with him,

And I shall keep myself from error on my part.

24 And let Jehovah repay me according to my righteousness,

According to the cleanness of my hands in front of his eyes.

25 With someone loyal you will act in loyalty;

With the faultless, able-bodied man you will deal faultlessly;

26 With the one keeping clean you will show yourself clean;

And with the crooked one you will show yourself tortuous;

27 Because the afflicted people you yourself will save;

But the haughty eyes you will abase.

28 For you yourself will light my lamp, O Jehovah;

My God himself will make my darkness shine.

29 For by you I can run against a marauder band;

And by my God I can climb a wall.

30 As for the true God, perfect is his way;

The saying of Jehovah is a refined one.

A shield he is to all those taking refuge in him.

31 For who is a God besides Jehovah?

And who is a rock except our God?

32 The true God is the One girding me closely with vital energy,

And he will grant my way to be perfect,

33 Making my feet like those of the hinds,

And upon places high for me he keeps me standing.

34 He is teaching my hands for warfare,

And my arms have pressed down a bow of copper.

35 And you will give me your shield of salvation,

And your own right hand will sustain me,

And your own humility will make me great.

36 You will make room large enough for my steps under me,

And my ankles will certainly not wobble.

37 I shall pursue my enemies and overtake them;

And I shall not return until they are exterminated.

38 I shall break them in pieces so that they will not be able to rise up;

They will fall under my feet.

39 And you will gird me with vital energy for warfare;

You will make those rising against me collapse under me.

40 And as for my enemies, you will certainly give me the back of their neck;

And as for those hating me intensely, I shall silence them.

41 They cry for help, but there is no savior,

To Jehovah, but he actually does not answer them.

42 And I shall pound them fine like dust before the wind;

Like the mire of the streets I shall pour them out.

43 You will provide me escape from the faultfinding of the people.

You will appoint me the head of the nations.

A people that I have not known—they will serve me.

44 At mere hearsay they will be obedient to me;

Foreigners themselves will come cringing to me.

45 Foreigners themselves will fade away,

And they will come quaking out from their bulwarks.

46 Jehovah is living, and blessed be my Rock,

And let the God of my salvation be exalted.

47 The true God is the Giver of acts of vengeance to me;

And he subdues the peoples under me.

48 He is providing escape for me from my angry enemies;

Above those who rise up against me you will lift me up,

From the man of violence you will deliver me.

49 That is why I shall laud you among the nations, O Jehovah,

And to your name I will make melody.

50 He is doing great acts of salvation for his king

And exercising loving-kindness to his anointed one,

To David and to his seed to time indefinite.

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David.

19 The heavens are declaring the glory of God;

And of the work of his hands the expanse is telling.

2 One day after another day causes speech to bubble forth,

And one night after another night shows forth knowledge.

3 There is no speech, and there are no words;

No voice on their part is being heard.

4 Into all the earth their measuring line has gone out,

And to the extremity of the productive land their utterances.

In them he has set a tent for the sun,

5 And it is like a bridegroom when coming out of his nuptial chamber;

It exults as a mighty man does to run in a path.

6 From one extremity of the heavens is its going forth,

And its finished circuit is to their other extremities;

And there is nothing concealed from its heat.

7 The law of Jehovah is perfect, bringing back the soul.

The reminder of Jehovah is trustworthy, making the inexperienced one wise.

8 The orders from Jehovah are upright, causing the heart to rejoice;

The commandment of Jehovah is clean, making the eyes shine.

9 The fear of Jehovah is pure, standing forever.

The judicial decisions of Jehovah are true; they have proved altogether righteous.

10 They are more to be desired than gold, yes, than much refined gold;

And sweeter than honey and the flowing honey of the combs.

11 Also, your own servant has been warned by them;

In the keeping of them there is a large reward.

12 Mistakes—who can discern?

From concealed sins pronounce me innocent.

13 Also from presumptuous acts hold your servant back;

Do not let them dominate me.

In that case I shall be complete,

And I shall have remained innocent from much transgression.

14 Let the sayings of my mouth and the meditation of my heart

Become pleasurable before you, O Jehovah my Rock and my Redeemer.

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David.

21 O Jehovah, in your strength the king rejoices;

And in your salvation how very joyful he wants to be!

2 The desire of his heart you have given him,

And the wish of his lips you have not withheld. Se′lah.

3 For you proceeded to meet him with blessings of good,

And to place on his head a crown of refined gold.

4 Life he asked of you. You gave it to him,

Length of days to time indefinite, even forever.

5 His glory is great in your salvation.

Dignity and splendor you put upon him.

6 For you constitute him highly blessed forever;

You make him feel glad with the rejoicing at your face.

7 For the king is trusting in Jehovah,

Even in the loving-kindness of the Most High. He will not be caused to totter.

8 Your hand will find all your enemies;

Your own right hand will find those hating you.

9 You will constitute them as a fiery furnace at the appointed time for your attention.

Jehovah in his anger will swallow them up, and the fire will devour them.

10 Their fruitage you will destroy from the very earth,

And their offspring from the sons of men.

11 For they have directed against you what is bad;

They have thought out ideas that they are unable to carry out.

12 For you will make them turn their backs in flight

By your bowstrings that you make ready against their face.

13 O be exalted in your strength, O Jehovah.

We will sing and make melody to your mightiness.

Psalms

To the director upon the Hind of the Dawn. A melody of David.

22 My God, my God, why have you left me?

Why are you far from saving me,

From the words of my roaring?

2 O my God, I keep calling by day, and you do not answer;

And by night, and there is no silence on my part.

3 But you are holy,

Inhabiting the praises of Israel.

4 In you our fathers trusted;

They trusted, and you kept providing them with escape.

5 To you they cried out, and they got away safe;

In you they trusted, and they did not come to shame.

6 But I am a worm, and not a man,

A reproach to men and despicable to the people.

7 As for all those seeing me, they hold me in derision;

They keep opening their mouths wide, they keep wagging their head:

8 “He committed himself to Jehovah. Let Him provide him with escape!

Let him deliver him, since he has taken delight in him!”

9 For you were the One drawing me forth from the belly,

The One making me trust while upon the breasts of my mother.

10 Upon you I have been thrown from the womb;

From the belly of my mother you have been my God.

11 Do not keep far off from me, because distress is nearby,

Because there is no other helper.

12 Many young bulls have surrounded me;

The powerful ones of Ba′shan themselves have got around me.

13 They have opened against me their mouth,

As a lion tearing in pieces and roaring.

14 Like water I have been poured out,

And all my bones have been separated from one another.

My heart has become like wax;

It has melted deep in my inward parts.

15 My power has dried up just like a fragment of earthenware,

And my tongue is made to stick to my gums;

And in the dust of death you are setting me.

16 For dogs have surrounded me;

The assembly of evildoers themselves have enclosed me.

Like a lion they are at my hands and my feet.

17 I can count all my bones.

They themselves look, they gaze upon me.

18 They apportion my garments among themselves,

And upon my clothing they cast lots.

19 But you, O Jehovah, O do not keep far off.

O you my strength, do make haste to my assistance.

20 Do deliver from the sword my soul,

My only one from the very paw of the dog;

21 Save me from the mouth of the lion,

And from the horns of wild bulls you must answer and save me.

22 I will declare your name to my brothers;

In the middle of the congregation I shall praise you.

23 YOU fearers of Jehovah, praise him!

All YOU the seed of Jacob, glorify him!

And be frightened at him, all YOU the seed of Israel.

24 For he has neither despised

Nor loathed the affliction of the afflicted one;

And he has not concealed his face from him,

And when he cried to him for help he heard.

25 From you my praise will be in the large congregation;

My vows I shall pay in front of those fearing him.

26 The meek ones will eat and be satisfied;

Those seeking him will praise Jehovah.

May YOUR hearts live forever.

27 All the ends of the earth will remember and turn back to Jehovah.

And all the families of the nations will bow down before you.

28 For the kingship belongs to Jehovah,

And he is dominating the nations.

29 All the fat ones of the earth shall eat and will bow down;

Before him all those going down to the dust will bend down,

And no one will ever preserve his own soul alive.

30 A seed itself will serve him;

It will be declared concerning Jehovah to the generation.

31 They will come and tell of his righteousness

To the people that is to be born, that he has done this.

Psalms

Of David.

26 Judge me, O Jehovah, for I myself have walked in my own integrity,

And in Jehovah I have trusted, that I may not wobble.

2 Examine me, O Jehovah, and put me to the test;

Refine my kidneys and my heart.

3 For your loving-kindness is in front of my eyes,

And I have walked in your truth.

4 I have not sat with men of untruth;

And with those who hide what they are I do not come in.

5 I have hated the congregation of evildoers,

And with the wicked ones I do not sit.

6 I shall wash my hands in innocency itself,

And I will march around your altar, O Jehovah,

7 To cause thanksgiving to be heard aloud,

And to declare all your wonderful works.

8 Jehovah, I have loved the dwelling of your house

And the place of the residing of your glory.

9 Do not take away my soul along with sinners,

Nor my life along with bloodguilty men,

10 In whose hands there is loose conduct,

And whose right hand is full of bribery.

11 As for me, in my integrity I shall walk.

O redeem me and show me favor.

12 My own foot will certainly stand on a level place;

Among the congregated throngs I shall bless Jehovah.

Psalms

Of David.

27 Jehovah is my light and my salvation.

Of whom shall I be in fear?

Jehovah is the stronghold of my life.

Of whom shall I be in dread?

2 When the evildoers approached against me to eat up my flesh,

They being my adversaries and my enemies personally,

They themselves stumbled and fell.

3 Though against me an encampment should pitch tent,

My heart will not fear.

Though against me war should rise,

Even then I shall be trusting.

4 One thing I have asked from Jehovah—

It is what I shall look for,

That I may dwell in the house of Jehovah all the days of my life,

To behold the pleasantness of Jehovah

And to look with appreciation upon his temple.

5 For he will hide me in his covert in the day of calamity;

He will conceal me in the secret place of his tent;

High on a rock he will put me.

6 And now my head will be high above my enemies all around me;

And I will sacrifice at his tent sacrifices of joyful shouting;

I will sing and make melody to Jehovah.

7 Hear, O Jehovah, when I call with my voice,

And show me favor and answer me.

8 Concerning you my heart has said: “Seek to find my face, YOU people.”

Your face, O Jehovah, I shall seek to find.

9 Do not conceal your face from me.

Do not in anger turn your servant away.

My assistance you must become.

Do not forsake me and do not leave me, O my God of salvation.

10 In case my own father and my own mother did leave me,

Even Jehovah himself would take me up.

11 Instruct me, O Jehovah, in your way,

And lead me in the path of uprightness on account of my foes.

12 Do not give me over to the soul of my adversaries;

For against me false witnesses have risen up,

And he who launches forth violence.

13 If I had not had faith in seeing the goodness of Jehovah in the land of those alive—!

14 Hope in Jehovah; be courageous and let your heart be strong.

Yes, hope in Jehovah.

Psalms

Of David.

28 To you, O Jehovah, I keep calling.

O my Rock, do not be deaf to me,

That you may not keep still toward me

And I do not have to become like those going down to the pit.

2 Hear the voice of my entreaties when I cry to you for help,

When I raise my hands to the innermost room of your holy place.

3 Do not draw me along with wicked people and with practicers of what is hurtful,

Those who are speaking peace with their companions but in whose hearts is what is bad.

4 Give to them according to their acting

And according to the badness of their practices.

According to the work of their hands do you give to them.

Pay back to them their own doing.

5 For they have no regard for the activities of Jehovah,

Nor for the work of his hands.

He will tear them down and not build them up.

6 Blessed be Jehovah, for he has heard the voice of my entreaties.

7 Jehovah is my strength and my shield.

In him my heart has trusted,

And I have been helped, so that my heart exults,

And with my song I shall laud him.

8 Jehovah is a strength to his people,

And he is a stronghold of the grand salvation of his anointed one.

9 Do save your people, and bless your inheritance;

And shepherd them and carry them to time indefinite.

Psalms

A melody. A song of inauguration of the house. Of David.

30 I shall exalt you, O Jehovah, for you have drawn me up

And you have not let my enemies rejoice over me.

2 O Jehovah my God, I cried to you for help, and you proceeded to heal me.

3 O Jehovah, you have brought up my soul from She′ol itself;

You have kept me alive, that I should not go down into the pit.

4 Make melody to Jehovah, O YOU loyal ones of his,

Give thanks to his holy memorial;

5 Because being under his anger is for a moment,

Being under his goodwill is for a lifetime.

In the evening weeping may take up lodging, but in the morning there is a joyful cry.

6 As for me, I have said in my ease:

“Never shall I be made to totter.”

7 O Jehovah, in your goodwill you have made my mountain to stand in strength.

You concealed your face; I became one that is disturbed.

8 To you, O Jehovah, I kept calling;

And to Jehovah I kept making entreaty for favor.

9 What profit is there in my blood when I go down to the pit?

Will the dust laud you? Will it tell of your trueness?

10 Hear, O Jehovah, and show me favor.

O Jehovah, prove yourself my helper.

11 You have changed my mourning into dancing for me;

You have loosened my sackcloth, and you keep me girded with rejoicing,

12 In order that my glory may make melody to you and not keep silent.

O Jehovah my God, to time indefinite I will laud you.

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David.

31 In you, O Jehovah, have I taken refuge.

O may I never be ashamed.

In your righteousness provide escape for me.

2 Incline to me your ear.

Deliver me speedily.

Become for me a rocky stronghold,

A house of strongholds to save me.

3 For you are my crag and my stronghold;

And for the sake of your name you will lead me and conduct me.

4 You will bring me out of the net that they have hidden for me,

For you are my fortress.

5 Into your hand I entrust my spirit.

You have redeemed me, O Jehovah the God of truth.

6 I do hate those paying regard to worthless, vain idols;

But as for me, in Jehovah I do trust.

7 I will be joyful and rejoice in your loving-kindness,

In that you have seen my affliction;

You have known about the distresses of my soul,

8 And you have not surrendered me into the hand of the enemy.

You have made my feet stand in a roomy place.

9 Show me favor, O Jehovah, for I am in sore straits.

With vexation my eye has become weak, my soul and my belly.

10 For with grief my life has come to an end,

And my years in sighing.

Because of my error my power has stumbled,

And my very bones have become weak.

11 From the standpoint of all those showing hostility to me I have become a reproach,

And to my neighbors very much so,

And a dread to my acquaintances.

When seeing me out of doors, they have fled from me.

12 Like someone dead and not in the heart, I have been forgotten;

I have become like a damaged vessel;

13 For I have heard the bad report by many,

Fright being on all sides.

When they mass together as one against me,

It is to take away my soul that they do scheme.

14 But I—in you I have put my trust, O Jehovah.

I have said: “You are my God.”

15 My times are in your hand.

Deliver me from the hand of my enemies and from those pursuing me.

16 Do cause your face to shine upon your servant.

Save me in your loving-kindness.

17 O Jehovah, may I not be ashamed, for I have called on you.

May the wicked ones be ashamed;

May they keep silent in She′ol.

18 May false lips become speechless,

That are speaking against the righteous one, unrestrainedly in haughtiness and contempt.

19 How abundant your goodness is, which you have treasured up for those fearing you!

Which you have rendered to those taking refuge in you,

In front of the sons of men.

20 You will conceal them in the secret place of your person

From the banding together of men.

You will hide them in your booth from the quarreling of tongues.

21 Blessed be Jehovah,

For he has rendered wonderful loving-kindness to me in a city under stress.

22 As for me, I said when I became panicky:

“I shall certainly be exterminated from in front of your eyes.”

Surely you have heard the voice of my entreaties when I cried to you for help.

23 O love Jehovah, all YOU loyal ones of his.

The faithful ones Jehovah is safeguarding,

But he is rewarding exceedingly anyone showing haughtiness.

24 Be courageous, and may YOUR heart be strong,

All YOU who are waiting for Jehovah.

Psalms

Of David.

35 Do conduct my case, O Jehovah, against my opponents;

War against those warring against me.

2 Take hold of buckler and large shield,

And do rise up in assistance of me,

3 And draw spear and double ax to meet those pursuing me.

Say to my soul: “I am your salvation.”

4 May those be shamed and humiliated who are hunting for my soul.

May those be turned back and be abashed who are scheming calamity for me.

5 May they become like chaff before the wind,

And let Jehovah’s angel be pushing them along.

6 Let their way become darkness and slippery places,

And let Jehovah’s angel be pursuing them.

7 For without cause they have hid for me their netted pit;

Without cause they have dug it for my soul.

8 Let ruin come upon him without his knowing,

And let his own net that he hid catch him;

With ruin let him fall into it.

9 But let my own soul be joyful in Jehovah;

Let it exult in his salvation.

10 Let all my bones themselves say:

“O Jehovah, who is there like you,

Delivering the afflicted one from one stronger than he is,

And the afflicted and poor one from the one robbing him?”

11 Violent witnesses rise up;

What I have not known they ask me.

12 They reward me with bad for good,

Bereavement to my soul.

13 As for me, when they became ill, my clothing was sackcloth,

With fasting I afflicted my soul,

And upon my bosom my own prayer would return.

14 As for a companion, as for a brother of mine,

I walked about like one mourning for a mother.

Saddened, I bowed down.

15 But at my limping they rejoiced and gathered together;

They gathered together against me,

Striking me down when I did not know it;

They ripped me to pieces and did not keep silent.

16 Among the apostate mockers for a cake

There was a grinding of their teeth even against me.

17 O Jehovah, how long will you keep seeing it?

Do bring back my soul from their ravages,

Even my only one from the maned young lions.

18 I will laud you in the big congregation;

Among a numerous people I shall praise you.

19 O may those who for no reason are my enemies not rejoice over me;

As for those hating me without cause, let them not wink the eye.

20 For it is not peace that they speak;

But against the quiet ones of the earth

Things of deception they keep scheming.

21 And they open wide their mouth even against me.

They have said: “Aha! Aha! our eye has seen it.”

22 You have seen, O Jehovah. Do not keep silent.

O Jehovah, do not keep yourself far from me.

23 Do arouse yourself and awake to my judgment,

O my God, even Jehovah, to my case at law.

24 Judge me according to your righteousness, O Jehovah my God,

And may they not rejoice over me.

25 O may they not say in their heart: “Aha, our soul!”

May they not say: “We have swallowed him up.”

26 Let those be ashamed and abashed all together

Who are joyful at my calamity.

Let those be clothed with shame and humiliation who are assuming great airs against me.

27 Let those cry out joyfully and rejoice who are delighting in my righteousness,

And let them say constantly:

“Let Jehovah be magnified, who takes delight in the peace of his servant.”

28 And let my own tongue utter in an undertone your righteousness,

All day long your praise.

Psalms

Of David.

א [ʼA′leph]

37 Do not show yourself heated up because of the evildoers.

Do not be envious of those doing unrighteousness.

2 For like grass they will speedily wither,

And like green new grass they will fade away.

ב [Behth]

3 Trust in Jehovah and do good;

Reside in the earth, and deal with faithfulness.

4 Also take exquisite delight in Jehovah,

And he will give you the requests of your heart.

ג [Gi′mel]

5 Roll upon Jehovah your way,

And rely upon him, and he himself will act.

6 And he will certainly bring forth your righteousness as the light itself,

And your justice as the midday.

ד [Da′leth]

7 Keep silent before Jehovah

And wait longingly for him.

Do not show yourself heated up at anyone making his way successful,

At the man carrying out his ideas.

ה [Heʼ]

8 Let anger alone and leave rage;

Do not show yourself heated up only to do evil.

9 For evildoers themselves will be cut off,

But those hoping in Jehovah are the ones that will possess the earth.

ו [Waw]

10 And just a little while longer, and the wicked one will be no more;

And you will certainly give attention to his place, and he will not be.

11 But the meek ones themselves will possess the earth,

And they will indeed find their exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

ז [Za′yin]

12 The wicked one is plotting against the righteous one,

And at him he is grinding his teeth.

13 Jehovah himself will laugh at him,

For he certainly sees that his day will come.

ח [Chehth]

14 The wicked ones have drawn a sword itself and have bent their bow,

To cause the afflicted and poor one to fall,

To slaughter those who are upright in their way.

15 Their own sword will enter into their heart,

And their own bows will be broken.

ט [Tehth]

16 Better is the little of the righteous one

Than the abundance of the many wicked ones.

17 For the very arms of the wicked ones will be broken,

But Jehovah will be supporting the righteous ones.

י [Yohdh]

18 Jehovah is aware of the days of the faultless ones,

And their very inheritance will continue even to time indefinite.

19 They will not be ashamed in the time of calamity,

And in the days of famine they will be satisfied.

כ [Kaph]

20 For the wicked themselves will perish,

And the enemies of Jehovah will be like the preciousness of pastures;

They must come to their end. In smoke they must come to their end.

ל [La′medh]

21 The wicked one is borrowing and does not pay back,

But the righteous one is showing favor and is making gifts.

22 For those being blessed by him will themselves possess the earth,

But those upon whom evil is called by him will be cut off.

מ [Mem]

23 By Jehovah the very steps of an able-bodied man have been made ready,

And in his way He takes delight.

24 Although he may fall, he will not be hurled down,

For Jehovah is supporting his hand.

נ [Nun]

25 A young man I used to be, I have also grown old,

And yet I have not seen anyone righteous left entirely,

Nor his offspring looking for bread.

26 All day long he is showing favor and lending,

And so his offspring are in line for a blessing.

ס [Sa′mekh]

27 Turn away from what is bad and do what is good,

And so reside to time indefinite.

28 For Jehovah is a lover of justice,

And he will not leave his loyal ones.

ע [ʽA′yin]

To time indefinite they will certainly be guarded;

But as for the offspring of the wicked ones, they will indeed be cut off.

29 The righteous themselves will possess the earth,

And they will reside forever upon it.

פ [Peʼ]

30 The mouth of the righteous is the one that utters wisdom in an undertone,

And his is the tongue that speaks justly.

31 The law of his God is in his heart;

His steps will not wobble.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

32 The wicked one is keeping on the watch for the righteous

And is seeking to put him to death.

33 As for Jehovah, he will not leave him to the hand of that one,

And he will not pronounce him wicked when he is being judged.

ק [Qohph]

34 Hope in Jehovah and keep his way,

And he will exalt you to take possession of the earth.

When the wicked ones are cut off, you will see it.

ר [Rehsh]

35 I have seen the wicked a tyrant

And spreading himself as a luxuriant tree in native soil.

36 And yet he proceeded to pass away, and there he was not;

And I kept seeking him, and he was not found.

ש [Shin]

37 Watch the blameless one and keep the upright one in sight,

For the future of that man will be peaceful.

38 But the transgressors themselves will certainly be annihilated together;

The future of wicked people will indeed be cut off.

ת [Taw]

39 And the salvation of the righteous ones is from Jehovah;

He is their fortress in the time of distress.

40 And Jehovah will help them and provide them with escape.

He will provide them with escape from wicked people and save them,

Because they have taken refuge in him.

Psalms

A melody of David, to bring to remembrance.

38 O Jehovah, do not in your indignation reprove me,

Nor in your rage correct me.

2 For your own arrows have sunk themselves deep into me,

And upon me your hand is come down.

3 There is no sound spot in my flesh because of your denunciation.

There is no peace in my bones on account of my sin.

4 For my own errors have passed over my head;

Like a heavy load they are too heavy for me.

5 My wounds have become stinky, they have festered,

Because of my foolishness.

6 I have become disconcerted, I have bowed low to an extreme degree;

All day long I have walked about sad.

7 For my very loins have become full of burning,

And there is no sound spot in my flesh.

8 I have grown numb and become crushed to an extreme degree;

I have roared due to the groaning of my heart.

9 O Jehovah, in front of you is all my desire,

And from you my sighing itself has not been concealed.

10 My own heart has palpitated heavily, my power has left me,

And the light of my own eyes also is not with me.

11 As for my lovers and my companions, they keep standing away from my plague,

And my close acquaintances themselves have stood off at a distance.

12 But those seeking my soul lay out traps,

And those working for a calamity to me have spoken of adversities,

And deceptions they keep muttering all day long.

13 As for me, like someone deaf, I would not listen;

And like someone speechless, I would not open my mouth.

14 And I came to be like a man that was not hearing,

And in my mouth there were no counterarguments.

15 For on you, O Jehovah, I waited;

You yourself proceeded to answer, O Jehovah my God.

16 For I said: “Otherwise they would rejoice at me;

When my foot moved unsteadily, they would certainly assume great airs against me.”

17 For I was ready to limp,

And my pain was in front of me constantly.

18 For I proceeded to tell about my own error;

I began to be anxious over my sin.

19 And my enemies who are alive became mighty,

And those hating me for no reason became many.

20 And they were rewarding me with bad for good;

They kept resisting me in return for my pursuing what is good.

21 Do not leave me, O Jehovah.

O my God, do not keep far away from me.

22 Do make haste to my assistance,

O Jehovah my salvation.

Psalms

To the director. Of David, a melody.

40 I earnestly hoped in Jehovah,

And so he inclined his ear to me and heard my cry for help.

2 He also proceeded to bring me up out of a roaring pit,

Out of the mire of the sediment.

Then he raised up my feet upon a crag;

He firmly established my steps.

3 Further, he put in my mouth a new song,

Praise to our God.

Many will see it and will fear,

And they will trust in Jehovah.

4 Happy is the able-bodied man that has put Jehovah as his trust

And that has not turned his face to defiant people,

Nor to those falling away to lies.

5 Many things you yourself have done,

O Jehovah my God, even your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us;

There is none to be compared to you.

Were I inclined to tell and speak of them,

They have become more numerous than I can recount.

6 Sacrifice and offering you did not delight in;

These ears of mine you opened up.

Burnt offering and sin offering you did not ask for.

7 In view of that, I said: “Here I have come,

In the roll of the book it being written about me.

8 To do your will, O my God, I have delighted,

And your law is within my inward parts.

9 I have told the good news of righteousness in the big congregation.

Look! My lips I do not restrain.

O Jehovah, you yourself know that well.

10 Your righteousness I have not covered over within my heart.

Your faithfulness and your salvation I have declared.

I have not hidden your loving-kindness and your trueness in the big congregation.”

11 You yourself, O Jehovah, do not restrain your pity from me.

Let your loving-kindness and your trueness themselves constantly safeguard me.

12 For calamities encircled me until there was no numbering of them.

More errors of mine overtook me than I was able to see;

They became more numerous than the hairs of my head,

And my own heart left me.

13 Be pleased, O Jehovah, to deliver me.

O Jehovah, to my assistance do make haste.

14 May those be ashamed and abashed all together

Who are seeking my soul to sweep it away.

May those turn back and be humiliated who are delighting in my calamity.

15 Let those stare in amazement in consequence of their shame

Who are saying to me: “Aha! Aha!”

16 Let those exult and rejoice in you,

All those who are seeking you.

Let those say constantly: “May Jehovah be magnified,”

Those who are loving salvation by you.

17 But I am afflicted and poor.

Jehovah himself takes account of me.

You are my assistance and the Provider of escape for me.

O my God, do not be too late.

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David.

41 Happy is anyone acting with consideration toward the lowly one;

In the day of calamity Jehovah will provide escape for him.

2 Jehovah himself will guard him and preserve him alive.

He will be pronounced happy in the earth;

And you cannot possibly give him over to the soul of his enemies.

3 Jehovah himself will sustain him upon a divan of illness;

All his bed you will certainly change during his sickness.

4 As for me, I said: “O Jehovah, show me favor.

Do heal my soul, for I have sinned against you.”

5 As for my enemies, they say what is bad concerning me:

“When will he die and his name actually perish?”

6 And if one does come to see me, untruth is what his heart will speak;

He will gather up for himself something hurtful;

He will go out; on the outside he will speak of it.

7 Unitedly against me all those hating me whisper to one another;

Against me they keep scheming something bad for me:

8 “A good-for-nothing thing is poured out upon him;

Now that he has lain down, he will not get up again.”

9 Also the man at peace with me, in whom I trusted,

Who was eating my bread, has magnified his heel against me.

10 As for you, O Jehovah, show me favor and cause me to get up,

That I may pay them back.

11 By this I do know that you have found delight in me,

Because my enemy does not shout in triumph over me.

12 As for me, because of my integrity you have upheld me,

And you will set me before your face to time indefinite.

13 Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel

From time indefinite even to time indefinite.

Amen and Amen.

Psalms

To the director. Of the sons of Ko′rah. Mas′kil.

44 O God, with our ears we have heard,

Our forefathers themselves have recounted to us

The activity that you performed in their days,

In the days of long ago.

2 You yourself by your hand drove away even nations,

And you proceeded to plant them instead.

You went breaking national groups and sending them away.

3 For it was not by their own sword that they took possession of the land,

And their own arm was not what brought them salvation.

For it was your right hand and your arm and the light of your face,

Because you took pleasure in them.

4 You yourself are my King, O God.

Command grand salvation for Jacob.

5 By you we shall push our adversaries themselves;

In your name we shall tread down those rising up against us.

6 For it was not in my bow that I kept trusting

And it was not my sword that was saving me.

7 For you saved us from our adversaries,

And those intensely hating us you put to shame.

8 In God we will offer praise all day long,

And to time indefinite your name we shall laud. Se′lah.

9 But now you have cast off and keep humiliating us,

And you do not go forth with our armies.

10 You keep making us turn back from the adversary,

And the very ones intensely hating us have pillaged for themselves.

11 You give us up like sheep, as something to eat,

And among the nations you have scattered us.

12 You sell your people for no value at all,

And you have made no wealth by the price for them.

13 You set us as a reproach to our neighbors,

A derision and jeering to those all around us.

14 You set us as a proverbial saying among the nations,

A shaking of the head among the national groups.

15 All day long my humiliation is in front of me,

And the shame of my own face has covered me,

16 Due to the voice of the one reproaching and speaking abusively,

Because of the enemy and the one taking his revenge.

17 All this is what has come upon us, and we have not forgotten you,

And we have not acted falsely in your covenant.

18 Our heart has not turned faithlessly back,

Nor do our footsteps deviate from your path.

19 For you have crushed us in the place of jackals,

And you cover us over with deep shadow.

20 If we have forgotten the name of our God,

Or we spread out our palms to a strange god,

21 Will not God himself search this out?

For he is aware of the secrets of the heart.

22 But for your sake we have been killed all day long;

We have been accounted as sheep for slaughtering.

23 Do arouse yourself. Why do you keep sleeping, O Jehovah?

Do awake. Do not keep casting off forever.

24 Why do you keep your very face concealed?

Why do you forget our affliction and our oppression?

25 For our soul has bowed down to the dust itself;

Our belly has clung to the very earth.

26 Do arise in assistance to us

And redeem us for the sake of your loving-kindness.

Psalms

To the director. Of the sons of Ko′rah upon The Maidens. A song.

46 God is for us a refuge and strength,

A help that is readily to be found during distresses.

2 That is why we shall not fear, though the earth undergo change

And though the mountains totter into the heart of the vast sea;

3 Though its waters be boisterous, foam over,

Though the mountains rock at its uproar. Se′lah.

4 There is a river the streams of which make the city of God rejoice,

The holiest grand tabernacle of the Most High.

5 God is in the midst of the city; it will not be made to totter.

God will help it at the appearance of morning.

6 The nations became boisterous, the kingdoms tottered;

He sounded with his voice, the earth proceeded to melt.

7 Jehovah of armies is with us;

The God of Jacob is a secure height for us. Se′lah.

8 Come, YOU people, behold the activities of Jehovah,

How he has set astonishing events on the earth.

9 He is making wars to cease to the extremity of the earth.

The bow he breaks apart and does cut the spear in pieces;

The wagons he burns in the fire.

10 “Give in, YOU people, and know that I am God.

I will be exalted among the nations,

I will be exalted in the earth.”

11 Jehovah of armies is with us;

The God of Jacob is a secure height for us. Se′lah.

Psalms

A song. A melody of the sons of Ko′rah.

48 Jehovah is great and much to be praised

In the city of our God, in his holy mountain.

2 Pretty for loftiness, the exultation of the whole earth,

Is Mount Zion on the remote sides of the north,

The town of the Grand King.

3 In her dwelling towers God himself has become known as a secure height.

4 For, look! the kings themselves have met by appointment,

They have passed by together.

5 They themselves saw; and so they were amazed.

They got disturbed, they were sent running in panic.

6 Trembling itself took hold of them there,

Birth pangs like those of a woman giving birth.

7 With an east wind you wreck the ships of Tar′shish.

8 Just as we have heard, so we have seen

In the city of Jehovah of armies, in the city of our God.

God himself will firmly establish it to time indefinite. Se′lah.

9 We have pondered, O God, over your loving-kindness

In the midst of your temple.

10 Like your name, O God, so your praise is

To the borders of the earth.

Your right hand is full of righteousness itself.

11 May Mount Zion rejoice,

May the dependent towns of Judah be joyful, on account of your judicial decisions.

12 March around Zion, YOU people, and go about it,

Count its towers.

13 Set YOUR hearts upon its rampart.

Inspect its dwelling towers,

In order that YOU may recount it to the future generation.

14 For this God is our God to time indefinite, even forever.

He himself will guide us until we die.

Psalms

To the director. Of the sons of Ko′rah. A melody.

49 Hear this, all YOU peoples.

Give ear, all YOU inhabitants of the system of things,

2 YOU sons of humankind as well as YOU sons of man,

You rich one and you poor one together.

3 My own mouth will speak things of wisdom,

And the meditation of my heart will be of things of understanding.

4 To a proverbial utterance I shall incline my ear;

On a harp I shall open up my riddle.

5 Why should I be afraid in the days of evil,

When the very error of my supplanters surrounds me?

6 Those who are trusting in their means of maintenance,

And who keep boasting about the abundance of their riches,

7 Not one of them can by any means redeem even a brother,

Nor give to God a ransom for him;

8 (And the redemption price of their soul is so precious

That it has ceased to time indefinite)

9 That he should still live forever and not see the pit.

10 For he sees that even the wise ones die,

Together the stupid one and the unreasoning one perish,

And they must leave to others their means of maintenance.

11 Their inward wish is that their houses may be to time indefinite,

Their tabernacles to generation after generation.

They have called their landed estates by their names.

12 And yet earthling man, though in honor, cannot keep lodging;

He is indeed comparable with the beasts that have been destroyed.

13 This is the way of those who have stupidity,

And of those coming after them who take pleasure in their very mouthings. Se′lah.

14 Like sheep they have been appointed to She′ol itself;

Death itself will shepherd them;

And the upright ones will have them in subjection in the morning,

And their forms are due to wear away;

She′ol rather than a lofty abode is for each one.

15 However, God himself will redeem my soul from the hand of She′ol,

For he will receive me. Se′lah.

16 Do not be afraid because some man gains riches,

Because the glory of his house increases,

17 For at his death he cannot take along anything at all;

His glory will not go down along with him himself.

18 For during his lifetime he kept blessing his own soul;

(And people will laud you because you do well for yourself)

19 His soul finally comes only as far as the generation of his forefathers.

Nevermore will they see the light.

20 Earthling man, although in honor, who does not understand,

Is indeed comparable with the beasts that have been destroyed.

Psalms

To the director. Mas′kil. Of David, when Do′eg the E′dom·ite came and proceeded to tell Saul and say to him that David had come to the house of A·him′e·lech.

52 Why do you make your boast over what is bad, O you mighty one?

The loving-kindness of God is all day long.

2 Adversities your tongue schemes up, sharpened like a razor,

Working deceitfully.

3 You have loved what is bad more than what is good,

Falsehood more than speaking righteousness. Se′lah.

4 You have loved all devouring words,

O you deceitful tongue.

5 God himself will also pull you down forever;

He will knock you down and tear you away from your tent,

And he will certainly root you out of the land of the living ones. Se′lah.

6 And the righteous ones will see it and will be afraid,

And over him they will laugh.

7 Here is the able-bodied man that does not put God as his fortress,

But that trusts in the abundance of his riches,

That takes shelter in adversities by him.

8 But I shall be like a luxuriant olive tree in God’s house;

I do trust in the loving-kindness of God to time indefinite, even forever.

9 I will laud you to time indefinite, for you have taken action;

And I shall hope in your name, because it is good, in front of your loyal ones.

Psalms

To the director over Ma′ha·lath. Mas′kil. Of David.

53 The senseless one has said in his heart:

“There is no Jehovah.”

They have acted ruinously and have acted detestably in unrighteousness;

There is no one doing good.

2 As for God, he has looked down from heaven itself upon the sons of men,

To see whether there exists anyone having insight, anyone seeking Jehovah.

3 They have all of them turned back, they are all alike corrupt;

There is no one doing good,

Not even one.

4 Have none of the practicers of what is hurtful got knowledge,

Eating up my people as they have eaten bread?

They have not called even upon Jehovah.

5 There they were filled with a great dread,

Where there had proved to be no dread;

For God himself will certainly scatter the bones of anyone camping against you.

You will certainly put them to shame, for Jehovah himself has rejected them.

6 O that out of Zion there were the grand salvation of Israel!

When Jehovah gathers back the captive ones of his people,

Let Jacob be joyful, let Israel rejoice.

Psalms

To the director on stringed instruments. Mas′kil. Of David.

55 Do give ear, O God, to my prayer;

And do not hide yourself from my request for favor.

2 Do pay attention to me and answer me.

I am driven restlessly about by my concern,

And I cannot but show disquietude,

3 Due to the voice of the enemy, because of the pressure of the wicked one.

For they keep dropping upon me what is hurtful,

And in anger they harbor animosity against me.

4 My very heart is in severe pain within me,

And the frights of death itself have fallen upon me.

5 Fear, yes, trembling itself enters into me,

And shuddering covers me.

6 And I keep saying: “O that I had wings as a dove has!

I would fly away and reside.

7 Look! I would go far away in flight;

I would lodge in the wilderness.—Se′lah—

8 I would hasten to a place of escape for me

From the rushing wind, from the tempest.”

9 Confuse, O Jehovah, divide their tongue,

For I have seen violence and disputing in the city.

10 Day and night they go round about it upon its walls;

And hurtfulness and trouble are within it.

11 Adversities are within it;

And from its public square oppression and deception have not moved away.

12 For it was not an enemy that proceeded to reproach me;

Otherwise I could put up with it.

It was not an intense hater of me that assumed great airs against me;

Otherwise I could conceal myself from him.

13 But it was you, a mortal man who was as my equal,

One familiar to me and my acquaintance,

14 Because we used to enjoy sweet intimacy together;

Into the house of God we used to walk with the throng.

15 Desolations be upon them!

Let them go down into She′ol alive;

For during their alien residence bad things have been within them.

16 As for me, to God I shall call out;

And Jehovah himself will save me.

17 Evening and morning and noontime I cannot but show concern and I moan,

And he hears my voice.

18 He will certainly redeem and put my soul in peace from the fight that is against me,

For in multitudes they have come to be against me.

19 God will hear and answer them,

Even He that is sitting enthroned as in the past—Se′lah—

Those with whom there are no changings

And who have not feared God.

20 He has thrust out his hands against those at peace with him;

He has profaned his covenant.

21 Smoother than butter are the words of his mouth,

But his heart is disposed to fight.

His words are softer than oil,

But they are drawn swords.

22 Throw your burden upon Jehovah himself,

And he himself will sustain you.

Never will he allow the righteous one to totter.

23 But you yourself, O God, will bring them down to the lowest pit.

As for bloodguilty and deceitful men, they will not live out half their days.

But as for me, I shall trust in you.

Psalms

To the director. “Do not bring to ruin.” Of David. Mik′tam.

58 In YOUR silence can YOU really speak about righteousness itself?

Can YOU judge in uprightness itself, O YOU sons of men?

2 How much, rather, do YOU with the heart practice outright unrighteousness in the earth,

And prepare the road for the very violence of YOUR hands!

3 The wicked ones have been perverts from the womb;

They have wandered about from the belly onward;

They are speaking lies.

4 The venom of theirs is like the venom of the serpent,

Deaf like the cobra that stops up its ear,

5 That will not listen to the voice of charmers,

Though someone wise is binding with spells.

6 O God, knock out their teeth in their mouth.

Break down the very jawbones of maned young lions, O Jehovah.

7 May they dissolve as into waters that go their way;

May he bend the bow for his arrows as they collapse.

8 Like a snail melting away he walks;

Like a miscarriage of a woman they will certainly not behold the sun.

9 Before YOUR pots feel the kindled bramble,

The live green as well as the burning, he will carry them off as a stormy wind.

10 The righteous one will rejoice because he has beheld the vengeance.

His steps he will bathe in the blood of the wicked one.

11 And mankind will say: “Surely there is fruitage for the righteous one.

Surely there exists a God that is judging in the earth.”

Psalms

A melody of David, when he happened to be in the wilderness of Judah.

63 O God, you are my God, I keep looking for you.

My soul does thirst for you.

For you my flesh has grown faint with longing

In a land dry and exhausted, where there is no water.

2 Thus I have beheld you in the holy place,

At seeing your strength and your glory.

3 Because your loving-kindness is better than life,

My own lips will commend you.

4 Thus I shall bless you during my lifetime;

In your name I shall raise my palms.

5 As with the best part, even fatness, my soul is satisfied,

And with lips of joyful cries my mouth offers praise.

6 When I have remembered you upon my lounge,

During the night watches I meditate on you.

7 For you have proved to be of assistance to me,

And in the shadow of your wings I cry out joyfully.

8 My soul has closely followed you;

On me your right hand keeps fast hold.

9 As for those who keep seeking my soul for its ruin,

They will come into the lowest parts of the earth.

10 They will be delivered over to the power of the sword;

They will become a mere portion for foxes.

11 And the king himself will rejoice in God.

Every one swearing by him will boast,

For the mouth of those speaking falsehood will be stopped up.

Psalms

To the director. A song, a melody.

66 Shout in triumph to God, all YOU people of the earth.

2 Make melody to the glory of his name.

Render his praise glorious.

3 Say to God: “How fear-inspiring your works are!

Because of the abundance of your strength your enemies will come cringing to you.

4 All people of the earth will bow down to you,

And they will make melody to you, they will make melody to your name.” Se′lah.

5 Come, YOU people, and see the activities of God.

His dealing with the sons of men is fear-inspiring.

6 He has changed the sea into dry land;

Through the river they went crossing over on foot.

There we began to rejoice in him.

7 He is ruling by his mightiness to time indefinite.

Upon the nations his own eyes keep watch.

As for those who are stubborn, let them not be exalted in themselves. Se′lah.

8 Bless our God, O YOU peoples,

And cause the voice of praise to him to be heard.

9 He is setting our soul in life,

And he has not allowed our foot to totter.

10 For you have examined us, O God;

You have refined us as when refining silver.

11 You have brought us into a hunting net;

You have put pressure on our hips.

12 You have made mortal man to ride over our head;

We have come through fire and through water,

And you proceeded to bring us forth to relief.

13 I shall come into your house with whole burnt offerings;

I shall pay to you my vows

14 That my lips have opened up to say

And that my mouth has spoken when I was in sore straits.

15 Whole burnt offerings of fatlings I shall offer up to you,

With the sacrificial smoke of rams.

I shall render up a bull with he-goats. Se′lah.

16 Come, listen, all YOU who fear God, and I will relate

What he has done for my soul.

17 To him I called with my mouth,

And there was an extolling with my tongue.

18 If I have regarded anything hurtful in my heart,

Jehovah will not hear me.

19 Truly God has heard;

He has paid attention to the voice of my prayer.

20 Blessed be God, who has not turned aside my prayer,

Nor his loving-kindness from me.

Psalms

To the director. Of David. A melody, a song.

68 Let God arise, let his enemies be scattered,

And let those who intensely hate him flee because of him.

2 As smoke is driven away, may you drive them away;

As wax melts because of the fire,

Let the wicked ones perish from before God.

3 But as for the righteous, let them rejoice,

Let them be elated before God,

And let them exult with rejoicing.

4 Sing YOU to God, make melody to his name;

Raise up a song to the One riding through the desert plains

As Jah, which is his name; and jubilate before him;

5 A father of fatherless boys and a judge of widows

Is God in his holy dwelling.

6 God is causing the solitary ones to dwell in a house;

He is bringing forth prisoners into full prosperity.

However, as for the stubborn, they have to reside in a scorched land.

7 O God, when you went forth before your people,

When you marched through the desert—Se′lah—

8 The earth itself rocked,

Heaven itself also dripped because of God;

This Si′nai rocked because of God, the God of Israel.

9 A copious downpour you began causing to fall, O God;

Your inheritance, even when it was weary—you yourself reinvigorated it.

10 Your tent community—they have dwelt in it;

With your goodness you proceeded to make it ready for the afflicted one, O God.

11 Jehovah himself gives the saying;

The women telling the good news are a large army.

12 Even the kings of armies flee, they flee.

As for her who abides at home, she shares in the spoil.

13 Although YOU men kept lying between the camp ash heaps,

There will be the wings of a dove covered with silver

And its pinions with yellowish-green gold.

14 When the Almighty One scattered abroad the kings in it,

It began to snow in Zal′mon.

15 The mountainous region of Ba′shan is a mountain of God;

The mountainous region of Ba′shan is a mountain of peaks.

16 Why do YOU, O YOU mountains of peaks, keep watching enviously

The mountain that God has desired for himself to dwell in?

Even Jehovah himself will reside there forever.

17 The war chariots of God are in tens of thousands, thousands over and over again.

Jehovah himself has come from Si′nai into the holy place.

18 You have ascended on high;

You have carried away captives;

You have taken gifts in the form of men,

Yes, even the stubborn ones, to reside among them, O Jah God.

19 Blessed be Jehovah, who daily carries the load for us,

The true God of our salvation. Se′lah.

20 The true God is for us a God of saving acts;

And to Jehovah the Sovereign Lord belong the ways out from death.

21 Indeed God himself will break the head of his enemies in pieces,

The hairy crown of the head of anyone walking about in his guiltiness.

22 Jehovah has said: “From Ba′shan I shall bring back,

I shall bring them back from the depths of the sea,

23 In order that you may wash your foot in blood,

That the tongue of your dogs may have its portion from the enemies.”

24 They have seen your processions, O God,

The processions of my God, my King, into the holy place.

25 The singers went in front, the players on stringed instruments after them;

In between were the maidens beating tambourines.

26 In congregated throngs bless God,

Jehovah, O YOU who are from the Source of Israel.

27 There is little Benjamin subduing them,

The princes of Judah with their shouting crowd,

The princes of Zeb′u·lun, the princes of Naph′ta·li.

28 Your God has laid command upon your strength.

Do show strength, O God, you who have acted for us.

29 Because of your temple at Jerusalem,

Kings will bring gifts to you yourself.

30 Rebuke the wild beast of the reeds, the assembly of bulls,

With the calves of the peoples, each one stamping down on pieces of silver.

He has scattered the peoples that take delight in fights.

31 Bronzeware things will come out of Egypt;

Cush itself will quickly stretch out its hands with gifts to God.

32 O YOU kingdoms of the earth, sing to God,

Make melody to Jehovah—Se′lah—

33 To the One riding on the ancient heaven of heavens.

Lo! He sounds with his voice, a strong voice.

34 ASCRIBE strength to God.

Over Israel his eminence is and his strength is in the clouds.

35 God is fear-inspiring out of your grand sanctuary.

The God of Israel he is, giving strength, even might to the people.

Blessed be God.

Psalms

Regarding Solomon.

72 O God, give your own judicial decisions to the king,

And your righteousness to the son of the king.

2 May he plead the cause of your people with righteousness

And of your afflicted ones with judicial decision.

3 Let the mountains carry peace to the people,

Also the hills, through righteousness.

4 Let him judge the afflicted ones of the people,

Let him save the sons of the poor one,

And let him crush the defrauder.

5 They will fear you as long as there is a sun,

And before the moon for generation after generation.

6 He will descend like the rain upon the mown grass,

Like copious showers that wet the earth.

7 In his days the righteous one will sprout,

And the abundance of peace until the moon is no more.

8 And he will have subjects from sea to sea

And from the River to the ends of the earth.

9 Before him the inhabitants of waterless regions will bow down,

And his very enemies will lick the dust itself.

10 The kings of Tar′shish and of the islands—

Tribute they will pay.

The kings of She′ba and of Se′ba—

A gift they will present.

11 And to him all the kings will prostrate themselves;

All the nations, for their part, will serve him.

12 For he will deliver the poor one crying for help,

Also the afflicted one and whoever has no helper.

13 He will feel sorry for the lowly one and the poor one,

And the souls of the poor ones he will save.

14 From oppression and from violence he will redeem their soul,

And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

15 And let him live, and to him let some of the gold of She′ba be given.

And in his behalf let prayer be made constantly;

All day long let him be blessed.

16 There will come to be plenty of grain on the earth;

On the top of the mountains there will be an overflow.

His fruit will be as in Leb′a·non,

And those who are from the city will blossom like the vegetation of the earth.

17 Let his name prove to be to time indefinite;

Before the sun let his name have increase,

And by means of him let them bless themselves;

Let all nations pronounce him happy.

18 Blessed be Jehovah God, Israel’s God,

Who alone is doing wonderful works.

19 And blessed be his glorious name to time indefinite,

And let his glory fill the whole earth.

Amen and Amen.

20 The prayers of David, the son of Jes′se, have come to their end.

Psalms

BOOK THREE

(Psalms 73 – 89)

A melody of A′saph.

73 God is indeed good to Israel, to those clean in heart.

2 As for me, my feet had almost turned aside,

My steps had nearly been made to slip.

3 For I became envious of the boasters,

When I would see the very peace of wicked people.

4 For they have no deathly pangs;

And their paunch is fat.

5 They are not even in the trouble of mortal man,

And they are not plagued the same as other men.

6 Therefore haughtiness has served as a necklace to them;

Violence envelops them as a garment.

7 Their eye has bulged from fatness;

They have exceeded the imaginations of the heart.

8 They scoff and speak about what is bad;

About defrauding they speak in an elevated style.

9 They have put their mouth in the very heavens,

And their tongue itself walks about in the earth.

10 Therefore he brings his people back hither,

And the waters of what is full are drained out for them.

11 And they have said: “How has God come to know?

And does there exist knowledge in the Most High?”

12 Look! These are the wicked, who are at ease indefinitely.

They have increased their means of maintenance.

13 Surely it is in vain that I have cleansed my heart

And that I wash my hands in innocence itself.

14 And I came to be plagued all day long,

And my correction is every morning.

15 If I had said: “I will tell a story like that,”

Look! against the generation of your sons

I should have acted treacherously.

16 And I kept considering so as to know this;

It was a trouble in my eyes,

17 Until I proceeded to come into the grand sanctuary of God.

I wanted to discern their future.

18 Surely on slippery ground is where you place them.

You have made them fall to ruins.

19 O how they have become an object of astonishment as in a moment!

How they have reached their end, have been brought to their finish through sudden terrors!

20 Like a dream after awaking, O Jehovah,

So when arousing yourself you will despise their very image.

21 For my heart was soured

And in my kidneys I was sharply pained,

22 And I was unreasoning and I could not know;

I became as mere beasts from your standpoint.

23 But I am constantly with you;

You have taken hold of my right hand.

24 With your counsel you will lead me,

And afterward you will take me even to glory.

25 Whom do I have in the heavens?

And besides you I do have no other delight on the earth.

26 My organism and my heart have failed.

God is the rock of my heart and my share to time indefinite.

27 For, look! the very ones keeping away from you will perish.

You will certainly silence every one immorally leaving you.

28 But as for me, the drawing near to God is good for me.

In the Sovereign Lord Jehovah I have placed my refuge,

To declare all your works.

Psalms

A mas′kil. Of A′saph.

74 Why, O God, have you cast off forever?

Why does your anger keep smoking against the flock of your pasturage?

2 Remember your assembly that you acquired long ago,

The tribe that you redeemed as your inheritance,

This Mount Zion in which you have resided.

3 Do lift up your steps to the long-lasting desolations.

Everything the enemy has treated badly in the holy place.

4 Those showing hostility to you have roared in the middle of your meeting place.

They have set their own signs as the signs.

5 One is notorious in being like him that brings up axes on high against a thicket of trees.

6 And now the very engravings of it, one and all, they strike even with hatchet and iron-tipped beams.

7 They have thrust your sanctuary into the fire itself.

They have profaned the tabernacle of your name to the very earth.

8 They, even their offspring, have said together in their own heart:

“All the meeting places of God must be burned in the land.”

9 Our signs we have not seen; there is no prophet anymore,

And there is no one with us knowing how long.

10 How long, O God, will the adversary keep reproaching?

Will the enemy keep treating your name with disrespect forever?

11 Why do you keep your hand, even your right hand, withdrawn

From the midst of your bosom to make an end of us?

12 And yet God is my King from long ago,

The One performing grand salvation in the midst of the earth.

13 You yourself stirred up the sea with your own strength;

You broke the heads of the sea monsters in the waters.

14 You yourself crushed to pieces the heads of Le·vi′a·than.

You proceeded to give it as food to the people, to those inhabiting the waterless regions.

15 You were the One that split the spring and the torrent;

You yourself dried up ever-flowing rivers.

16 To you the day belongs; also, to you the night belongs.

You yourself prepared the luminary, even the sun.

17 It was you that set up all the boundaries of the earth;

Summer and winter—you yourself formed them.

18 Remember this: The enemy himself has reproached, O Jehovah,

And a senseless people have treated your name with disrespect.

19 Do not give to the wild beast the soul of your turtledove.

Do not forget the very life of your afflicted ones forever.

20 Take a look at the covenant,

For the dark places of the earth have become full of the abodes of violence.

21 O may the crushed one not return humiliated.

May the afflicted one and the poor one praise your name.

22 Do arise, O God, do conduct your own case at law.

Remember your reproach from the senseless one all day long.

23 Do not forget the voice of those showing hostility to you.

The noise of those rising up against you is ascending constantly.

Psalms

To the director on Je·du′thun. Of A′saph. A melody.

77 With my voice I will even cry out to God himself,

With my voice to God, and he will certainly give ear to me.

2 In the day of my distress I have searched for Jehovah himself.

At night my very hand has been stretched out and does not grow numb;

My soul has refused to be comforted.

3 I will remember God and be boisterous;

I will show concern, that my spirit may faint away. Se′lah.

4 You have seized hold of my eyelids;

I have become agitated, and I cannot speak.

5 I have thought upon the days of long ago,

On the years in the indefinite past.

6 I will remember my string music in the night;

With my heart I will show concern,

And my spirit will carefully search.

7 Will it be to times indefinite that Jehovah keeps casting off,

And will he no more be pleased again?

8 Has his loving-kindness terminated forever?

Has his saying come to nothing for generation after generation?

9 Has God forgotten to be favorable,

Or has he shut off his mercies in anger? Se′lah.

10 And shall I keep saying: “This is what pierces me through,

The changing of the right hand of the Most High”?

11 I shall remember the practices of Jah;

For I will remember your marvelous doing of long ago.

12 And I shall certainly meditate on all your activity,

And with your dealings I will concern myself.

13 O God, your way is in the holy place.

Who is a great God like God?

14 You are the true God, doing marvelously.

Among the peoples you have made your strength known.

15 With your arm you have recovered your people,

The sons of Jacob and of Joseph. Se′lah.

16 The waters have seen you, O God,

The waters have seen you; they began to be in severe pains.

Also, the watery deeps began to be agitated.

17 The clouds have thunderously poured down water;

A sound the cloudy skies have given forth.

Also, your own arrows proceeded to go here and there.

18 The sound of your thunder was like chariot wheels;

Lightnings have lighted up the productive land;

The earth became agitated and began to rock.

19 Through the sea your way was,

And your path was through many waters;

And your very footprints have not come to be known.

20 You have led your people just like a flock,

By the hand of Moses and Aaron.

Psalms

Mas′kil. Of A′saph.

78 Do give ear, O my people, to my law;

Incline YOUR ear to the sayings of my mouth.

2 In a proverbial saying I will open my mouth;

I will cause riddles of long ago to bubble forth,

3 Which we have heard and know,

And which our own fathers have related to us;

4 Which we do not hide from their sons,

Relating them even to the generation to come,

The praises of Jehovah and his strength

And his wonderful things that he has done.

5 And he proceeded to raise up a reminder in Jacob,

And a law he set in Israel,

Things that he commanded our forefathers,

To make them known to their sons;

6 In order that the generation to come, the sons that were to be born, might know them,

That they might rise up and relate them to their sons,

7 And that they might set their confidence in God himself

And not forget the practices of God but observe his own commandments.

8 And they should not become like their forefathers,

A generation stubborn and rebellious,

A generation who had not prepared their heart

And whose spirit was not trustworthy with God.

9 The sons of E′phra·im, though armed shooters of the bow,

Retreated in the day of fight.

10 They did not keep the covenant of God,

And in his law they refused to walk.

11 They also began to forget his dealings

And his wonderful works that he caused them to see.

12 In front of their forefathers he had done marvelously

In the land of Egypt, the field of Zo′an.

13 He split the sea, that he might let them pass over,

And he caused the waters to stand like a dam.

14 And he continued to lead them with a cloud by day

And the whole night with a light of fire.

15 He proceeded to split rocks in the wilderness,

That he might cause them to drink an abundance just like watery deeps.

16 And he went bringing forth streams out of a crag

And causing waters to descend just like rivers.

17 And they kept sinning still more against him

By rebelling against the Most High in the waterless region;

18 And they proceeded to test God in their heart

By asking for something to eat for their soul.

19 So they began to speak against God.

They said: “Is God able to arrange a table in the wilderness?”

20 Look! He struck a rock

That waters might flow and torrents themselves might flood forth.

“Is he able also to give bread itself,

Or can he prepare sustenance for his people?”

21 That was why Jehovah heard and began to be furious;

And fire itself was kindled against Jacob,

And anger also ascended against Israel.

22 For they did not put faith in God,

And they did not trust in salvation by him.

23 And he proceeded to command the cloudy skies above,

And he opened the very doors of heaven.

24 And he kept raining upon them manna to eat,

And the grain of heaven he gave to them.

25 Men ate the very bread of powerful ones;

Provisions he sent them to satisfaction.

26 He began making an east wind burst forth in the heavens

And making a south wind blow by his own strength.

27 And he proceeded to make sustenance rain upon them just like dust,

Even winged flying creatures just like the sand grains of the seas.

28 And he kept making them fall in the middle of his camp,

All around his tabernacles.

29 And they went eating and satisfying themselves very much,

And what they desired he proceeded to bring to them.

30 They had not turned aside from their desire,

While their food was yet in their mouth,

31 When God’s wrath itself ascended against them.

And he went killing among their stout ones;

And the young men of Israel he made collapse.

32 Despite all this they sinned some more

And did not put faith in his wonderful works.

33 So he brought their days to an end as if a mere exhalation,

And their years by the disturbance.

34 As often as he killed them, they also inquired for him,

And they returned and looked for God.

35 And they began to remember that God was their Rock,

And that God the Most High was their Avenger.

36 And they tried to fool him with their mouth;

And with their tongue they tried to lie to him.

37 And their heart was not steadfast with him;

And they did not prove faithful in his covenant.

38 But he was merciful; he would cover the error and not bring ruin.

And many times he made his anger turn back,

And he would not rouse up all his rage.

39 And he kept remembering that they were flesh,

That the spirit is going forth and does not come back.

40 How often they would rebel against him in the wilderness,

They would make him feel hurt in the desert!

41 And again and again they would put God to the test,

And they pained even the Holy One of Israel.

42 They did not remember his hand,

The day that he redeemed them from the adversary,

43 How he put his signs in Egypt itself

And his miracles in the field of Zo′an;

44 And how he began changing to blood their Nile canals,

So that they could not drink from their own streams.

45 He proceeded to send upon them gadflies, that these might eat them up;

And frogs, that these might bring them to ruin.

46 And he began to give to the cockroaches their yield,

And their toil to the locusts.

47 He went killing their vine even by the hail

And their sycamore trees by hailstones.

48 And he proceeded to hand over their beasts of burden even to the hail

And their livestock to the flaming fever.

49 He went sending upon them his burning anger,

Fury and denunciation and distress,

Deputations of angels bringing calamity.

50 He proceeded to prepare a pathway for his anger.

He did not hold back their soul from death itself;

And their life he handed over even to the pestilence.

51 Finally he struck down all the firstborn in Egypt,

The beginning of their generative power in the tents of Ham.

52 Afterward he caused his people to depart just like a flock,

And conducted them like a drove in the wilderness.

53 And he kept leading them in security, and they felt no dread;

And the sea covered their enemies themselves.

54 And he proceeded to bring them to his holy territory,

This mountainous region that his right hand acquired.

55 And because of them he gradually drove out the nations,

And by the measuring line he went allotting them an inheritance,

So that he caused the tribes of Israel to reside in their own homes.

56 And they began to test and rebel against God the Most High,

And his reminders they did not keep.

57 They also kept turning back and acting treacherously like their forefathers;

They turned around like a loose bow.

58 And they kept offending him with their high places,

And with their graven images they kept inciting him to jealousy.

59 God heard and got to be furious,

And so he contemned Israel very much.

60 And he finally forsook the tabernacle of Shi′loh,

The tent in which he resided among earthling men.

61 And he proceeded to give his strength even to captivity

And his beauty into the hand of the adversary.

62 And he kept handing over his people to the sword itself,

And against his inheritance he became furious.

63 His young men a fire ate up,

And his virgins were not praised.

64 As for his priests, they fell by the very sword,

And their own widows did not give way to weeping.

65 Then Jehovah began to awake as from sleeping,

Like a mighty one sobering up from wine.

66 And he went striking down his adversaries from behind;

A reproach of indefinite duration he gave to them.

67 And he proceeded to reject the tent of Joseph;

And the tribe of E′phra·im he did not choose.

68 But he chose the tribe of Judah,

Mount Zion, which he loved.

69 And he began to build his sanctuary just like the heights,

Like the earth that he has founded to time indefinite.

70 And so he chose David his servant

And took him from the pens of the flock.

71 From following the females giving suck

He brought him in to be a shepherd over Jacob his people

And over Israel his inheritance.

72 And he began to shepherd them according to the integrity of his heart,

And with the skillfulness of his hands he began leading them.

Psalms

A melody of A′saph.

79 O God, the nations have come into your inheritance;

They have defiled your holy temple;

They have laid Jerusalem in a heap of ruins.

2 They have given the dead body of your servants as food to the fowls of the heavens,

The flesh of your loyal ones to the wild beasts of the earth.

3 They have poured out their blood like water

All around Jerusalem, and there is no one to do the burying.

4 We have become a reproach to our neighbors,

A derision and a jeering to those round about us.

5 How long, O Jehovah, will you be incensed? Forever?

How long will your ardor burn just like fire?

6 Pour out your rage upon the nations that have not known you,

And upon the kingdoms that have not called upon your own name.

7 For they have eaten up Jacob,

And they have caused his own abiding place to be desolated.

8 Do not remember against us the errors of ancestors.

Hurry! Let your mercies confront us,

For we have become greatly impoverished.

9 Help us, O God of our salvation,

For the sake of the glory of your name;

And deliver us and cover over our sins on account of your name.

10 Why should the nations say: “Where is their God?”

Among the nations let there be known before our eyes

The avenging of the blood of your servants that has been shed.

11 May the sighing of the prisoner come in even before you.

According to the greatness of your arm preserve those appointed to death.

12 And repay to our neighbors seven times into their bosom

Their reproach with which they have reproached you, O Jehovah.

13 As for us your people and the flock of your pasturage,

We shall give thanks to you to time indefinite;

From generation to generation we shall declare your praise.

Psalms

To the director upon the Git′tith. Of A′saph.

81 O cry out joyfully, YOU people, to God our strength;

Shout in triumph to the God of Jacob.

2 Strike up a melody and take a tambourine,

The pleasant harp together with the stringed instrument.

3 On the new moon, BLOW the horn;

On the full moon, for the day of our festival.

4 For it is a regulation for Israel,

A judicial decision of the God of Jacob.

5 As a reminder he laid it upon Joseph himself,

When he was going forth over the land of Egypt.

A language that I did not know I kept hearing.

6 “I turned aside his shoulder even from the burden;

His own hands got to be free even from the basket.

7 In distress you called, and I proceeded to rescue you;

I began to answer you in the concealed place of thunder.

I went examining you at the waters of Mer′i·bah. Se′lah.

8 Hear, O my people, and I will bear witness against you,

O Israel, if you will listen to me.

9 Among you there will prove to be no strange god;

And you will not bow down to a foreign god.

10 I, Jehovah, am your God,

The One bringing you up out of the land of Egypt.

Open your mouth wide, and I shall fill it.

11 But my people has not listened to my voice;

And Israel itself has not showed any willingness toward me.

12 And so I let them go in the stubbornness of their heart;

They went walking in their own counsels.

13 O that my people were listening to me,

O that Israel itself would walk in my very ways!

14 Their enemies I would easily subdue,

And against their adversaries I would turn my hand.

15 As for those intensely hating Jehovah, they will come cringing to him,

And their time will prove to be to time indefinite.

16 And he will keep feeding him off the fat of the wheat,

And out of the rock I shall satisfy you with honey itself.”

Psalms

A song. A melody of A′saph.

83 O God, let there be no silence on your part;

Do not keep speechless, and do not stay quiet, O Divine One.

2 For, look! your very enemies are in an uproar;

And the very ones intensely hating you have raised their head.

3 Against your people they cunningly carry on their confidential talk;

And they conspire against your concealed ones.

4 They have said: “Come and let us efface them from being a nation,

That the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”

5 For with the heart they have unitedly exchanged counsel;

Against you they proceeded to conclude even a covenant,

6 The tents of E′dom and the Ish′ma·el·ites, Mo′ab and the Hag′rites,

7 Ge′bal and Am′mon and Am′a·lek,

Phi·lis′ti·a together with the inhabitants of Tyre.

8 Also, As·syr′i·a itself has become joined with them;

They have become an arm to the sons of Lot. Se′lah.

9 Do to them as to Mid′i·an, as to Sis′e·ra,

As to Ja′bin at the torrent valley of Ki′shon.

10 They were annihilated at En-dor;

They became manure for the ground.

11 As for their nobles, make these like O′reb and like Ze′eb,

And like Ze′bah and like Zal·mun′na all their dukes,

12 Who have said: “Let us take possession of the abiding places of God for ourselves.”

13 O my God, make them like a thistle whirl,

Like stubble before a wind.

14 Like a fire that burns up the forest

And like a flame that scorches the mountains,

15 In just that way may you pursue them with your tempest

And may you disturb them with your own storm wind.

16 Fill their faces with dishonor,

That people may search for your name, O Jehovah.

17 O may they be ashamed and be disturbed for all times,

And may they become abashed and perish;

18 That people may know that you, whose name is Jehovah,

You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

Psalms

A prayer of David.

86 Incline, O Jehovah, your ear. Answer me,

For I am afflicted and poor.

2 O do guard my soul, for I am loyal.

Save your servant—you are my God—that is trusting in you.

3 Show me favor, O Jehovah,

For to you I keep calling all day long.

4 Make the soul of your servant rejoice,

For to you, O Jehovah, I lift up my very soul.

5 For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive;

And the loving-kindness to all those calling upon you is abundant.

6 Do give ear, O Jehovah, to my prayer;

And do pay attention to the voice of my entreaties.

7 In the day of my distress I will call upon you,

For you will answer me.

8 There is none like you among the gods, O Jehovah,

Neither are there any works like yours.

9 All the nations whom you have made will themselves come,

And they will bow down before you, O Jehovah,

And will give glory to your name.

10 For you are great and are doing wondrous things;

You are God, you alone.

11 Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way.

I shall walk in your truth.

Unify my heart to fear your name.

12 I laud you, O Jehovah my God, with all my heart,

And I will glorify your name to time indefinite,

13 For your loving-kindness is great toward me,

And you have delivered my soul out of She′ol, its lowest place.

14 O God, the presumptuous ones themselves have risen up against me;

And the very assembly of tyrannical ones have looked for my soul,

And they have not set you in front of themselves.

15 But you, O Jehovah, are a God merciful and gracious,

Slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness and trueness.

16 Turn to me and show me favor.

Do give your strength to your servant,

And do save the son of your slave girl.

17 Work out with me a sign meaning goodness,

That those hating me may see it and be ashamed.

For you yourself, O Jehovah, have helped me and comforted me.

Psalms

A song, a melody of the sons of Ko′rah. To the director over Ma′ha·lath for making responses. Mas′kil of He′man the Ez′ra·hite.

88 O Jehovah, the God of my salvation,

By day I have cried out,

In the night also in front of you.

2 Before you my prayer will come.

Incline your ear to my entreating cry.

3 For my soul has had enough of calamities,

And my very life has come in touch even with She′ol.

4 I have been reckoned in among those going down to the pit;

I have become like an able-bodied man without strength,

5 Set free among the dead themselves,

Like slain ones lying in the burial place,

Whom you have remembered no longer

And who have been severed from your own helping hand.

6 You have put me in a pit of the lowest depths,

In dark places, in a large abyss.

7 Upon me your rage has thrown itself,

And with all your breaking waves you have afflicted me. Se′lah.

8 You have put my acquaintances far away from me;

You have set me as something very detestable to them.

I am under restraint and cannot go forth.

9 My own eye has languished because of my affliction.

I have called on you, O Jehovah, all day long;

To you I have spread out my palms.

10 For those who are dead will you do a marvel?

Or will those impotent in death themselves arise,

Will they laud you? Se′lah.

11 Will your loving-kindness be declared in the burial place itself,

Your faithfulness in the place of destruction?

12 Will a marvel by you be known in the darkness itself,

Or your righteousness in the land of oblivion?

13 And yet to you, O Jehovah, I myself have cried for help,

And in the morning my own prayer keeps confronting you.

14 Why is it, O Jehovah, that you cast off my soul?

Why do you keep your face concealed from me?

15 I am afflicted and about to expire from boyhood on;

I have borne frightful things from you very much.

16 Over me your flashes of burning anger have passed;

Terrors from you yourself have brought me to silence.

17 They have surrounded me like waters all day long;

They have closed in upon me all at one time.

18 You have put far away from me friend and companion;

My acquaintances are a dark place.

Psalms

Mas′kil. Of E′than the Ez′ra·hite.

89 Jehovah’s expressions of loving-kindness I will sing about even to time indefinite.

For generation after generation I shall make your faithfulness known with my mouth.

2 For I have said: “Loving-kindness will stay built even to time indefinite;

As for the heavens, you keep your faithfulness firmly established in them.”

3 “I have concluded a covenant toward my chosen one;

I have sworn to David my servant,

4 ‘Even to time indefinite I shall firmly establish your seed,

And I will build your throne to generation after generation.’” Se′lah.

5 And the heavens will laud your marvelous act, O Jehovah,

Yes, your faithfulness in the congregation of the holy ones.

6 For who in the skies can be compared to Jehovah?

Who can resemble Jehovah among the sons of God?

7 God is to be held in awe among the intimate group of holy ones;

He is grand and fear-inspiring over all who are round about him.

8 O Jehovah God of armies,

Who is vigorous like you, O Jah?

And your faithfulness is all around you.

9 You are ruling over the swelling of the sea;

When it raises up its waves you yourself calm them.

10 You yourself have crushed Ra′hab, even as someone slain.

By the arm of your strength you have scattered your enemies.

11 Heaven is yours, the earth also is yours;

The productive land and what fills it—you yourself have founded them.

12 The north and the south—you yourself created them;

Ta′bor and Her′mon—in your name they cry out joyfully.

13 An arm with mightiness is yours,

Your hand is strong,

Your right hand is exalted.

14 Righteousness and judgment are the established place of your throne;

Loving-kindness and trueness themselves come in before your face.

15 Happy are the people knowing the joyful shouting.

O Jehovah, in the light of your face they keep walking.

16 In your name they are joyful all day long

And in your righteousness they are exalted.

17 For you are the beauty of their strength;

And by your goodwill our horn is exalted.

18 For our shield belongs to Jehovah,

And our king belongs to the Holy One of Israel.

19 At that time you spoke in a vision to your loyal ones,

And you proceeded to say:

“I have placed help upon a mighty one;

I have exalted a chosen one from among the people.

20 I have found David my servant;

With my holy oil I have anointed him,

21 With whom my own hand will be firm,

Whom my own arm also will strengthen.

22 No enemy will make exactions upon him,

Neither will any son of unrighteousness afflict him.

23 And from before him I crushed his adversaries to pieces,

And to those intensely hating him I kept dealing out blows.

24 And my faithfulness and my loving-kindness are with him,

And in my name his horn is exalted.

25 And on the sea I have put his hand

And on the rivers his right hand.

26 He himself calls out to me, ‘You are my Father,

My God and the Rock of my salvation.’

27 Also, I myself shall place him as firstborn,

The most high of the kings of the earth.

28 To time indefinite I shall preserve my loving-kindness toward him,

And my covenant will be faithful to him.

29 And I shall certainly set up his seed forever

And his throne as the days of heaven.

30 If his sons leave my law

And in my judicial decisions they do not walk,

31 If they profane my own statutes

And they do not keep my own commandments,

32 I must also turn my attention to their transgression even with a rod

And to their error even with strokes.

33 But my loving-kindness I shall not break off from him,

Nor shall I prove false with regard to my faithfulness.

34 I shall not profane my covenant,

And the expression out of my lips I shall not change.

35 Once I have sworn in my holiness,

To David I will not tell lies.

36 His seed itself will prove to be even to time indefinite,

And his throne as the sun in front of me.

37 As the moon it will be firmly established for time indefinite,

And as a faithful witness in the skies.” Se′lah.

38 But you—you have cast off and you keep contemning;

You have become furious toward your anointed one.

39 You have spurned the covenant of your servant;

You have profaned his diadem to the very earth.

40 You have broken down all his stone pens;

You have laid his fortifications in ruin.

41 All those passing along the way have pillaged him;

He has become a reproach to his neighbors.

42 You have exalted the right hand of his adversaries;

You have caused all his enemies to rejoice.

43 What is more, you again treat his sword as a foe,

And you have caused him not to gain ground in the battle.

44 You have made him cease from his luster,

And his throne you have hurled to the very earth.

45 You have shortened the days of his youth;

You have enwrapped him with shame. Se′lah.

46 How long, O Jehovah, will you keep yourself concealed? For all time?

Will your rage keep on burning just like a fire?

47 Remember of what duration of life I am.

Is it all in vain that you have created all the sons of men?

48 What able-bodied man is there alive who will not see death?

Can he provide escape for his soul from the hand of She′ol? Se′lah.

49 Where are your former acts of loving-kindness, O Jehovah,

About which you swore to David in your faithfulness?

50 Remember, O Jehovah, the reproach upon your servants,

My carrying in my bosom the reproach of all the many peoples,

51 How your enemies have reproached, O Jehovah,

How they have reproached the footprints of your anointed one.

52 Blessed be Jehovah to time indefinite. Amen and Amen.

Psalms

BOOK FOUR

(Psalms 90 – 106)

A prayer of Moses, the man of the true God.

90 O Jehovah, you yourself have proved to be a real dwelling for us

During generation after generation.

2 Before the mountains themselves were born,

Or you proceeded to bring forth as with labor pains the earth and the productive land,

Even from time indefinite to time indefinite you are God.

3 You make mortal man go back to crushed matter,

And you say: “GO back, YOU sons of men.”

4 For a thousand years are in your eyes but as yesterday when it is past,

And as a watch during the night.

5 You have swept them away; they become a mere sleep;

In the morning they are just like green grass that changes.

6 In the morning it puts forth blossoms and must change;

At evening it withers and certainly dries up.

7 For we have come to an end in your anger,

And by your rage we have been disturbed.

8 You have set our errors right in front of you,

Our hidden things before your bright face.

9 For all our days have come to their decline in your fury;

We have finished our years just like a whisper.

10 In themselves the days of our years are seventy years;

And if because of special mightiness they are eighty years,

Yet their insistence is on trouble and hurtful things;

For it must quickly pass by, and away we fly.

11 Who is there knowing the strength of your anger

And your fury according to the fear of you?

12 Show us just how to count our days in such a way

That we may bring a heart of wisdom in.

13 Do return, O Jehovah! How long will it be?

And feel regret over your servants.

14 Satisfy us in the morning with your loving-kindness,

That we may cry out joyfully and may rejoice during all our days.

15 Make us rejoice correspondingly to the days that you have afflicted us,

The years that we have seen calamity.

16 May your activity appear to your own servants

And your splendor upon their sons.

17 And let the pleasantness of Jehovah our God prove to be upon us,

And the work of our hands do you firmly establish upon us.

Yes, the work of our hands, do you firmly establish it.

Psalms

91 Anyone dwelling in the secret place of the Most High

Will procure himself lodging under the very shadow of the Almighty One.

2 I will say to Jehovah: “You are my refuge and my stronghold,

My God, in whom I will trust.”

3 For he himself will deliver you from the trap of the birdcatcher,

From the pestilence causing adversities.

4 With his pinions he will block approach to you,

And under his wings you will take refuge.

His trueness will be a large shield and bulwark.

5 You will not be afraid of anything dreadful by night,

Nor of the arrow that flies by day,

6 Nor of the pestilence that walks in the gloom,

Nor of the destruction that despoils at midday.

7 A thousand will fall at your very side

And ten thousand at your right hand;

To you it will not come near.

8 Only with your eyes will you look on

And see the retribution itself of the wicked ones.

9 Because you said: “Jehovah is my refuge,”

You have made the Most High himself your dwelling;

10 No calamity will befall you,

And not even a plague will draw near to your tent.

11 For he will give his own angels a command concerning you,

To guard you in all your ways.

12 Upon their hands they will carry you,

That you may not strike your foot against any stone.

13 Upon the young lion and the cobra you will tread;

You will trample down the maned young lion and the big snake.

14 Because on me he has set his affection,

I shall also provide him with escape.

I shall protect him because he has come to know my name.

15 He will call upon me, and I shall answer him.

I shall be with him in distress.

I shall rescue him and glorify him.

16 With length of days I shall satisfy him,

And I shall cause him to see salvation by me.

Psalms

94 O God of acts of vengeance, Jehovah,

O God of acts of vengeance, beam forth!

2 Raise yourself up, O Judge of the earth.

Bring back a retribution upon the haughty ones.

3 How long are the wicked, O Jehovah,

How long are the wicked themselves going to exult?

4 They keep bubbling forth, they keep speaking unrestrained;

All the practicers of what is hurtful keep bragging about themselves.

5 Your people, O Jehovah, they keep crushing,

And your inheritance they keep afflicting.

6 The widow and the alien resident they kill,

And the fatherless boys they murder.

7 And they keep saying: “Jah does not see;

And the God of Jacob does not understand it.”

8 Understand, YOU who are unreasoning among the people;

And as for YOU stupid ones, when will YOU have any insight?

9 The One planting the ear, can he not hear?

Or the One forming the eye, can he not look?

10 The One correcting the nations, can he not reprove,

Even the One teaching men knowledge?

11 Jehovah is knowing the thoughts of men, that they are as an exhalation.

12 Happy is the able-bodied man whom you correct, O Jah,

And whom you teach out of your own law,

13 To give him quietness from days of calamity,

Until for the wicked one a pit is excavated.

14 For Jehovah will not forsake his people,

Nor will he leave his own inheritance.

15 For judicial decision will return even to righteousness,

And all the upright in heart will follow it.

16 Who will rise up for me against the evildoers?

Who will take his stand for me against the practicers of hurtfulness?

17 Unless Jehovah had been of assistance to me,

In a little while my soul would have resided in silence.

18 When I said: “My foot will certainly move unsteadily,”

Your own loving-kindness, O Jehovah, kept sustaining me.

19 When my disquieting thoughts became many inside of me,

Your own consolations began to fondle my soul.

20 Will the throne causing adversities be allied with you

While it is framing trouble by decree?

21 They make sharp attacks on the soul of the righteous one

And pronounce wicked even the blood of the innocent one.

22 But Jehovah will become a secure height for me,

And my God the rock of my refuge.

23 And he will turn back upon them their hurtfulness

And will silence them with their own calamity.

Jehovah our God will silence them.

Psalms

A prayer of the afflicted in case he grows feeble and pours out his concern before Jehovah himself.

102 O Jehovah, do hear my prayer;

And to you may my own cry for help come.

2 Do not conceal your face from me on the day that I am in sore straits.

Incline to me your ear;

On the day that I call, hurry, answer me.

3 For my days have come to an end just like smoke,

And my very bones have been made red-hot just like a fireplace.

4 My heart has been struck just like vegetation and is dried up,

For I have forgotten to eat my food.

5 Because of the sound of my sighing

My bones have stuck to my flesh.

6 I do resemble the pelican of the wilderness.

I have become like a little owl of desolated places.

7 I have grown emaciated,

And I am become like a bird isolated upon a roof.

8 All day long my enemies have reproached me.

Those making a fool of me have sworn even by me.

9 For I have eaten ashes themselves just like bread;

And the things I drink I have mingled even with weeping,

10 Because of your denunciation and your indignation;

For you have lifted me up, that you might throw me away.

11 My days are like a shadow that has declined,

And I myself am dried up like mere vegetation.

12 As for you, O Jehovah, to time indefinite you will dwell,

And your memorial will be for generation after generation.

13 You yourself will arise, you will have mercy on Zion,

For it is the season to be favorable to her,

For the appointed time has come.

14 For your servants have found pleasure in her stones,

And to her dust they direct their favor.

15 And the nations will fear the name of Jehovah,

And all the kings of the earth your glory.

16 For Jehovah will certainly build up Zion;

He must appear in his glory.

17 He will certainly turn to the prayer of those stripped of everything,

And not despise their prayer.

18 This is written for the future generation;

And the people that is to be created will praise Jah.

19 For he has looked down from his holy height,

From the very heavens Jehovah himself has looked even at the earth,

20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner,

To loosen those appointed to death;

21 For the name of Jehovah to be declared in Zion

And his praise in Jerusalem,

22 When the peoples are collected all together,

And the kingdoms to serve Jehovah.

23 On the way he afflicted my power,

He cut short my days.

24 I proceeded to say: “O my God,

Do not take me off at the half of my days;

Your years are throughout all generations.

25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth itself,

And the heavens are the work of your hands.

26 They themselves will perish, but you yourself will keep standing;

And just like a garment they will all of them wear out.

Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will finish their turn.

27 But you are the same, and your own years will not be completed.

28 The sons of your servants will continue residing;

And before you their own offspring will be firmly established.”

Psalms

Of David.

103 Bless Jehovah, O my soul,

Even everything within me, his holy name.

2 Bless Jehovah, O my soul,

And do not forget all his doings,

3 Him who is forgiving all your error,

Who is healing all your maladies,

4 Who is reclaiming your life from the very pit,

Who is crowning you with loving-kindness and mercies,

5 Who is satisfying your lifetime with what is good;

Your youth keeps renewing itself just like that of an eagle.

6 Jehovah is executing acts of righteousness

And judicial decisions for all those being defrauded.

7 He made known his ways to Moses,

His dealings even to the sons of Israel.

8 Jehovah is merciful and gracious,

Slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness.

9 He will not for all time keep finding fault,

Neither will he to time indefinite keep resentful.

10 He has not done to us even according to our sins;

Nor according to our errors has he brought upon us what we deserve.

11 For as the heavens are higher than the earth,

His loving-kindness is superior toward those fearing him.

12 As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset,

So far off from us he has put our transgressions.

13 As a father shows mercy to his sons,

Jehovah has shown mercy to those fearing him.

14 For he himself well knows the formation of us,

Remembering that we are dust.

15 As for mortal man, his days are like those of green grass;

Like a blossom of the field is the way he blossoms forth.

16 For a mere wind has to pass over it, and it is no more;

And its place will acknowledge it no further.

17 But the loving-kindness of Jehovah is from time indefinite even to time indefinite

Toward those fearing him,

And his righteousness to the sons of sons,

18 Toward those keeping his covenant

And toward those remembering his orders so as to carry them out.

19 Jehovah himself has firmly established his throne in the very heavens;

And over everything his own kingship has held domination.

20 Bless Jehovah, O YOU angels of his, mighty in power, carrying out his word,

By listening to the voice of his word.

21 Bless Jehovah, all YOU armies of his,

YOU ministers of his, doing his will.

22 Bless Jehovah, all YOU his works,

In all places of his domination.

Bless Jehovah, O my soul.

Psalms

105 GIVE thanks to Jehovah, call upon his name,

Make known among the peoples his dealings.

2 Sing to him, make melody to him,

Concern yourselves with all his wonderful works.

3 Make YOUR boast in his holy name.

Let the heart of those seeking Jehovah rejoice.

4 Search for Jehovah and his strength.

Seek his face constantly.

5 Remember his wonderful works that he has performed,

His miracles and the judicial decisions of his mouth,

6 O YOU seed of Abraham his servant,

YOU sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.

7 He is Jehovah our God.

His judicial decisions are in all the earth.

8 He has remembered his covenant even to time indefinite,

The word that he commanded, to a thousand generations,

9 Which covenant he concluded with Abraham,

And his sworn statement to Isaac,

10 And which statement he kept standing as a regulation even to Jacob,

As an indefinitely lasting covenant even to Israel,

11 Saying: “To you I shall give the land of Ca′naan

As the allotment of YOUR inheritance.”

12 This was when they happened to be few in number,

Yes, very few, and alien residents in it.

13 And they kept walking about from nation to nation,

From one kingdom to another people.

14 He did not allow any human to defraud them,

But on their account he reproved kings,

15 Saying: “Do not YOU men touch my anointed ones,

And to my prophets do nothing bad.”

16 And he proceeded to call for a famine upon the land;

He broke every rod around which ring-shaped loaves were suspended.

17 He sent ahead of them a man

Who was sold to be a slave, Joseph.

18 With fetters they afflicted his feet,

Into irons his soul came;

19 Until the time that his word came,

The saying of Jehovah itself refined him.

20 The king sent that he might release him,

The ruler of the peoples, that he might let him loose.

21 He set him as master to his household

And as ruler over all his property,

22 To bind his princes agreeably to his soul

And that he might teach wisdom to even his elderly men.

23 And Israel proceeded to come into Egypt,

And Jacob himself resided as an alien in the land of Ham.

24 And he kept making his people very fruitful,

And gradually made them mightier than their adversaries.

25 He let their heart change to hate his people,

To behave cunningly against his servants.

26 He sent Moses his servant,

Aaron whom he had chosen.

27 They set among them the matters of his signs,

And the miracles in the land of Ham.

28 He sent darkness and so made it dark;

And they did not rebel against his words.

29 He changed their waters into blood,

And proceeded to put their fish to death.

30 Their land swarmed with frogs,

In the interior rooms of their kings.

31 He said that the gadflies should come in,

Gnats in all their territories.

32 He made their downpours hail,

A flaming fire on their land.

33 And he proceeded to strike their vines and their fig trees

And to break the trees of their territory.

34 He said that the locusts should come in,

And a species of locust, even without number.

35 And they went eating all the vegetation in their land;

They also went eating the fruitage of their ground.

36 And he proceeded to strike down every firstborn in their land,

The beginning of all their generative power.

37 And he began to bring them out with silver and gold;

And among his tribes there was no one stumbling along.

38 Egypt rejoiced when they went out,

For the dread of them had fallen upon them.

39 He spread out a cloud for a screen,

And fire to give light by night.

40 They asked, and he proceeded to bring quails,

And with bread from heaven he kept satisfying them.

41 He opened a rock, and waters began to flow out;

These went through the waterless regions as a river.

42 For he remembered his holy word with Abraham his servant.

43 So he brought out his people with exultation,

His chosen ones even with a joyful cry.

44 And gradually he gave them the lands of the nations,

And they kept taking possession of the product of the hard work of national groups,

45 To the end that they might keep his regulations

And observe his own laws.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Psalms

BOOK FIVE

(Psalms 107 – 150)

107 O give thanks to Jehovah, YOU people, for he is good;

For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.

2 Let the reclaimed ones of Jehovah say so,

Whom he has reclaimed from the hand of the adversary,

3 And whom he has collected together even from the lands,

From the sunrise and from the sunset,

From the north and from the south.

4 They wandered about in the wilderness, in the desert;

They did not find any way to a city of habitation.

5 They were hungry, also thirsty;

Their very soul within them began to faint away.

6 And they kept crying out to Jehovah in their distress;

Out of the stresses upon them he proceeded to deliver them,

7 And to have them walk in the right way,

So as to come to a city of habitation.

8 O let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loving-kindness

And for his wonderful works to the sons of men.

9 For he has satisfied the dried-out soul;

And the hungry soul he has filled with good things.

10 There were those dwelling in darkness and deep shadow,

Prisoners in affliction and irons.

11 For they had behaved rebelliously against the sayings of God;

And the counsel of the Most High they had disrespected.

12 So with trouble he proceeded to subdue their heart;

They stumbled, and there was no one helping.

13 And they began calling to Jehovah for help in their distress;

Out of the stresses upon them he as usual saved them.

14 He went bringing them out from darkness and deep shadow,

And tearing even their bands apart.

15 O let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loving-kindness

And for his wonderful works to the sons of men.

16 For he has broken the doors of copper,

And he has cut down even the bars of iron.

17 Those who were foolish, due to the way of their transgression

And due to their errors, finally caused themselves affliction.

18 Their soul got to detest even every sort of food,

And they were arriving at the gates of death.

19 And they began calling to Jehovah for help in their distress;

Out of the stresses upon them he as usual saved them.

20 He proceeded to send his word and heal them

And to provide them escape out of their pits.

21 O let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loving-kindness

And for his wonderful works to the sons of men.

22 And let them offer the sacrifices of thanksgiving

And declare his works with a joyful cry.

23 Those going down to the sea in the ships,

Doing business on vast waters,

24 They are the ones that have seen the works of Jehovah

And his wonderful works in the depths;

25 How he says the word and causes a tempestuous wind to arise,

So that it lifts up its waves.

26 They go up to the heavens,

They go down to the bottoms.

Because of the calamity their very soul finds itself melting.

27 They reel and move unsteadily like a drunken man,

And even all their wisdom proves confused.

28 And they begin crying out to Jehovah in their distress,

And out of the stresses upon them he brings them forth.

29 He causes the windstorm to stand at a calm,

So that the waves of the sea keep quiet.

30 And they rejoice because these become still,

And he leads them to the haven of their delight.

31 O let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loving-kindness

And for his wonderful works to the sons of men.

32 And let them extol him in the congregation of the people;

And in the seat of the elderly men let them praise him.

33 He converts rivers into a wilderness,

And the outflows of water into thirsty ground,

34 Fruitful land into salt country,

Owing to the badness of those dwelling in it.

35 He converts a wilderness into a reedy pool of water,

And the land of a waterless region into outflows of water.

36 And there he causes the hungry ones to dwell,

So that they firmly establish a city of habitation.

37 And they sow fields and plant vineyards,

That they may yield fruitful crops.

38 And he blesses them so that they become very many;

And he does not let their cattle become few.

39 Again they become few and crouch down

Owing to restraint, calamity and grief.

40 He is pouring out contempt upon nobles,

So that he makes them wander about in a featureless place, where there is no way.

41 But he protects the poor one from affliction

And converts him into families just like a flock.

42 The upright ones see and rejoice;

But as for all unrighteousness, it has to shut its mouth.

43 Who is wise? He will both observe these things

And show himself attentive toward Jehovah’s acts of loving-kindness.

Psalms

A song. A melody of David.

108 My heart is steadfast, O God.

I will sing and make melody,

Even my glory.

2 Do awake, O stringed instrument; you too, O harp.

I will awaken the dawn.

3 I shall laud you among the peoples, O Jehovah;

And I shall make melody to you among the national groups.

4 For your loving-kindness is great up to the heavens,

And your trueness up to the skies.

5 O be exalted above the heavens, O God;

And let your glory be above all the earth.

6 In order that your beloved ones may be rescued,

O do save with your right hand and answer me.

7 God himself has spoken in his holiness:

“I will exult, I will give out She′chem as a portion;

And the low plain of Suc′coth I shall measure off.

8 Gil′e·ad belongs to me; Ma·nas′seh belongs to me;

And E′phra·im is the fortress of my head one;

Judah is my commander’s staff.

9 Mo′ab is my washing pot.

Over E′dom I shall throw my sandal.

Over Phi·lis′ti·a I shall shout in triumph.”

10 Who will bring me to the fortified city?

Who will actually lead me as far as E′dom?

11 Is it not you, O God, who have cast us off

And who do not go forth with our armies as God?

12 Do give us assistance from distress,

As salvation by earthling man is worthless.

13 By God we shall gain vital energy,

And he himself will tread down our adversaries.

Psalms

To the director. Of David. A melody.

109 O God of my praise, do not keep silent.

2 For the mouth of the wicked one and the mouth of deception have opened against me.

They have spoken about me with the tongue of falsehood;

3 And with words of hatred they have surrounded me,

And they keep fighting against me without cause.

4 For my love they keep resisting me;

But on my part there is prayer.

5 And they render to me bad for good

And hatred for my love.

6 Appoint over him someone wicked,

And may a resister himself keep standing at his right hand.

7 When he is judged, let him go forth as someone wicked;

And let his very prayer become a sin.

8 Let his days prove to be few;

His office of oversight let someone else take.

9 Let his sons become fatherless boys

And his wife be a widow.

10 And without fail let his sons go wandering about;

And they must do begging,

And they must look for food from their desolate places.

11 Let the usurer lay out traps for all that he has,

And let strangers make plunder of his product of toil.

12 May he come to have no one extending loving-kindness,

And may there prove to be no one showing favor to his fatherless boys.

13 Let his posterity be for cutting off.

In the following generation let their name be wiped out.

14 Let the error of his forefathers be remembered to Jehovah,

And the sin of his mother—may it not be wiped out.

15 Let them prove to be in front of Jehovah constantly;

And may he cut off the remembrance of them from the very earth;

16 For the reason that he did not remember to exercise loving-kindness,

But he kept pursuing the afflicted and poor man

And the one dejected at heart, to put him to death.

17 And he kept loving the malediction, so that it came upon him;

And he did not take delight in the blessing,

So that it became far away from him;

18 And he came to be clothed with malediction as his garment.

So it came like waters into the midst of him

And like oil into his bones.

19 May it prove to be for him like a garment with which he enwraps himself

And as a girdle that he keeps girded about himself constantly.

20 This is the wages from Jehovah of the one resisting me

And of those speaking evil against my soul.

21 But you are Jehovah the Sovereign Lord.

Deal with me for the sake of your name.

Because your loving-kindness is good, deliver me.

22 For I am afflicted and poor,

And my heart itself has been pierced within me.

23 Like a shadow when it declines, I am obliged to go away;

I have been shaken off like a locust.

24 My knees themselves have swayed from fasting,

And my very flesh has grown lean, without any oil.

25 And to them I myself have become something reproachable.

They see me—they begin wagging their head.

26 Help me, O Jehovah my God;

Save me according to your loving-kindness.

27 And may they know that this is your hand;

That you yourself, O Jehovah, have done it.

28 Let them, for their part, pronounce a malediction,

But may you, for your part, pronounce a blessing.

They have risen up, but let them be ashamed,

And let your own servant rejoice.

29 Let those resisting me be clothed with humiliation,

And let them enwrap themselves with their shame just as with a sleeveless coat.

30 I shall laud Jehovah very much with my mouth,

And in among many people I shall praise him.

31 For he will stand at the right hand of the poor,

To save him from those judging his soul.

Psalms

118 Give thanks to Jehovah, YOU people, for he is good;

For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.

2 Let Israel now say:

“For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.”

3 Let those of the house of Aaron now say:

“For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.”

4 Let those fearing Jehovah now say:

“For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.”

5 Out of the distressing circumstances I called upon Jah;

Jah answered and put me into a roomy place.

6 Jehovah is on my side; I shall not fear.

What can earthling man do to me?

7 Jehovah is on my side among those helping me,

So that I myself shall look upon those hating me.

8 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah

Than to trust in earthling man.

9 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah

Than to trust in nobles.

10 All the nations themselves surrounded me.

It was in the name of Jehovah that I kept holding them off.

11 They surrounded me, yes, they had me surrounded.

It was in the name of Jehovah that I kept holding them off.

12 They surrounded me like bees;

They were extinguished like a fire of thornbushes.

It was in the name of Jehovah that I kept holding them off.

13 You pushed me hard that I should fall,

But Jehovah himself helped me.

14 Jah is my shelter and my might,

And to me he becomes salvation.

15 The voice of a joyful cry and salvation

Is in the tents of the righteous ones.

The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating vital energy.

16 The right hand of Jehovah is exalting itself;

The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating vital energy.

17 I shall not die, but I shall keep living,

That I may declare the works of Jah.

18 Jah corrected me severely,

But he did not give me over to death itself.

19 Open to me the gates of righteousness, YOU people.

I shall go into them; I shall laud Jah.

20 This is the gate of Jehovah.

The righteous themselves will go into it.

21 I shall laud you, for you answered me

And you came to be my salvation.

22 The stone that the builders rejected

Has become the head of the corner.

23 This has come to be from Jehovah himself;

It is wonderful in our eyes.

24 This is the day that Jehovah has made;

We will be joyful and rejoice in it.

25 Ah, now, Jehovah, do save, please!

Ah, now, Jehovah, do grant success, please!

26 Blessed be the One coming in the name of Jehovah;

We have blessed YOU people out of the house of Jehovah.

27 Jehovah is the Divine One,

And he gives us light.

Bind the festival procession with boughs, O YOU people,

As far as the horns of the altar.

28 You are my Divine One, and I shall laud you;

My God—I shall exalt you.

29 Give thanks to Jehovah, YOU people, for he is good;

For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.

Psalms

א [ʼA′leph]

119 Happy are the ones faultless in their way,

The ones walking in the law of Jehovah.

2 Happy are those observing his reminders;

With all the heart they keep searching for him.

3 Really they have practiced no unrighteousness.

In his ways they have walked.

4 You yourself have commandingly given your orders

To be carefully kept.

5 O that my ways were firmly established

To keep your regulations!

6 In that case I should not be ashamed,

When I look to all your commandments.

7 I shall laud you in uprightness of heart,

When I learn your righteous judicial decisions.

8 Your regulations I continue to keep.

O do not leave me entirely.

ב [Behth]

9 How will a young man cleanse his path?

By keeping on guard according to your word.

10 With my whole heart I have searched for you.

Do not cause me to go astray from your commandments.

11 In my heart I have treasured up your saying,

In order that I may not sin against you.

12 Blessed you are, O Jehovah.

Teach me your regulations.

13 With my lips I have declared

All the judicial decisions of your mouth.

14 In the way of your reminders I have exulted,

Just as over all other valuable things.

15 With your orders I will concern myself,

And I will look to your paths.

16 For your statutes I shall show a fondness.

I shall not forget your word.

ג [Gi′mel]

17 Act appropriately toward your servant, that I may live

And that I may keep your word.

18 Uncover my eyes, that I may look

At the wonderful things out of your law.

19 I am but an alien resident in the land.

Do not conceal from me your commandments.

20 My soul is crushed with longing

For your judicial decisions all the time.

21 You have rebuked the cursed presumptuous ones,

Who are straying from your commandments.

22 Roll off me reproach and contempt,

For I have observed your own reminders.

23 Even princes have sat; against me they have spoken with one another.

As for your servant, he concerns himself with your regulations.

24 Also, your reminders are what I am fond of,

As men of my counsel.

ד [Da′leth]

25 My soul has been cleaving to the very dust.

Preserve me alive according to your word.

26 I have declared my own ways, that you may answer me.

Teach me your regulations.

27 Make me understand the way of your own orders,

That I may concern myself with your wonderful works.

28 My soul has been sleepless from grief.

Raise me up according to your word.

29 Remove from me even the false way,

And favor me with your own law.

30 The way of faithfulness I have chosen.

Your judicial decisions I have considered appropriate.

31 I have cleaved to your reminders.

O Jehovah, do not put me to shame.

32 I shall run the very way of your commandments,

Because you make my heart have the room.

ה [Heʼ]

33 Instruct me, O Jehovah, in the way of your regulations,

That I may observe it down to the last.

34 Make me understand, that I may observe your law

And that I may keep it with the whole heart.

35 Cause me to tread in the pathway of your commandments,

For in it I have taken delight.

36 Incline my heart to your reminders,

And not to profits.

37 Make my eyes pass on from seeing what is worthless;

Preserve me alive in your own way.

38 Carry out to your servant your saying

That tends to the fear of you.

39 Make my reproach pass away, of which I have been scared,

For your judicial decisions are good.

40 Look! I have longed for your orders.

In your righteousness preserve me alive.

ו [Waw]

41 And may your loving-kindnesses come to me, O Jehovah,

Your salvation according to your saying,

42 That I may answer the one reproaching me with a word,

For I have trusted in your word.

43 And do not take away from my mouth the word of truth entirely,

For I have waited for your own judicial decision.

44 And I will keep your law constantly,

To time indefinite, even forever.

45 And I will walk about in a roomy place,

For I have searched even for your orders.

46 I will also speak about your reminders in front of kings,

And I shall not be ashamed.

47 And I shall show a fondness for your commandments

That I have loved.

48 And I shall raise my palms to your commandments that I have loved,

And I will concern myself with your regulations.

ז [Za′yin]

49 Remember the word to your servant,

For which you have made me wait.

50 This is my comfort in my affliction,

For your own saying has preserved me alive.

51 The presumptuous ones themselves have derided me to the extreme.

From your law I have not deviated.

52 I have remembered your judicial decisions from time indefinite, O Jehovah,

And I find comfort for myself.

53 A raging heat itself has taken hold of me because of the wicked,

Who are leaving your law.

54 Melodies your regulations have become to me

In the house of my alien residences.

55 In the night I have remembered your name, O Jehovah,

That I may keep your law.

56 Even this has become mine,

Because your orders I have observed.

ח [Chehth]

57 Jehovah is my share;

I have promised to keep your words.

58 I have softened your face with all my heart.

Show me favor according to your saying.

59 I have considered my ways,

That I may turn back my feet to your reminders.

60 I hurried up, and I did not delay

To keep your commandments.

61 The very ropes of the wicked ones surrounded me.

Your law I did not forget.

62 At midnight I get up to give thanks to you

For your righteous judicial decisions.

63 A partner I am of all those who do fear you,

And of those keeping your orders.

64 Your loving-kindness, O Jehovah, has filled the earth.

Teach me your own regulations.

ט [Tehth]

65 You have dealt well indeed with your servant,

O Jehovah, according to your word.

66 Teach me goodness, sensibleness and knowledge themselves,

For in your commandments I have exercised faith.

67 Before I was under affliction I was sinning by mistake,

But now I have kept your very saying.

68 You are good and are doing good.

Teach me your regulations.

69 The presumptuous have smeared me with falsehood.

As for me, with all my heart I shall observe your orders.

70 Their heart has become unfeeling just like fat.

I, for my part, have been fond of your own law.

71 It is good for me that I have been afflicted,

In order that I may learn your regulations.

72 The law of your mouth is good for me,

More so than thousands of pieces of gold and silver.

י [Yohdh]

73 Your own hands have made me, and they proceeded to fix me solidly.

Make me understand, that I may learn your commandments.

74 Those fearing you are the ones that see me and rejoice,

For I have waited for your own word.

75 I well know, O Jehovah, that your judicial decisions are righteousness

And that with faithfulness you have afflicted me.

76 May your loving-kindness serve, please, to comfort me,

According to your saying to your servant.

77 Let your mercies come to me, that I may keep living;

For your law is what I am fond of.

78 Let the presumptuous ones be ashamed, for without cause they have misled me.

As for me, I concern myself with your orders.

79 Let those fearing you turn back to me,

Those also knowing your reminders.

80 Let my heart prove faultless in your regulations,

In order that I may not be ashamed.

כ [Kaph]

81 For your salvation my soul has pined away;

For your word I have waited.

82 My eyes have pined away for your saying,

While I say: “When will you comfort me?”

83 For I have become like a skin bottle in the smoke.

Your regulations I have not forgotten.

84 How many are the days of your servant?

When will you execute judgment against those persecuting me?

85 The presumptuous have excavated pitfalls to get me,

Those who are not in accord with your law.

86 All your commandments are faithfulness itself.

Without cause they have persecuted me. O help me.

87 In a little while they would have exterminated me in the earth;

But I myself did not leave your orders.

88 According to your loving-kindness preserve me alive,

That I may keep the reminder of your mouth.

ל [La′medh]

89 To time indefinite, O Jehovah,

Your word is stationed in the heavens.

90 Your faithfulness is for generation after generation.

You have solidly fixed the earth, that it may keep standing.

91 According to your judicial decisions they have stood till today,

For they are all your servants.

92 If your law had not been what I am fond of,

Then I should have perished in my affliction.

93 To time indefinite I shall not forget your orders,

Because by them you have preserved me alive.

94 I am yours. O save me,

Because I have searched for your own orders.

95 For me the wicked have waited, to destroy me.

To your reminders I keep showing myself attentive.

96 To all perfection I have seen an end.

Your commandment is very broad.

מ [Mem]

97 How I do love your law!

All day long it is my concern.

98 Wiser than my enemies your commandment makes me,

Because to time indefinite it is mine.

99 More insight than all my teachers I have come to have,

Because your reminders are a concern to me.

100 With more understanding than older men I behave,

Because I have observed your own orders.

101 From every bad path I have restrained my feet,

For the purpose that I may keep your word.

102 From your judicial decisions I have not turned aside,

For you yourself have instructed me.

103 How smooth to my palate your sayings have been,

More so than honey to my mouth!

104 Owing to your orders I behave with understanding.

That is why I have hated every false path.

נ [Nun]

105 Your word is a lamp to my foot,

And a light to my roadway.

106 I have made a sworn statement, and I will carry it out,

To keep your righteous judicial decisions.

107 I have been afflicted to a great extent.

O Jehovah, preserve me alive according to your word.

108 Please take pleasure in the voluntary offerings of my mouth, O Jehovah,

And teach me your own judicial decisions.

109 My soul is in my palm constantly;

But your law I have not forgotten.

110 The wicked have set a trap for me,

But from your orders I have not wandered.

111 I have taken your reminders as a possession to time indefinite,

For they are the exultation of my heart.

112 I have inclined my heart to do your regulations

To time indefinite, down to the last.

ס [Sa′mekh]

113 The halfhearted ones I have hated,

But your law I have loved.

114 You are my place of concealment and my shield.

For your word I have waited.

115 Get away from me, YOU evildoers,

That I may observe the commandments of my God.

116 Support me according to your saying, that I may keep living,

And do not put me to shame for my hope.

117 Sustain me, that I may be saved,

And I shall gaze upon your regulations constantly.

118 You have tossed away all those straying from your regulations;

For their trickiness is falsehood.

119 As scummy dross you have made all the wicked ones of the earth to cease.

Therefore I have loved your reminders.

120 From the dread of you my flesh has had a creepy feeling;

And because of your judicial decisions I have been afraid.

ע [ʽA′yin]

121 I have executed judgment and righteousness.

O do not abandon me to those defrauding me!

122 Act as a surety for your servant for what is good.

May the presumptuous ones not defraud me.

123 My very eyes have pined away for your salvation

And for your righteous saying.

124 Do with your servant according to your loving-kindness,

And teach me your own regulations.

125 I am your servant. Make me understand,

That I may know your reminders.

126 It is the time for Jehovah to act.

They have broken your law.

127 That is why I have loved your commandments

More than gold, even refined gold.

128 That is why I have considered all orders regarding all things to be right;

Every false path I have hated.

פ [Peʼ]

129 Your reminders are wonderful.

That is why my soul has observed them.

130 The very disclosure of your words gives light,

Making the inexperienced ones understand.

131 My mouth I have opened wide, that I may pant,

Because for your commandments I have longed.

132 Turn to me and show me favor,

According to your judicial decision toward those loving your name.

133 Fix my own steps solidly in your saying,

And may no kind of hurtful thing domineer over me.

134 Redeem me from any defrauder of mankind,

And I will keep your orders.

135 Make your own face shine upon your servant,

And teach me your regulations.

136 Streams of water have run down my eyes

Over the fact that they have not kept your law.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

137 You are righteous, O Jehovah,

And your judicial decisions are upright.

138 You have commanded your reminders in righteousness

And in exceeding faithfulness.

139 My ardor has made an end of me,

Because my adversaries have forgotten your words.

140 Your saying is very much refined,

And your own servant loves it.

141 I am insignificant and contemptible.

Your orders I have not forgotten.

142 Your righteousness is a righteousness to time indefinite,

And your law is truth.

143 Distress and difficulty themselves found me.

Your commandments I was fond of.

144 The righteousness of your reminders is to time indefinite.

Make me understand, that I may keep living.

ק [Qohph]

145 I have called with my whole heart. Answer me, O Jehovah.

Your regulations I will observe.

146 I have called upon you. O save me!

And I will keep your reminders.

147 I have been up early in the morning twilight, that I may cry for help.

For your words I have waited.

148 My eyes have been ahead of the night watches,

For me to concern myself with your saying.

149 O do hear my own voice according to your loving-kindness.

O Jehovah, according to your judicial decision preserve me alive.

150 Those in pursuit of loose conduct have come near;

They have got far away from your own law.

151 You are near, O Jehovah,

And all your commandments are truth.

152 Long ago I have known some of your reminders,

For to time indefinite you have founded them.

ר [Rehsh]

153 O see my affliction, and rescue me;

For I have not forgotten your own law.

154 O do conduct my legal case and recover me;

Preserve me alive in agreement with your saying.

155 Salvation is far away from the wicked ones,

For they have not searched for your own regulations.

156 Many are your mercies, O Jehovah.

According to your judicial decisions, O preserve me alive.

157 My persecutors and my adversaries are many.

From your reminders I have not deviated.

158 I have seen those who are treacherous in dealing,

And I do feel a loathing, because they have not kept your own saying.

159 O see that I have loved your own orders.

O Jehovah, according to your loving-kindness preserve me alive.

160 The substance of your word is truth,

And every righteous judicial decision of yours is to time indefinite.

ש [Sin] or [Shin]

161 Princes themselves have persecuted me for no cause,

But my heart has been in dread of your own words.

162 I am exulting over your saying

Just as one does when finding much spoil.

163 Falsehood I have hated, and I do keep detesting it.

Your law I have loved.

164 Seven times in the day I have praised you

Because of your righteous judicial decisions.

165 Abundant peace belongs to those loving your law,

And for them there is no stumbling block.

166 I have hoped for your salvation, O Jehovah,

And I have done your own commandments.

167 My soul has kept your reminders,

And I love them exceedingly.

168 I have kept your orders and your reminders,

For all my ways are in front of you.

ת [Taw]

169 May my entreating cry come near before you, O Jehovah.

According to your word, O make me understand.

170 May my request for favor enter in before you.

According to your saying, O deliver me.

171 May my lips bubble forth praise,

For you teach me your regulations.

172 May my tongue sing forth your saying,

For all your commandments are righteousness.

173 May your hand serve to help me,

Because your orders I have chosen.

174 I have longed for your salvation, O Jehovah,

And your law I am fond of.

175 May my soul keep living and praising you,

And may your own judicial decisions help me.

176 I have wandered like a lost sheep. O look for your servant,

For I have not forgotten your own commandments.

Psalms

135 Praise Jah, YOU people!

Praise the name of Jehovah,

Offer praise, O servants of Jehovah,

2 YOU who are standing in the house of Jehovah,

In the courtyards of the house of our God.

3 Praise Jah, for Jehovah is good.

Make melody to his name, for it is pleasant.

4 For Jah has chosen even Jacob for himself,

Israel for his special property.

5 For I myself well know that Jehovah is great,

And our Lord is more than all other gods.

6 Everything that Jehovah delighted to do he has done

In the heavens and in the earth, in the seas and all the watery deeps.

7 He is causing vapors to ascend from the extremity of the earth;

He has made even sluices for the rain;

He is bringing forth the wind from his storehouses,

8 He who struck down the firstborn ones of Egypt,

Both man and beast.

9 He sent signs and miracles into the midst of you, O Egypt,

Upon Phar′aoh and upon all his servants;

10 He who struck down many nations

And killed potent kings,

11 Even Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites

And Og the king of Ba′shan

And all the kingdoms of Ca′naan,

12 And who gave their land as an inheritance,

An inheritance to Israel his people.

13 O Jehovah, your name is to time indefinite.

O Jehovah, your memorial is to generation after generation.

14 For Jehovah will plead the cause of his people,

And he will feel regret even over his servants.

15 The idols of the nations are silver and gold,

The work of the hands of earthling man.

16 A mouth they have, but they can speak nothing;

Eyes they have, but they can see nothing;

17 Ears they have, but they can give ear to nothing.

Also there exists no spirit in their mouth.

18 Those making them will become just like them,

Everyone who is trusting in them.

19 O house of Israel, do YOU men bless Jehovah.

O house of Aaron, do YOU men bless Jehovah.

20 O house of Le′vi, do YOU men bless Jehovah.

YOU fearers of Jehovah, bless Jehovah.

21 Blessed out of Zion be Jehovah,

Who is residing in Jerusalem.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Psalms

For the director. Of David. A melody.

139 O Jehovah, you have searched through me, and you know me.

2 You yourself have come to know my sitting down and my rising up.

You have considered my thought from far off.

3 My journeying and my lying outstretched you have measured off,

And you have become familiar even with all my ways.

4 For there is not a word on my tongue,

But, look! O Jehovah, you already know it all.

5 Behind and before, you have besieged me;

And you place your hand upon me.

6 Such knowledge is too wonderful for me.

It is so high up that I cannot attain to it.

7 Where can I go from your spirit,

And where can I run away from your face?

8 If I should ascend to heaven, there you would be;

And if I should spread out my couch in She′ol, look! you would be there.

9 Were I to take the wings of the dawn,

That I might reside in the most remote sea,

10 There, also, your own hand would lead me

And your right hand would lay hold of me.

11 And were I to say: “Surely darkness itself will hastily seize me!”

Then night would be light about me.

12 Even the darkness itself would not prove too dark for you,

But night itself would shine just as the day does;

The darkness might just as well be the light.

13 For you yourself produced my kidneys;

You kept me screened off in the belly of my mother.

14 I shall laud you because in a fear-inspiring way I am wonderfully made.

Your works are wonderful,

As my soul is very well aware.

15 My bones were not hidden from you

When I was made in secret,

When I was woven in the lowest parts of the earth.

16 Your eyes saw even the embryo of me,

And in your book all its parts were down in writing,

As regards the days when they were formed

And there was not yet one among them.

17 So, to me how precious your thoughts are!

O God, how much does the grand sum of them amount to!

18 Were I to try to count them, they are more than even the grains of sand.

I have awaked, and yet I am still with you.

19 O that you, O God, would slay the wicked one!

Then even the bloodguilty men will certainly depart from me,

20 Who say things about you according to their idea;

They have taken up your name in a worthless way—your adversaries.

21 Do I not hate those who are intensely hating you, O Jehovah,

And do I not feel a loathing for those revolting against you?

22 With a complete hatred I do hate them.

They have become to me real enemies.

23 Search through me, O God, and know my heart.

Examine me, and know my disquieting thoughts,

24 And see whether there is in me any painful way,

And lead me in the way of time indefinite.

Psalms

A melody of David.

141 O Jehovah, I have called upon you.

Do make haste to me.

Do give ear to my voice when I call to you.

2 May my prayer be prepared as incense before you,

The raising up of my palms as the evening grain offering.

3 Do set a guard, O Jehovah, for my mouth;

Do set a watch over the door of my lips.

4 Do not incline my heart to anything bad,

So as to carry on notorious deeds in wickedness

With men who are practicing what is hurtful,

That I may not feed myself on their dainties.

5 Should the righteous one strike me, it would be a loving-kindness;

And should he reprove me, it would be oil upon the head,

Which my head would not want to refuse.

For still there would be even my prayer during their calamities.

6 Their judges have been thrown down by the sides of the crag,

But they have heard my sayings, that they are pleasant.

7 As when one is doing cleaving and splitting on the earth,

Our bones have been scattered at the mouth of She′ol.

8 However, my eyes are to you, O Jehovah the Sovereign Lord.

In you I have taken refuge.

Do not pour out my soul.

9 Keep me from the clutches of the trap that they have laid for me

And from the snares of those practicing what is hurtful.

10 The wicked will fall into their own nets all together,

While I, for my part, pass by.

Psalms

A melody of David.

143 O Jehovah, hear my prayer;

Do give ear to my entreaty.

In your faithfulness answer me in your righteousness.

2 And do not enter into judgment with your servant;

For before you no one alive can be righteous.

3 For the enemy has pursued my soul;

He has crushed my life to the very earth.

He has caused me to dwell in dark places like those dead for time indefinite.

4 And my spirit faints away within me;

In the midst of me my heart shows itself numbed.

5 I have remembered days of long ago;

I have meditated on all your activity;

I willingly kept myself concerned with the work of your own hands.

6 I have spread out my hands to you;

My soul is like an exhausted land to you. Se′lah.

7 O hurry, answer me, O Jehovah.

My spirit has come to an end.

Do not conceal your face from me,

Or else I must become comparable with those going down into the pit.

8 In the morning cause me to hear your loving-kindness,

For in you I have put my trust.

Make known to me the way in which I should walk,

For to you I have lifted up my soul.

9 Deliver me from my enemies, O Jehovah.

I have taken cover even with you.

10 Teach me to do your will,

For you are my God.

Your spirit is good;

May it lead me in the land of uprightness.

11 For the sake of your name, O Jehovah, may you preserve me alive.

In your righteousness may you bring forth my soul out of distress.

12 And in your loving-kindness may you silence my enemies;

And you must destroy all those showing hostility to my soul,

For I am your servant.

Psalms

Of David.

144 Blessed be Jehovah my Rock,

Who is teaching my hands for fighting,

My fingers for warfare;

2 My loving-kindness and my stronghold,

My secure height and my Provider of escape for me,

My shield and the One in whom I have taken refuge,

The One subduing peoples under me.

3 O Jehovah, what is man that you should notice him,

The son of mortal man that you should take account of him?

4 Man himself bears resemblance to a mere exhalation;

His days are like a passing shadow.

5 O Jehovah, bend down your heavens that you may descend;

Touch the mountains that they may smoke.

6 Lighten with lightning that you may scatter them;

Send out your arrows that you may throw them into confusion.

7 Thrust your hands out from the height;

Set me free and deliver me from the many waters,

From the hand of the foreigners,

8 Whose mouth has spoken what is untrue

And whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood.

9 O God, a new song I will sing to you.

On an instrument of ten strings I will make melody to you,

10 The One giving salvation to kings,

The One setting David his servant free from the injurious sword.

11 Set me free and deliver me from the hand of the foreigners,

Whose mouth has spoken what is untrue

And whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood,

12 Who say: “Our sons are like little plants grown up in their youth,

Our daughters like corners carved in palace style,

13 Our garners full, furnishing products of one sort after another,

Our flocks multiplying by thousands, ten thousand to one, in our streets,

14 Our cattle loaded down, without any rupture and with no abortion,

And with no outcry in our public squares.

15 Happy is the people for whom it is just like that!”

Happy is the people whose God is Jehovah!

Psalms

147 Praise Jah, YOU people,

For it is good to make melody to our God;

For it is pleasant—praise is fitting.

2 Jehovah is building Jerusalem;

The dispersed ones of Israel he brings together.

3 He is healing the brokenhearted ones,

And is binding up their painful spots.

4 He is counting the number of the stars;

All of them he calls by their names.

5 Our Lord is great and is abundant in power;

His understanding is beyond recounting.

6 Jehovah is relieving the meek ones;

He is abasing the wicked ones to the earth.

7 Respond to Jehovah with thanksgiving, YOU people;

Make melody to our God on the harp,

8 The One who is covering the heavens with clouds,

The One preparing rain for the earth,

The One making the mountains to sprout green grass.

9 To the beasts he is giving their food,

To the young ravens that keep calling.

10 Not in the mightiness of the horse does he take delight,

Nor in the legs of the man does he find pleasure.

11 Jehovah is finding pleasure in those fearing him,

In those waiting for his loving-kindness.

12 Commend Jehovah, O Jerusalem.

Praise your God, O Zion.

13 For he has made the bars of your gates strong;

He has blessed your sons in the midst of you.

14 He is putting peace in your territory;

With the fat of the wheat he keeps satisfying you.

15 He is sending his saying to the earth;

With speed his word runs.

16 He is giving snow like wool;

Hoarfrost he scatters just like ashes.

17 He is throwing his ice like morsels.

Before his cold who can stand?

18 He sends forth his word and melts them.

He causes his wind to blow;

The waters trickle.

19 He is telling his word to Jacob,

His regulations and his judicial decisions to Israel.

20 He has not done that way to any other nation;

And as for his judicial decisions, they have not known them.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Proverbs

1 The proverbs of Sol′o·mon the son of David, the king of Israel, 2 for one to know wisdom and discipline, to discern the sayings of understanding, 3 to receive the discipline that gives insight, righteousness and judgment and uprightness, 4 to give to the inexperienced ones shrewdness, to a young man knowledge and thinking ability.

5 A wise person will listen and take in more instruction, and a man of understanding is the one who acquires skillful direction, 6 to understand a proverb and a puzzling saying, the words of wise persons and their riddles.

7 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Wisdom and discipline are what mere fools have despised.

8 Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, and do not forsake the law of your mother. 9 For they are a wreath of attractiveness to your head and a fine necklace to your throat.

10 My son, if sinners try to seduce you, do not consent. 11 If they keep saying: “Do go with us. Do let us lie in ambush for blood. Do let us lie in concealment for the innocent men without any cause. 12 Let us swallow them down alive just like She′ol, even whole, like those going down into a pit. 13 Let us find all sorts of precious valuables. Let us fill our houses with spoil. 14 Your lot you ought to cast in among us. Let there come to be just one bag belonging to all of us”— 15 my son, do not go in the way with them. Hold back your foot from their roadway. 16 For their feet are those that run to sheer badness, and they keep hastening to shed blood. 17 For it is for nothing that the net is spread before the eyes of anything owning wings. 18 Consequently they themselves lie in ambush for the very blood of these; they lie in concealment for their souls. 19 Thus are the paths of everyone making unjust profit. It takes away the very soul of its owners.

20 True wisdom itself keeps crying aloud in the very street. In the public squares it keeps giving forth its voice. 21 At the upper end of the noisy streets it calls out. At the entrances of the gates into the city it says its own sayings:

22 “How long will YOU inexperienced ones keep loving inexperience, and how long must YOU ridiculers desire for yourselves outright ridicule, and how long will YOU stupid ones keep hating knowledge? 23 Turn back at my reproof. Then to YOU I will cause my spirit to bubble forth; I will make my words known to YOU. 24 Because I have called out but YOU keep refusing, I have stretched out my hand but there is no one paying attention, 25 and YOU keep neglecting all my counsel, and my reproof YOU have not accepted, 26 I also, for my part, shall laugh at YOUR own disaster, I shall mock when what YOU dread comes, 27 when what YOU dread comes just like a storm, and YOUR own disaster gets here just like a storm wind, when distress and hard times come upon YOU. 28 At that time they will keep calling me, but I shall not answer; they will keep looking for me, but they will not find me, 29 for the reason that they hated knowledge, and the fear of Jehovah they did not choose. 30 They did not consent to my counsel; they disrespected all my reproof. 31 So they will eat from the fruitage of their way, and they will be glutted with their own counsels. 32 For the renegading of the inexperienced ones is what will kill them, and the easygoingness of the stupid is what will destroy them. 33 As for the one listening to me, he will reside in security and be undisturbed from dread of calamity.”

Proverbs

4 Listen, O sons, to the discipline of a father and pay attention, so as to know understanding. 2 For good instruction is what I certainly shall give to YOU. My law DO not leave. 3 For I proved to be a real son to my father, tender and the only one before my mother. 4 And he would instruct me and say to me: “May your heart keep fast hold of my words. Keep my commandments and continue living. 5 Acquire wisdom, acquire understanding. Do not forget, and do not turn aside from the sayings of my mouth. 6 Do not leave it, and it will keep you. Love it, and it will safeguard you. 7 Wisdom is the prime thing. Acquire wisdom; and with all that you acquire, acquire understanding. 8 Highly esteem it, and it will exalt you. It will glorify you because you embrace it. 9 To your head it will give a wreath of charm; a crown of beauty it will bestow upon you.”

10 Hear, my son, and accept my sayings. Then for you the years of life will become many. 11 I will instruct you even in the way of wisdom; I will cause you to tread in the tracks of uprightness. 12 When you walk, your pace will not be cramped; and if you run, you will not stumble. 13 Take hold on discipline; do not let go. Safeguard it, for it itself is your life.

14 Into the path of the wicked ones do not enter, and do not walk straight on into the way of the bad ones. 15 Shun it, do not pass along by it; turn aside from it, and pass along. 16 For they do not sleep unless they do badness, and their sleep has been snatched away unless they cause someone to stumble. 17 For they have fed themselves with the bread of wickedness, and the wine of acts of violence is what they drink. 18 But the path of the righteous ones is like the bright light that is getting lighter and lighter until the day is firmly established. 19 The way of the wicked ones is like the gloom; they have not known at what they keep stumbling.

20 My son, to my words do pay attention. To my sayings incline your ear. 21 May they not get away from your eyes. Keep them in the midst of your heart. 22 For they are life to those finding them and health to all their flesh. 23 More than all else that is to be guarded, safeguard your heart, for out of it are the sources of life. 24 Remove from yourself the crookedness of speech; and the deviousness of lips put far away from yourself. 25 As for your eyes, straight ahead they should look, yes, your own beaming eyes should gaze straight in front of you. 26 Smooth out the course of your foot, and may all your own ways be firmly established. 27 Do not incline to the right hand or to the left. Remove your foot from what is bad.

Proverbs

5 My son, to my wisdom O do pay attention. To my discernment incline your ears, 2 so as to guard thinking abilities; and may your own lips safeguard knowledge itself.

3 For as a honeycomb the lips of a strange woman keep dripping, and her palate is smoother than oil. 4 But the aftereffect from her is as bitter as wormwood; it is as sharp as a two-edged sword. 5 Her feet are descending to death. Her very steps take hold on She′ol itself. 6 The path of life she does not contemplate. Her tracks have wandered she does not know where. 7 So now, O sons, listen to me and do not turn away from the sayings of my mouth. 8 Keep your way far off from alongside her, and do not get near to the entrance of her house, 9 that you may not give to others your dignity, nor your years to what is cruel; 10 that strangers may not satisfy themselves with your power, nor the things you got by pain be in the house of a foreigner, 11 nor you have to groan in your future when your flesh and your organism come to an end. 12 And you will have to say: “How I have hated discipline and my heart has disrespected even reproof! 13 And I have not listened to the voice of my instructors, and to my teachers I have not inclined my ear. 14 Easily I have come to be in every sort of badness in the midst of the congregation and of the assembly.”

15 Drink water out of your own cistern, and tricklings out of the midst of your own well. 16 Should your springs be scattered out of doors, your streams of water in the public squares themselves? 17 Let them prove to be for you alone, and not for strangers with you. 18 Let your water source prove to be blessed, and rejoice with the wife of your youth, 19 a lovable hind and a charming mountain goat. Let her own breasts intoxicate you at all times. With her love may you be in an ecstasy constantly. 20 So why should you, my son, be in an ecstasy with a strange woman or embrace the bosom of a foreign woman? 21 For the ways of man are in front of the eyes of Jehovah, and he is contemplating all his tracks. 22 His own errors will catch the wicked one, and in the ropes of his own sin he will be taken hold of. 23 He will be the one to die because there is no discipline, and because in the abundance of his foolishness he goes astray.

Proverbs

6 My son, if you have gone surety for your fellowman, if you have given your handshake even to the stranger, 2 if you have been ensnared by the sayings of your mouth, if you have been caught by the sayings of your mouth, 3 take this action then, my son, and deliver yourself, for you have come into the palm of your fellowman: Go humble yourself and storm your fellowman with importunities. 4 Do not give any sleep to your eyes, nor any slumber to your beaming eyes. 5 Deliver yourself like a gazelle from the hand and like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.

6 Go to the ant, you lazy one; see its ways and become wise. 7 Although it has no commander, officer or ruler, 8 it prepares its food even in the summer; it has gathered its food supplies even in the harvest. 9 How long, you lazy one, will you keep lying down? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little more sleep, a little more slumbering, a little more folding of the hands in lying down, 11 and your poverty will certainly come just like some rover, and your want like an armed man.

12 A good-for-nothing man, a man of hurtfulness, is walking with crookedness of speech, 13 winking with his eye, making signs with his foot, making indications with his fingers. 14 Perverseness is in his heart. He is fabricating something bad all the time. He keeps sending out merely contentions. 15 That is why suddenly there will come his disaster; in an instant he will be broken, and there will be no healing.

16 There are six things that Jehovah does hate; yes, seven are things detestable to his soul: 17 lofty eyes, a false tongue, and hands that are shedding innocent blood, 18 a heart fabricating hurtful schemes, feet that are in a hurry to run to badness, 19 a false witness that launches forth lies, and anyone sending forth contentions among brothers.

20 Observe, O my son, the commandment of your father, and do not forsake the law of your mother. 21 Tie them upon your heart constantly; bind them upon your throat. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; when you lie down, it will stand guard over you; and when you have waked up, it itself will make you its concern. 23 For the commandment is a lamp, and a light the law is, and the reproofs of discipline are the way of life, 24 to guard you against the bad woman, against the smoothness of the tongue of the foreign woman. 25 Do not desire her prettiness in your heart, and may she not take you with her lustrous eyes, 26 because in behalf of a woman prostitute one comes down to a round loaf of bread; but as regards another man’s wife, she hunts even for a precious soul. 27 Can a man rake together fire into his bosom and yet his very garments not be burned? 28 Or can a man walk upon the coals and his feet themselves not be scorched? 29 Likewise with anyone having relations with the wife of his fellowman, no one touching her will remain unpunishable. 30 People do not despise a thief just because he commits thievery to fill his soul when he is hungry. 31 But, when found, he will make it good with seven times as much; all the valuables of his house he will give. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is in want of heart; he that does it is bringing his own soul to ruin. 33 A plague and dishonor he will find, and his reproach itself will not be wiped out. 34 For the rage of an able-bodied man is jealousy, and he will not show compassion in the day of vengeance. 35 He will have no consideration for any sort of ransom, neither will he show willingness, no matter how large you make the present.

Proverbs

8 Does not wisdom keep calling out, and discernment keep giving forth its voice? 2 On top of the heights, by the way, at the crossing of the roadways it has stationed itself. 3 At the side of the gates, at the mouth of the town, at the going in of the entrances it keeps crying loudly:

4 “To YOU, O men, I am calling, and my voice is to the sons of men. 5 O inexperienced ones, understand shrewdness; and YOU stupid ones, understand heart. 6 Listen, for it is about the foremost things that I speak, and the opening of my lips is about uprightness. 7 For my palate in low tones utters truth itself; and wickedness is something detestable to my lips. 8 All the sayings of my mouth are in righteousness. Among them there is nothing twisted or crooked. 9 All of them are straight to the discerning one, and upright to the ones finding knowledge. 10 TAKE my discipline and not silver, and knowledge rather than choice gold. 11 For wisdom is better than corals, and all other delights themselves cannot be made equal to it.

12 “I, wisdom, I have resided with shrewdness and I find even the knowledge of thinking abilities. 13 The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. Self-exaltation and pride and the bad way and the perverse mouth I have hated. 14 I have counsel and practical wisdom. I—understanding; I have mightiness. 15 By me kings themselves keep reigning, and high officials themselves keep decreeing righteousness. 16 By me princes themselves keep ruling as princes, and nobles are all judging in righteousness. 17 Those loving me I myself love, and those looking for me are the ones that find me. 18 Riches and glory are with me, hereditary values and righteousness. 19 My fruitage is better than gold, even than refined gold, and my produce than choice silver. 20 In the path of righteousness I walk, in the middle of the roadways of judgment, 21 to cause those loving me to take possession of substance; and their storehouses I keep filled.

22 “Jehovah himself produced me as the beginning of his way, the earliest of his achievements of long ago. 23 From time indefinite I was installed, from the start, from times earlier than the earth. 24 When there were no watery deeps I was brought forth as with labor pains, when there were no springs heavily charged with water. 25 Before the mountains themselves had been settled down, ahead of the hills, I was brought forth as with labor pains, 26 when as yet he had not made the earth and the open spaces and the first part of the dust masses of the productive land. 27 When he prepared the heavens I was there; when he decreed a circle upon the face of the watery deep, 28 when he made firm the cloud masses above, when he caused the fountains of the watery deep to be strong, 29 when he set for the sea his decree that the waters themselves should not pass beyond his order, when he decreed the foundations of the earth, 30 then I came to be beside him as a master worker, and I came to be the one he was specially fond of day by day, I being glad before him all the time, 31 being glad at the productive land of his earth, and the things I was fond of were with the sons of men.

32 “And now, O sons, listen to me; yes, happy are the ones that keep my very ways. 33 Listen to discipline and become wise, and do not show any neglect. 34 Happy is the man that is listening to me by keeping awake at my doors day by day, by watching at the posts of my entrances. 35 For the one finding me will certainly find life, and gets goodwill from Jehovah. 36 But the one missing me is doing violence to his soul; all those intensely hating me are the ones that do love death.”

Proverbs

9 True wisdom has built its house; it has hewn out its seven pillars. 2 It has organized its meat slaughtering; it has mixed its wine; more than that, it has set in order its table. 3 It has sent forth its lady attendants, that it may call out on top of the heights of the town: 4 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him turn aside here.” Whoever is in want of heart—she has said to him: 5 “Come, feed yourselves with my bread and share in drinking the wine that I have mixed. 6 Leave the inexperienced ones and keep living, and walk straight in the way of understanding.”

7 He that is correcting the ridiculer is taking to himself dishonor, and he that is giving a reproof to someone wicked—a defect in him. 8 Do not reprove a ridiculer, that he may not hate you. Give a reproof to a wise person and he will love you. 9 Give to a wise person and he will become still wiser. Impart knowledge to someone righteous and he will increase in learning.

10 The fear of Jehovah is the start of wisdom, and the knowledge of the Most Holy One is what understanding is. 11 For by me your days will become many, and to you years of life will be added. 12 If you have become wise, you have become wise in your own behalf; and if you have ridiculed, you will bear it, just you alone.

13 A woman of stupidity is boisterous. She is simplemindedness itself and has come to know nothing whatever. 14 And she has seated herself at the entrance of her house, upon a seat, in the high places of the town, 15 to call out to those passing along the way, those who are going straight ahead on their paths: 16 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him turn aside here.” And whoever is in want of heart—she has also said to him: 17 “Stolen waters themselves are sweet, and bread eaten in secrecy—it is pleasant.” 18 But he has not come to know that those impotent in death are there, that those called in by her are in the low places of She′ol.

Proverbs

10 Proverbs of Sol′o·mon.

A wise son is the one that makes a father rejoice, and a stupid son is the grief of his mother. 2 The treasures of the wicked one will be of no benefit, but righteousness is what will deliver from death. 3 Jehovah will not cause the soul of the righteous one to go hungry, but the craving of the wicked ones he will push away.

4 The one working with a slack hand will be of little means, but the hand of the diligent one is what will make one rich.

5 The son acting with insight is gathering during the summertime; the son acting shamefully is fast asleep during the harvest.

6 Blessings are for the head of the righteous one, but as regards the mouth of the wicked ones, it covers up violence. 7 The remembrance of the righteous one is due for a blessing, but the very name of the wicked ones will rot.

8 The one wise in heart will accept commandments, but the one foolish with his lips will be trodden down.

9 He that is walking in integrity will walk in security, but he that is making his ways crooked will make himself known.

10 The one winking his eye will give pain, and the one foolish with his lips will be trodden down. 11 The mouth of the righteous one is a source of life; but as regards the mouth of the wicked ones, it covers up violence.

12 Hatred is what stirs up contentions, but love covers over even all transgressions.

13 On the lips of the understanding person wisdom is found, but the rod is for the back of one in want of heart.

14 The wise are the ones that treasure up knowledge, but the mouth of the foolish one is near to ruin itself.

15 The valuable things of a rich man are his strong town. The ruin of the lowly ones is their poverty.

16 The activity of the righteous one results in life; the produce of the wicked one results in sin.

17 He that is holding to discipline is a path to life, but he that is leaving reproof is causing to wander.

18 Where there is one covering over hatred there are lips of falsehood, and the one bringing forth a bad report is stupid.

19 In the abundance of words there does not fail to be transgression, but the one keeping his lips in check is acting discreetly.

20 The tongue of the righteous one is choice silver; the heart of the wicked one is worth little.

21 The very lips of the righteous one keep pasturing many, but for want of heart the foolish themselves keep dying.

22 The blessing of Jehovah—that is what makes rich, and he adds no pain with it.

23 To the stupid one the carrying on of loose conduct is like sport, but wisdom is for the man of discernment.

24 The thing frightful to the wicked one—that is what will come to him; but the desire of the righteous ones will be granted. 25 As when the storm wind passes over, so the wicked one is no more; but the righteous one is a foundation to time indefinite.

26 As vinegar to the teeth and as smoke to the eyes, so the lazy man is to those sending him forth.

27 The very fear of Jehovah will add days, but the years themselves of the wicked ones will be cut short.

28 The expectation of the righteous ones is a rejoicing, but the very hope of the wicked ones will perish.

29 The way of Jehovah is a stronghold for the blameless one, but ruin is for the practicers of what is hurtful.

30 As for the righteous one, to time indefinite he will not be caused to stagger; but as for the wicked ones, they will not keep residing on the earth.

31 The mouth of the righteous one—it bears the fruit of wisdom, but the tongue of perverseness will be cut off.

32 The lips of the righteous one—they come to know goodwill, but the mouth of the wicked ones is perverseness.

Proverbs

12 A lover of discipline is a lover of knowledge, but a hater of reproof is unreasoning.

2 One that is good gets approval from Jehovah, but the man of wicked ideas he pronounces wicked.

3 No man will be firmly established by wickedness; but as for the root-foundation of the righteous ones, it will not be caused to stagger.

4 A capable wife is a crown to her owner, but as rottenness in his bones is she that acts shamefully.

5 The thoughts of the righteous ones are judgment; the steering by the wicked ones is deception.

6 The words of the wicked ones are a lying in wait for blood, but the mouth of the upright ones is what will deliver them.

7 There is an overthrowing of the wicked ones and they are no more, but the very house of the righteous ones will keep standing.

8 For his mouth of discretion a man will be praised, but one who is twisted at heart will come to be for contempt.

9 Better is the one lightly esteemed but having a servant than the one glorifying himself but in want of bread.

10 The righteous one is caring for the soul of his domestic animal, but the mercies of the wicked ones are cruel.

11 The one cultivating his ground will himself be satisfied with bread, but the one pursuing valueless things is in want of heart.

12 The wicked one has desired the netted prey of bad men; but as for the root of the righteous ones, it yields.

13 By the transgression of the lips the bad person is ensnared, but the righteous one gets out of distress.

14 From the fruitage of a man’s mouth he is satisfied with good, and the very doing of a man’s hands will come back to him.

15 The way of the foolish one is right in his own eyes, but the one listening to counsel is wise.

16 It is a foolish person that makes known his vexation in the same day, but the shrewd one is covering over a dishonor.

17 He that launches forth faithfulness will tell what is righteous, but a false witness, deception.

18 There exists the one speaking thoughtlessly as with the stabs of a sword, but the tongue of the wise ones is a healing.

19 It is the lip of truth that will be firmly established forever, but the tongue of falsehood will be only as long as a moment.

20 Deception is in the heart of those fabricating mischief, but those counseling peace have rejoicing.

21 Nothing hurtful will befall the righteous one, but the wicked are the ones that will certainly be filled with calamity.

22 False lips are something detestable to Jehovah, but those acting in faithfulness are a pleasure to him.

23 A shrewd man is covering knowledge, but the heart of the stupid ones is one that calls out foolishness.

24 The hand of the diligent ones is the one that will rule, but the slack hand will come to be for forced labor.

25 Anxious care in the heart of a man is what will cause it to bow down, but the good word is what makes it rejoice.

26 The righteous one spies out his own pasturage, but the very way of wicked ones causes them to wander about.

27 Slackness will not start up one’s game animals, but the diligent one is a man’s precious wealth.

28 In the path of righteousness there is life, and the journey in its pathway means no death.

Proverbs

14 The truly wise woman has built up her house, but the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.

2 The one walking in his uprightness is fearing Jehovah, but the one crooked in his ways is despising Him.

3 The rod of haughtiness is in the mouth of the foolish one, but the very lips of the wise ones will guard them.

4 Where there are no cattle the manger is clean, but the crop is abundant because of the power of a bull.

5 A faithful witness is one that will not lie, but a false witness launches forth mere lies.

6 The ridiculer has sought to find wisdom, and there is none; but to the understanding one knowledge is an easy thing.

7 Go away from in front of the stupid man, for you will certainly not take note of the lips of knowledge.

8 The wisdom of the shrewd is to understand his way, but the foolishness of stupid ones is deception.

9 Foolish are those who make a derision of guilt, but among the upright ones there is agreement.

10 The heart is aware of the bitterness of one’s soul, and with its rejoicing no stranger will intermeddle.

11 The house of wicked people will be annihilated, but the tent of the upright ones will flourish.

12 There exists a way that is upright before a man, but the ways of death are the end of it afterward.

13 Even in laughter the heart may be in pain; and grief is what rejoicing ends up in.

14 The one faithless at heart will be satisfied with the results of his own ways, but the good man with the results of his dealings.

15 Anyone inexperienced puts faith in every word, but the shrewd one considers his steps.

16 The wise one fears and is turning away from badness, but the stupid is becoming furious and self-confident.

17 He that is quick to anger will commit foolishness, but the man of thinking abilities is hated.

18 The inexperienced ones will certainly take possession of foolishness, but the shrewd ones will bear knowledge as a headdress.

19 Bad people will have to bow down before the good ones, and the wicked people at the gates of the righteous one.

20 Even to his fellowman one who is of little means is an object of hatred, but many are the friends of the rich person.

21 The one despising his own fellowman is sinning, but happy is he who is showing favor to the afflicted ones.

22 Will not those devising mischief go wandering about? But there are loving-kindness and trueness as regards those devising good.

23 By every kind of toil there comes to be an advantage, but merely the word of the lips tends to want.

24 The crown of the wise is their riches; the foolishness of the stupid ones is foolishness.

25 A true witness is delivering souls, but a deceitful one launches forth mere lies.

26 In the fear of Jehovah there is strong confidence, and for his sons there will come to be a refuge.

27 The fear of Jehovah is a well of life, to turn away from the snares of death.

28 In the multitude of people there is an adornment of a king, but in the lack of population is the ruin of a high official.

29 He that is slow to anger is abundant in discernment, but one that is impatient is exalting foolishness.

30 A calm heart is the life of the fleshly organism, but jealousy is rottenness to the bones.

31 He that is defrauding the lowly one has reproached his Maker, but the one showing favor to the poor one is glorifying Him.

32 Because of his badness the wicked will be pushed down, but the righteous will be finding refuge in his integrity.

33 In the heart of the understanding one there rests wisdom, and in the midst of stupid ones it becomes known.

34 Righteousness is what exalts a nation, but sin is something disgraceful to national groups.

35 The pleasure of a king is in the servant who is acting with insight, but his fury comes to be toward one acting shamefully.

Proverbs

15 An answer, when mild, turns away rage, but a word causing pain makes anger to come up.

2 The tongue of wise ones does good with knowledge, but the mouth of the stupid ones bubbles forth with foolishness.

3 The eyes of Jehovah are in every place, keeping watch upon the bad ones and the good ones.

4 The calmness of the tongue is a tree of life, but distortion in it means a breaking down in the spirit.

5 Anyone foolish disrespects the discipline of his father, but anyone regarding reproof is shrewd.

6 In the house of the righteous one there is an abundant store, but in the produce of the wicked one there is a becoming ostracized.

7 The lips of the wise ones keep scattering knowledge about, but the heart of the stupid ones is not like that.

8 The sacrifice of the wicked ones is something detestable to Jehovah, but the prayer of the upright ones is a pleasure to him.

9 The way of the wicked one is something detestable to Jehovah, but the one pursuing righteousness he loves.

10 Discipline is bad to the one leaving the path; anyone hating reproof will die.

11 She′ol and the place of destruction are in front of Jehovah. How much more so the hearts of the sons of mankind!

12 The ridiculer does not love the one reproving him. To the wise ones he will not go.

13 A joyful heart has a good effect on the countenance, but because of the pain of the heart there is a stricken spirit.

14 The understanding heart is one that searches for knowledge, but the mouth of stupid people is one that aspires to foolishness.

15 All the days of the afflicted one are bad; but the one that is good at heart has a feast constantly.

16 Better is a little in the fear of Jehovah than an abundant supply and confusion along with it.

17 Better is a dish of vegetables where there is love than a manger-fed bull and hatred along with it.

18 An enraged man stirs up contention, but one that is slow to anger quiets down quarreling.

19 The way of the lazy one is like a brier hedge, but the path of the upright ones is a way cast up.

20 A wise son is the one that makes a father rejoice, but a stupid man is despising his mother.

21 Foolishness is a rejoicing to one who is in want of heart, but the man of discernment is one who goes straight ahead.

22 There is a frustrating of plans where there is no confidential talk, but in the multitude of counselors there is accomplishment.

23 A man has rejoicing in the answer of his mouth, and a word at its right time is O how good!

24 The path of life is upward to one acting with insight, in order to turn away from She′ol down below.

25 The house of the self-exalted ones Jehovah will tear down, but he will fix the boundary of the widow.

26 The schemes of the bad one are something detestable to Jehovah, but pleasant sayings are clean.

27 The one making unjust profit is bringing ostracism upon his own house, but the hater of gifts is the one that will keep living.

28 The heart of the righteous one meditates so as to answer, but the mouth of the wicked ones bubbles forth with bad things.

29 Jehovah is far away from the wicked ones, but the prayer of the righteous ones he hears.

30 The brightness of the eyes makes the heart rejoice; a report that is good makes the bones fat.

31 The ear that is listening to the reproof of life lodges right in among wise people.

32 Anyone shunning discipline is rejecting his own soul, but the one listening to reproof is acquiring heart.

33 The fear of Jehovah is a discipline toward wisdom, and before glory there is humility.

Proverbs

16 To earthling man belong the arrangings of the heart, but from Jehovah is the answer of the tongue.

2 All the ways of a man are pure in his own eyes, but Jehovah is making an estimate of spirits.

3 Roll your works upon Jehovah himself and your plans will be firmly established.

4 Everything Jehovah has made for his purpose, yes, even the wicked one for the evil day.

5 Everyone that is proud in heart is something detestable to Jehovah. Hand may join to hand, yet one will not be free from punishment.

6 By loving-kindness and trueness error is atoned for, and in the fear of Jehovah one turns away from bad.

7 When Jehovah takes pleasure in the ways of a man he causes even his enemies themselves to be at peace with him.

8 Better is a little with righteousness than an abundance of products without justice.

9 The heart of earthling man may think out his way, but Jehovah himself does the directing of his steps.

10 Inspired decision should be upon the lips of a king; in judgment his mouth should not prove unfaithful.

11 The just indicator and scales belong to Jehovah; all the stone weights of the bag are his work.

12 The doing of wickedness is something detestable to kings, for by righteousness is the throne firmly established.

13 The lips of righteousness are a pleasure to a grand king; and the speaker of upright things he loves.

14 The rage of a king means messengers of death, but the wise man is one that averts it.

15 In the light of the king’s face there is life, and his goodwill is like the cloud of spring rain.

16 The getting of wisdom is O how much better than gold! And the getting of understanding is to be chosen more than silver.

17 The highway of the upright ones is to turn away from bad. One who is safeguarding his way is keeping his soul.

18 Pride is before a crash, and a haughty spirit before stumbling.

19 Better is it to be lowly in spirit with the meek ones than to divide spoil with the self-exalted ones.

20 He that is showing insight in a matter will find good, and happy is he that is trusting in Jehovah.

21 The one that is wise in heart will be called understanding, and he that is sweet in his lips adds persuasiveness.

22 To its owners insight is a well of life; and the discipline of the foolish ones is foolishness.

23 The heart of the wise one causes his mouth to show insight, and to his lips it adds persuasiveness.

24 Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, sweet to the soul and a healing to the bones.

25 There exists a way that is upright before a man, but the ways of death are the end of it afterward.

26 The soul of the hard worker has worked hard for him, because his mouth has pressed him hard.

27 A good-for-nothing man is digging up what is bad, and upon his lips there is, as it were, a scorching fire.

28 A man of intrigues keeps sending forth contention, and a slanderer is separating those familiar with one another.

29 A man of violence will seduce his fellow, and certainly causes him to go in a way that is not good. 30 He is blinking with his eyes to scheme up intrigues. Pinching his lips together, he certainly brings mischief to completion.

31 Gray-headedness is a crown of beauty when it is found in the way of righteousness.

32 He that is slow to anger is better than a mighty man, and he that is controlling his spirit than the one capturing a city.

33 Into the lap the lot is cast down, but every decision by it is from Jehovah.

Proverbs

17 Better is a dry piece of bread with which there is quietness than a house full of the sacrifices of quarreling.

2 A servant that is showing insight will rule over the son who is acting shamefully, and in among the brothers he will have a share of the inheritance.

3 The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, but Jehovah is the examiner of hearts.

4 The evildoer is paying attention to the lip of hurtfulness. A falsifier is giving ear to the tongue causing adversities.

5 He that is holding the one of little means in derision has reproached his Maker. He that is joyful at another’s disaster will not be free from punishment.

6 The crown of old men is the grandsons, and the beauty of sons is their fathers.

7 For anyone senseless the lip of uprightness is not fitting. How much less so for a noble the lip of falsehood!

8 The gift is a stone winning favor in the eyes of its grand owner. Everywhere that he turns he has success.

9 The one covering over transgression is seeking love, and he that keeps talking about a matter is separating those familiar with one another.

10 A rebuke works deeper in one having understanding than striking a stupid one a hundred times.

11 Only rebellion is what the bad one keeps seeking, and cruel is the messenger that is sent against him.

12 Let there be an encountering by a man of a bear bereaved of its cubs rather than anyone stupid in his foolishness.

13 As for anyone repaying bad for good, bad will not move away from his house.

14 The beginning of contention is as one letting out waters; so before the quarrel has burst forth, take your leave.

15 Anyone pronouncing the wicked one righteous and anyone pronouncing the righteous one wicked—even both of them are something detestable to Jehovah.

16 Why is it that there is in the hand of a stupid one the price to acquire wisdom, when he has no heart?

17 A true companion is loving all the time, and is a brother that is born for when there is distress.

18 A man that is wanting in heart shakes hands, going full surety before his companion.

19 Anyone loving transgression is loving a struggle. Anyone making his entryway high is seeking a crash.

20 He that is crooked at heart will not find good, and he that is turned around in his tongue will fall into calamity.

21 Anyone becoming father to a stupid child—it is a grief to him; and the father of a senseless child does not rejoice.

22 A heart that is joyful does good as a curer, but a spirit that is stricken makes the bones dry.

23 One who is wicked will take even a bribe from the bosom to bend the paths of judgment.

24 Wisdom is before the face of the understanding one, but the eyes of the stupid one are at the extremity of the earth.

25 A stupid son is a vexation to his father and a bitterness to her that gave him birth.

26 Furthermore, the laying of a fine upon the righteous one is not good. To strike nobles is against what is upright.

27 Anyone holding back his sayings is possessed of knowledge, and a man of discernment is cool of spirit.

28 Even anyone foolish, when keeping silent, will be regarded as wise; anyone closing up his own lips, as having understanding.

Proverbs

18 One isolating himself will seek his own selfish longing; against all practical wisdom he will break forth.

2 Anyone stupid finds no delight in discernment, except that his heart should uncover itself.

3 When a wicked one comes in, contempt also must come in; and along with dishonor there is reproach.

4 The words of a man’s mouth are deep waters. The well of wisdom is a torrent bubbling forth.

5 The showing of partiality to the wicked one is not good, nor the turning aside of the righteous one in judgment.

6 The lips of one who is stupid enter into quarreling, and his very mouth calls even for strokes.

7 The mouth of the stupid one is the ruin of him, and his lips are a snare for his soul.

8 The words of the slanderer are like things to be swallowed greedily, which do go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

9 Also, the one showing himself slack in his work—he is a brother to the one causing ruin.

10 The name of Jehovah is a strong tower. Into it the righteous runs and is given protection.

11 The valuable things of the rich are his strong town, and they are like a protective wall in his imagination.

12 Before a crash the heart of a man is lofty, and before glory there is humility.

13 When anyone is replying to a matter before he hears it, that is foolishness on his part and a humiliation.

14 The spirit of a man can put up with his malady; but as for a stricken spirit, who can bear it?

15 The heart of the understanding one acquires knowledge, and the ear of wise ones seeks to find knowledge.

16 A man’s gift will make a large opening for him, and it will lead him even before great people.

17 The one first in his legal case is righteous; his fellow comes in and certainly searches him through.

18 The lot puts even contentions to rest, and it separates even the mighty from one another.

19 A brother who is transgressed against is more than a strong town; and there are contentions that are like the bar of a dwelling tower.

20 From the fruitage of a man’s mouth his belly will be satisfied; he will be satisfied even with the produce of his lips.

21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue, and he that is loving it will eat its fruitage.

22 Has one found a good wife? One has found a good thing, and one gets goodwill from Jehovah.

23 Entreaties the one of little means speaks out, but one that is rich answers in a strong way.

24 There exist companions disposed to break one another to pieces, but there exists a friend sticking closer than a brother.

Proverbs

19 Anyone of little means who is walking in his integrity is better than the one crooked in his lips, and the one that is stupid.

2 Also, that the soul should be without knowledge is not good, and he that is hastening with his feet is sinning.

3 It is the foolishness of an earthling man that distorts his way, and so his heart becomes enraged against Jehovah himself.

4 Wealth is what adds many companions, but one that is lowly gets separated even from his companion.

5 A false witness will not be free from punishment, and he that launches forth lies will not escape.

6 Many are those who soften the face of a noble, and everybody is a companion to the man making gifts.

7 The brothers of one of little means have all hated him. How much farther have his personal friends kept away from him! He is pursuing with things to say; they are not.

8 He that is acquiring heart is loving his own soul. He that is guarding discernment is going to find good.

9 The false witness will not be free from punishment, and he that launches forth lies will perish.

10 Luxury is not fitting for anyone stupid. How much less for a servant to rule over princes!

11 The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, and it is beauty on his part to pass over transgression.

12 The raging of a king is a growling like that of a maned young lion, but his goodwill is like the dew upon the vegetation.

13 A stupid son means adversities to his father, and the contentions of a wife are as a leaking roof that drives one away.

14 The inheritance from fathers is a house and wealth, but a discreet wife is from Jehovah.

15 Laziness causes a deep sleep to fall, and a slack soul goes hungry.

16 He that is keeping the commandment is keeping his soul; he that is despising his ways will be put to death.

17 He that is showing favor to the lowly one is lending to Jehovah, and his treatment He will repay to him.

18 Chastise your son while there exists hope; and to the putting of him to death do not lift up your soulful desire.

19 He that is of great rage will be bearing the fine; for if you would deliver him, you will also keep doing it again and again.

20 Listen to counsel and accept discipline, in order that you may become wise in your future.

21 Many are the plans in the heart of a man, but the counsel of Jehovah is what will stand.

22 The desirable thing in earthling man is his loving-kindness; and one of little means is better than a lying man.

23 The fear of Jehovah tends toward life, and one will spend the night satisfied; one will not be visited with what is bad.

24 The lazy one has hidden his hand in the banquet bowl; he cannot bring it back even to his own mouth.

25 The ridiculer you should strike, that the inexperienced one may become shrewd; and there should be a reproving of the understanding one, that he may discern knowledge.

26 He that is maltreating a father and that chases a mother away is a son acting shamefully and disgracefully.

27 Cease, my son, to listen to discipline and it will mean to stray from the sayings of knowledge.

28 A good-for-nothing witness derides justice, and the very mouth of wicked people swallows down what is hurtful.

29 Judgments have been firmly established for ridiculers, and strokes for the back of stupid ones.

Proverbs

20 Wine is a ridiculer, intoxicating liquor is boisterous, and everyone going astray by it is not wise.

2 The frightfulness of a king is a growling like that of a maned young lion. Anyone drawing his fury against himself is sinning against his own soul.

3 It is a glory for a man to desist from disputing, but everyone foolish will burst out in it.

4 Because of winter the lazy one will not plow; he will be begging in reaping time, but there will be nothing.

5 Counsel in the heart of a man is as deep waters, but the man of discernment is one that will draw it up.

6 A multitude of men will proclaim each one his own loving-kindness, but a faithful man who can find?

7 The righteous is walking in his integrity. Happy are his sons after him.

8 The king is sitting upon the throne of judgment, scattering all badness with his own eyes.

9 Who can say: “I have cleansed my heart; I have become pure from my sin”?

10 Two sorts of weights and two sorts of e′phah measures—they are both of them together something detestable to Jehovah.

11 Even by his practices a boy makes himself recognized as to whether his activity is pure and upright.

12 The hearing ear and the seeing eye—Jehovah himself has made even both of them.

13 Do not love sleep, that you may not come to poverty. Open your eyes; be satisfied with bread.

14 “It is bad, bad!” says the buyer, and he is going his way. Then it is that he boasts about himself.

15 There exists gold, also an abundance of corals; but the lips of knowledge are precious vessels.

16 Take one’s garment, in case one has gone surety for a stranger; and in the instance of a foreign woman, seize from him a pledge.

17 Bread gained by falsehood is pleasurable to a man, but afterward his mouth will be filled with gravel.

18 By counsel plans themselves are firmly established, and by skillful direction carry on your war.

19 He that is going about as a slanderer is uncovering confidential talk; and with one that is enticed with his lips you must have no fellowship.

20 As for anyone calling down evil upon his father and his mother, his lamp will be extinguished at the approach of darkness.

21 An inheritance is being got by greed at first, but its own future will not be blessed.

22 Do not say: “I will pay back evil!” Hope in Jehovah, and he will save you.

23 Two sorts of weights are something detestable to Jehovah, and a cheating pair of scales is not good.

24 From Jehovah are the steppings of an able-bodied man. As regards earthling man, how can he discern his way?

25 It is a snare when earthling man has rashly cried out, “Holy!” and after vows he is disposed to make examination.

26 A wise king is scattering wicked people, and he turns around upon them a wheel.

27 The breath of earthling man is the lamp of Jehovah, carefully searching all the innermost parts of the belly.

28 Loving-kindness and trueness—they safeguard the king; and by loving-kindness he has sustained his throne.

29 The beauty of young men is their power, and the splendor of old men is their gray-headedness.

30 Bruising wounds are what scours away the bad; and strokes, the innermost parts of the belly.

Proverbs

22 A name is to be chosen rather than abundant riches; favor is better than even silver and gold.

2 The rich one and the one of little means have met each other. The Maker of them all is Jehovah.

3 Shrewd is the one that has seen the calamity and proceeds to conceal himself, but the inexperienced have passed along and must suffer the penalty.

4 The result of humility and the fear of Jehovah is riches and glory and life.

5 Thorns and traps are in the way of the crooked one; he that is guarding his soul keeps far away from them.

6 Train up a boy according to the way for him; even when he grows old he will not turn aside from it.

7 The rich is the one that rules over those of little means, and the borrower is servant to the man doing the lending.

8 He that is sowing unrighteousness will reap what is hurtful, but the very rod of his fury will come to its end.

9 He that is kindly in eye will be blessed, for he has given of his food to the lowly one.

10 Drive away the ridiculer, that contention may go out and that legal contest and dishonor may cease.

11 The one loving purity of heart—for the charm of his lips the king will be his companion.

12 The eyes of Jehovah himself have safeguarded knowledge, but he subverts the words of the treacherous one.

13 The lazy one has said: “There is a lion outside! In the midst of the public squares I shall be murdered!”

14 The mouth of strange women is a deep pit. The one denounced by Jehovah will fall into it.

15 Foolishness is tied up with the heart of a boy; the rod of discipline is what will remove it far from him.

16 He that is defrauding the lowly one to supply many things to himself, he also that is giving to the rich one, is surely destined for want.

17 Incline your ear and hear the words of the wise ones, that you may apply your very heart to my knowledge. 18 For it is pleasant that you should keep them in your belly, that they may be firmly established together upon your lips.

19 For your confidence to come to be in Jehovah himself I have given you knowledge today, even you.

20 Have I not written you heretofore with counselings and knowledge, 21 to show you the truthfulness of true sayings, so as to return sayings that are the truth—to the one sending you forth?

22 Do not rob the lowly one because he is lowly, and do not crush the afflicted one in the gate. 23 For Jehovah himself will plead their cause, and he will certainly rob of soul those robbing them.

24 Do not have companionship with anyone given to anger; and with a man having fits of rage you must not enter in, 25 that you may not get familiar with his paths and certainly take a snare for your soul.

26 Do not get to be among those striking hands, among those who go security for loans. 27 If you have nothing to pay, why should he take your bed from under you?

28 Do not move back a boundary of long ago, which your forefathers have made.

29 Have you beheld a man skillful in his work? Before kings is where he will station himself; he will not station himself before commonplace men.

Proverbs

24 Do not be envious of bad men, and do not show yourself craving to get in with them. 2 For despoiling is what their heart keeps meditating, and trouble is what their own lips keep speaking.

3 By wisdom a household will be built up, and by discernment it will prove firmly established. 4 And by knowledge will the interior rooms be filled with all precious and pleasant things of value.

5 One wise in strength is an able-bodied man, and a man of knowledge is reinforcing power. 6 For by skillful direction you will carry on your war, and in the multitude of counselors there is salvation.

7 For a foolish one true wisdom is too high; in the gate he will not open his mouth.

8 As for anyone scheming to do bad, he will be called a mere master at evil ideas.

9 The loose conduct of foolishness is sin, and a ridiculer is something detestable to mankind.

10 Have you shown yourself discouraged in the day of distress? Your power will be scanty.

11 Deliver those who are being taken away to death; and those staggering to the slaughter, O may you hold them back. 12 In case you should say: “Look! We did not know of this,” will not he himself that is making an estimate of hearts discern it, and he himself that is observing your soul know and certainly pay back to earthling man according to his activity?

13 My son, eat honey, for it is good; and let sweet comb honey be upon your palate. 14 In the same way, do know wisdom for your soul. If you have found it, then there exists a future, and your own hope will not be cut off.

15 Do not, as a wicked one, lie in wait for the abiding place of the righteous one; do not despoil his resting-place. 16 For the righteous one may fall even seven times, and he will certainly get up; but the wicked ones will be made to stumble by calamity.

17 When your enemy falls, do not rejoice; and when he is caused to stumble, may your heart not be joyful, 18 that Jehovah may not see and it be bad in his eyes and he certainly turn back his anger from against him.

19 Do not show yourself heated up at evildoers. Do not become envious of wicked people. 20 For there will prove to be no future for anyone bad; the very lamp of wicked people will be extinguished.

21 My son, fear Jehovah and the king. With those who are for a change, do not intermeddle. 22 For their disaster will arise so suddenly, that who is aware of the extinction of those who are for a change?

23 These sayings also are for the wise ones: The showing of partiality in judgment is not good.

24 He that is saying to the wicked one: “You are righteous,” the peoples will execrate him, national groups will denounce him. 25 But for those reproving him it will be pleasant, and upon them there will come the blessing of good. 26 Lips will he kiss who is replying in a straightforward way.

27 Prepare your work out of doors, and make it ready for yourself in the field. Afterward you must also build up your household.

28 Do not become a witness against your fellowman without grounds. Then you would have to be foolish with your lips. 29 Do not say: “Just as he did to me, so I am going to do to him. I shall repay to each one according to his acting.”

30 I passed along by the field of the lazy individual and by the vineyard of the man in need of heart. 31 And, look! all of it produced weeds. Nettles covered its very surface, and its stone wall itself had been torn down.

32 So I proceeded to behold, I myself; I began taking it to heart; I saw, I took the discipline: 33 A little sleeping, a little slumbering, a little folding of the hands to lie down, 34 and as a highwayman your poverty will certainly come and your neediness as an armed man.

Proverbs

26 Like snow in summer and like rain in harvesttime, so glory is not fitting for a stupid one.

2 Just as a bird has cause for fleeing and just as a swallow for flying, so a malediction itself does not come without real cause.

3 A whip is for the horse, a bridle is for the ass, and the rod is for the back of stupid people.

4 Do not answer anyone stupid according to his foolishness, that you yourself also may not become equal to him.

5 Answer someone stupid according to his foolishness, that he may not become someone wise in his own eyes.

6 As one that is mutilating his feet, as one that is drinking mere violence, is he that is thrusting matters into the hand of someone stupid.

7 Have the legs of the lame one drawn up water? Then there is a proverb in the mouth of stupid people.

8 Like one shutting up a stone in a heap of stones, so is the one giving glory to a mere stupid one.

9 As a thorny weed has come up into the hand of a drunkard, so a proverb into the mouth of stupid people.

10 As an archer piercing everything is the one hiring someone stupid or the one hiring passersby.

11 Just like a dog returning to its vomit, the stupid one is repeating his foolishness.

12 Have you seen a man wise in his own eyes? There is more hope for the stupid one than for him.

13 The lazy one has said: “There is a young lion in the way, a lion in among the public squares.”

14 A door keeps turning upon its pivot, and the lazy one upon his couch.

15 The lazy one has hidden his hand in the banquet bowl; he has become too weary to bring it back to his mouth.

16 The lazy one is wiser in his own eyes than seven giving a sensible reply.

17 As one grabbing hold of the ears of a dog is anyone passing by that is becoming furious at the quarrel that is not his.

18 Just like someone mad that is shooting fiery missiles, arrows and death, 19 so is the man that has tricked his fellowman and has said: “Was I not having fun?”

20 Where there is no wood the fire goes out, and where there is no slanderer contention grows still.

21 As charcoal for the embers and wood for the fire, so is a contentious man for causing a quarrel to glow.

22 The words of a slanderer are like things to be swallowed greedily, which do go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

23 As a silver glazing overlaid upon a fragment of earthenware are fervent lips along with a bad heart.

24 With his lips the hater makes himself unrecognizable, but inside of him he puts deception. 25 Although he makes his voice gracious, do not believe in him, for there are seven detestable things in his heart. 26 Hatred is covered over by deceit. His badness will be uncovered in the congregation.

27 He that is excavating a pit will fall into the same, and he that is rolling away a stone—back to him it will return.

28 A tongue that is false hates the one crushed by it, and a flattering mouth causes an overthrow.

Proverbs

27 Do not make your boast about the next day, for you do not know what a day will give birth to.

2 May a stranger, and not your own mouth, praise you; may a foreigner, and not your own lips, do so.

3 The heaviness of a stone and a load of sand—but the vexation by someone foolish is heavier than both of them.

4 There is the cruelty of rage, also the flood of anger, but who can stand before jealousy?

5 Better is a revealed reproof than a concealed love.

6 The wounds inflicted by a lover are faithful, but the kisses of a hater are things to be entreated.

7 A soul that is satisfied will tread down comb honey, but to a hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.

8 Just like a bird fleeing away from its nest, so is a man fleeing away from his place.

9 Oil and incense are what make the heart rejoice, also the sweetness of one’s companion due to the counsel of the soul.

10 Do not leave your own companion or the companion of your father, and do not enter the house of your own brother on the day of your disaster. Better is a neighbor that is near than a brother that is far away.

11 Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, that I may make a reply to him that is taunting me.

12 The shrewd one that has seen the calamity has concealed himself; the inexperienced that have passed along have suffered the penalty.

13 Take one’s garment, in case one has gone surety for a stranger; and in the instance of a foreign woman, seize from him a pledge.

14 He that is blessing his fellowman with a loud voice early in the morning, as a malediction it will be accounted on his part.

15 A leaking roof that drives one away in the day of a steady rain and a contentious wife are comparable. 16 Anyone sheltering her has sheltered the wind, and oil is what his right hand encounters.

17 By iron, iron itself is sharpened. So one man sharpens the face of another.

18 He that is safeguarding the fig tree will himself eat its fruit, and he that is guarding his master will be honored.

19 As in water face corresponds with face, so the heart of a man with that of a man.

20 She′ol and the place of destruction themselves do not get satisfied; neither do the eyes of a man get satisfied.

21 The refining pot is for silver, and the furnace is for gold; and an individual is according to his praise.

22 Even if you should pound the foolish one fine with a pestle in a mortar, in among cracked grain, his foolishness will not depart from him.

23 You ought to know positively the appearance of your flock. Set your heart to your droves; 24 for treasure will not be to time indefinite, nor a diadem for all generations.

25 The green grass has departed, and the new grass has appeared, and the vegetation of the mountains has been gathered. 26 The young rams are for your clothing, and the he-goats are the price of the field. 27 And there is a sufficiency of goats’ milk for your food, for the food of your household, and the means of life for your girls.

Proverbs

28 The wicked do flee when there is no pursuer, but the righteous are like a young lion that is confident.

2 Because of the transgression of a land many are its successive princes, but by a discerning man having knowledge of right the prince will remain long.

3 An able-bodied man that is of little means and that is defrauding the lowly ones is as a rain that washes away so that there is no food.

4 Those who are leaving the law praise the wicked one, but those who are keeping the law excite themselves against them.

5 Men given to badness cannot understand judgment, but those who are seeking Jehovah can understand everything.

6 Better is the one of little means who is walking in his integrity than anyone crooked in his ways, although he is rich.

7 An understanding son is observing the law, but one having companionship with gluttons humiliates his father.

8 He that is multiplying his valuables by interest and usury collects them merely for the one showing favor to the lowly ones.

9 He that is turning his ear away from hearing the law—even his prayer is something detestable.

10 He that is causing the upright ones to go astray into the bad way will himself fall into his own pit, but the faultless ones themselves will come into possession of good.

11 A rich man is wise in his own eyes, but the lowly one who is discerning searches him through.

12 When the righteous ones are exulting, there is abundant beauty; but when the wicked ones rise up, a man disguises himself.

13 He that is covering over his transgressions will not succeed, but he that is confessing and leaving them will be shown mercy.

14 Happy is the man that is feeling dread constantly, but he that is hardening his heart will fall into calamity.

15 As a growling lion and an onrushing bear is a wicked ruler over a lowly people.

16 A leader that is in want of true discernment is also abundant in fraudulent practices, but he that is hating unjust profit will prolong his days.

17 A man burdened with the bloodguilt for a soul will himself flee even to the pit. Let them not get hold of him.

18 He that is walking faultlessly will be saved, but he that is made crooked in his ways will fall at once.

19 He that is cultivating his own ground will have his sufficiency of bread, and he that is pursuing valueless things will have his sufficiency of poverty.

20 A man of faithful acts will get many blessings, but he that is hastening to gain riches will not remain innocent.

21 The showing of partiality is not good, nor that an able-bodied man should transgress over a mere piece of bread.

22 A man of envious eye is bestirring himself after valuable things, but he does not know that want itself will come upon him.

23 He that is reproving a man will afterward find more favor than he will that is flattering with his tongue.

24 He that is robbing his father and his mother and is saying: “It is no transgression,” is a partner of a man causing ruination.

25 He that is arrogant in soul stirs up contention, but he that is relying upon Jehovah will be made fat.

26 He that is trusting in his own heart is stupid, but he that is walking in wisdom is the one that will escape.

27 He that is giving to the one of little means will have no want, but he that is hiding his eyes will get many curses.

28 When the wicked rise up, a man conceals himself; but when they perish, the righteous become many.

Proverbs

29 A man repeatedly reproved but making his neck hard will suddenly be broken, and that without healing.

2 When the righteous become many, the people rejoice; but when anyone wicked bears rule, the people sigh.

3 A man that is loving wisdom makes his father rejoice, but he that is having companionship with prostitutes destroys valuable things.

4 By justice a king makes a land keep standing, but a man out for bribes tears it down.

5 An able-bodied man that is flattering his companion is spreading out a mere net for his steps.

6 In the transgression of a bad man there is a snare, but he that is righteous cries out joyfully and is glad.

7 The righteous one is knowing the legal claim of the lowly ones. He that is wicked does not consider such knowledge.

8 Men of boastful talk inflame a town, but those who are wise turn back anger.

9 A wise man having entered into judgment with a foolish man—he has become excited and has also laughed, and there is no rest.

10 Bloodthirsty men hate anyone blameless; and as for the upright ones, they keep seeking for the soul of each one.

11 All his spirit is what a stupid one lets out, but he that is wise keeps it calm to the last.

12 Where a ruler is paying attention to false speech, all those waiting on him will be wicked.

13 The one of little means and the man of oppressions have met each other; but Jehovah is lighting up the eyes of them both.

14 Where a king is judging the lowly ones in trueness, his throne will be firmly established for all time.

15 The rod and reproof are what give wisdom; but a boy let on the loose will be causing his mother shame.

16 When the wicked become many, transgression abounds; but those who are righteous will look on their very downfall.

17 Chastise your son and he will bring you rest and give much pleasure to your soul.

18 Where there is no vision the people go unrestrained, but happy are they that are keeping the law.

19 A servant will not let himself be corrected by mere words, for he understands but he is paying no heed.

20 Have you beheld a man hasty with his words? There is more hope for someone stupid than for him.

21 If one is pampering one’s servant from youth on, in his later life he will even become a thankless one.

22 A man given to anger stirs up contention, and anyone disposed to rage has many a transgression.

23 The very haughtiness of earthling man will humble him, but he that is humble in spirit will take hold of glory.

24 He that is partner with a thief is hating his own soul. An oath involving a curse he may hear, but he reports nothing.

25 Trembling at men is what lays a snare, but he that is trusting in Jehovah will be protected.

26 Many are those seeking the face of a ruler, but the judgment of a man is from Jehovah.

27 A man of injustice is something detestable to the righteous ones, and one who is upright in his way is something detestable to a wicked one.

Ecclesiastes

2 I said, even I, in my heart: “Do come now, let me try you out with rejoicing. Also, see good.” And, look! that too was vanity. 2 I said to laughter: “Insanity!” and to rejoicing: “What is this doing?”

3 I explored with my heart by cheering my flesh even with wine, while I was leading my heart with wisdom, even to lay hold on folly until I could see what good there was to the sons of mankind in what they did under the heavens for the number of the days of their life. 4 I engaged in greater works. I built houses for myself; I planted vineyards for myself. 5 I made gardens and parks for myself, and I planted in them fruit trees of all sorts. 6 I made pools of water for myself, to irrigate with them the forest, springing up with trees. 7 I acquired menservants and maidservants, and I came to have sons of the household. Also, livestock, cattle and flocks in great quantity I came to have, more so than all those who happened to be before me in Jerusalem. 8 I accumulated also silver and gold for myself, and property peculiar to kings and the jurisdictional districts. I made male singers and female singers for myself and the exquisite delights of the sons of mankind, a lady, even ladies. 9 And I became greater and increased more than anyone that happened to be before me in Jerusalem. Moreover, my own wisdom remained mine.

10 And anything that my eyes asked for I did not keep away from them. I did not hold back my heart from any sort of rejoicing, for my heart was joyful because of all my hard work, and this came to be my portion from all my hard work. 11 And I, even I, turned toward all the works of mine that my hands had done and toward the hard work that I had worked hard to accomplish, and, look! everything was vanity and a striving after wind, and there was nothing of advantage under the sun.

12 And I, even I, turned to see wisdom and madness and folly; for what can the earthling man do who comes in after the king? The thing that people have already done. 13 And I saw, even I, that there exists more advantage for wisdom than for folly, just as there is more advantage for light than for darkness.

14 As regards anyone wise, his eyes are in his head; but the stupid one is walking on in sheer darkness. And I have come to know, I too, that there is one eventuality that eventuates to them all. 15 And I myself said in my heart: “An eventuality like that upon the stupid one will eventuate to me, yes, me.” Why, then, had I become wise, I overmuch so at that time? And I spoke in my heart: “This too is vanity.” 16 For there is no more remembrance of the wise one than of the stupid one to time indefinite. In the days that are already coming in, everyone is certainly forgotten; and how will the wise one die? Along with the stupid one.

17 And I hated life, because the work that has been done under the sun was calamitous from my standpoint, for everything was vanity and a striving after wind. 18 And I, even I, hated all my hard work at which I was working hard under the sun, that I would leave behind for the man who would come to be after me. 19 And who is there knowing whether he will prove to be wise or foolish? Yet he will take control over all my hard work at which I worked hard and at which I showed wisdom under the sun. This too is vanity. 20 And I myself turned around toward making my heart despair over all the hard work at which I had worked hard under the sun. 21 For there exists the man whose hard work has been with wisdom and with knowledge and with proficiency, but to a man that has not worked hard at such a thing will be given the portion of that one. This too is vanity and a big calamity.

22 For what does a man come to have for all his hard work and for the striving of his heart with which he is working hard under the sun? 23 For all his days his occupation means pains and vexation, also during the night his heart just does not lie down. This too is mere vanity.

24 With a man there is nothing better than that he should eat and indeed drink and cause his soul to see good because of his hard work. This too I have seen, even I, that this is from the hand of the true God. 25 For who eats and who drinks better than I do?

26 For to the man that is good before him he has given wisdom and knowledge and rejoicing, but to the sinner he has given the occupation of gathering and bringing together merely to give to the one that is good before the true God. This too is vanity and a striving after wind.

Ecclesiastes

3 For everything there is an appointed time, even a time for every affair under the heavens: 2 a time for birth and a time to die; a time to plant and a time to uproot what was planted; 3 a time to kill and a time to heal; a time to break down and a time to build; 4 a time to weep and a time to laugh; a time to wail and a time to skip about; 5 a time to throw stones away and a time to bring stones together; a time to embrace and a time to keep away from embracing; 6 a time to seek and a time to give up as lost; a time to keep and a time to throw away; 7 a time to rip apart and a time to sew together; a time to keep quiet and a time to speak; 8 a time to love and a time to hate; a time for war and a time for peace. 9 What advantage is there for the doer in what he is working hard at?

10 I have seen the occupation that God has given to the sons of mankind in which to be occupied. 11 Everything he has made pretty in its time. Even time indefinite he has put in their heart, that mankind may never find out the work that the true God has made from the start to the finish. 12 I have come to know that there is nothing better for them than to rejoice and to do good during one’s life; 13 and also that every man should eat and indeed drink and see good for all his hard work. It is the gift of God.

14 I have come to know that everything that the true God makes, it will prove to be to time indefinite. To it there is nothing to add and from it there is nothing to subtract; but the true God himself has made it, that people may be afraid on account of him.

15 What has happened to be, it had already been, and what is to come to be has already proved to be; and the true God himself keeps seeking that which is pursued.

16 And I have further seen under the sun the place of justice where there was wickedness and the place of righteousness where wickedness was. 17 I myself have said in my heart: “The true God will judge both the righteous one and the wicked one, for there is a time for every affair and concerning every work there.”

18 I, even I, have said in my heart with regard to the sons of mankind that the true God is going to select them, that they may see that they themselves are beasts. 19 For there is an eventuality as respects the sons of mankind and an eventuality as respects the beast, and they have the same eventuality. As the one dies, so the other dies; and they all have but one spirit, so that there is no superiority of the man over the beast, for everything is vanity. 20 All are going to one place. They have all come to be from the dust, and they are all returning to the dust. 21 Who is there knowing the spirit of the sons of mankind, whether it is ascending upward; and the spirit of the beast, whether it is descending downward to the earth? 22 And I have seen that there is nothing better than that the man should rejoice in his works, for that is his portion; because who will bring him in to look on what is going to be after him?

Ecclesiastes

4 And I myself returned that I might see all the acts of oppression that are being done under the sun, and, look! the tears of those being oppressed, but they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power, so that they had no comforter. 2 And I congratulated the dead who had already died rather than the living who were still alive. 3 So better than both of them is the one who has not yet come to be, who has not seen the calamitous work that is being done under the sun.

4 And I myself have seen all the hard work and all the proficiency in work, that it means the rivalry of one toward another; this also is vanity and a striving after the wind.

5 The stupid one is folding his hands and is eating his own flesh.

6 Better is a handful of rest than a double handful of hard work and striving after the wind.

7 I myself returned that I might see the vanity under the sun: 8 There exists one, but not a second one; also no son or brother does he have, but there is no end to all his hard work. Also, his eyes themselves are not satisfied with riches: “And for whom am I working hard and causing my soul to lack in good things?” This too is vanity, and it is a calamitous occupation.

9 Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their hard work. 10 For if one of them should fall, the other one can raise his partner up. But how will it be with just the one who falls when there is not another to raise him up?

11 Moreover, if two lie down together, they also will certainly get warm; but how can just one keep warm? 12 And if somebody could overpower one alone, two together could make a stand against him. And a threefold cord cannot quickly be torn in two.

13 Better is a needy but wise child than an old but stupid king, who has not come to know enough to be warned any longer. 14 For he has gone forth from the prison house itself to become king, although in the kingship of this one he had been born as one of little means. 15 I have seen all those alive who are walking about under the sun, how it goes with the child, who is second, that stands up in the other one’s place. 16 There is no end to all the people, to all those before whom he happened to be; neither will people afterward rejoice in him, for this too is vanity and a striving after the wind.

Ecclesiastes

6 There exists a calamity that I have seen under the sun, and it is frequent among mankind: 2 a man to whom the true God gives riches and material possessions and glory and who, for his soul, is in no need of anything that he shows himself longing for, and yet the true God does not enable him to eat from it, although a mere foreigner may eat it. This is vanity and it is a bad sickness. 3 If a man should become a father a hundred times, and he should live many years, so that numerous the days of his years should become, yet his own soul is not satisfied with good things and even the grave has not become his, I must say that one prematurely born is better off than he is. 4 For in vain has this one come and in darkness he goes away, and with darkness his own name will be covered. 5 Even the sun itself he has not seen, neither known. This one has rest rather than the former one. 6 Even supposing that he has lived a thousand years twice over and yet he has not seen what is good, is it not to just one place that everyone is going?

7 All the hard work of mankind is for their mouth, but even their own soul does not get filled. 8 For what advantage does the wise have over the stupid one? What does the afflicted one have in knowing how to walk in front of the living ones? 9 Better is the seeing by the eyes than the walking about of the soul. This too is vanity and a striving after the wind.

10 Whatever has come to be, its name has already been pronounced, and it has become known what man is; and he is not able to plead his cause with one that is more powerful than he is.

11 Because there exist many things that are causing much vanity, what advantage does a man have? 12 For who is there knowing what good a man has in life for the number of the days of his vain life, when he spends them like a shadow? For who can tell man what will happen after him under the sun?

Ecclesiastes

8 Who is there like the wise one? And who is there knowing the interpretation of a thing? The wisdom of a man itself causes his face to shine, and even the sternness of his face is changed for the better.

2 I say: “Keep the very order of the king, and that out of regard for the oath of God. 3 Do not hurry yourself, that you may go out from before him. Do not stand in a bad thing. For all that he delights to do he will do, 4 because the word of the king is the power of control; and who may say to him: ‘What are you doing?’”

5 He that is keeping the commandment will not know any calamitous thing, and the wise heart will know both time and judgment. 6 For there exists a time and judgment even for every affair, because the calamity of mankind is abundant upon them. 7 For there is no one knowing what will come to be, because who can tell him just how it will come to be?

8 There is no man having power over the spirit to restrain the spirit; neither is there any power of control in the day of death; nor is there any discharge in the war. And wickedness will provide no escape for those indulging in it.

9 All this I have seen, and there was an applying of my heart to every work that has been done under the sun, during the time that man has dominated man to his injury. 10 But, though this is so, I have seen the wicked ones being buried, how they came in and how they would go away from the holy place itself and be forgotten in the city where they acted that way. This too is vanity.

11 Because sentence against a bad work has not been executed speedily, that is why the heart of the sons of men has become fully set in them to do bad. 12 Although a sinner may be doing bad a hundred times and continuing a long time as he pleases, yet I am also aware that it will turn out well with those fearing the true God, because they were in fear of him. 13 But it will not turn out well at all with the wicked one, neither will he prolong his days that are like a shadow, because he is not in fear of God.

14 There exists a vanity that is carried out on the earth, that there exist righteous ones to whom it is happening as if for the work of the wicked ones, and there exist wicked ones to whom it is happening as if for the work of the righteous ones. I said that this too is vanity.

15 And I myself commended rejoicing, because mankind have nothing better under the sun than to eat and drink and rejoice, and that it should accompany them in their hard work for the days of their life, which the true God has given them under the sun. 16 In accord with this I applied my heart to know wisdom and to see the occupation that is carried on in the earth, because there is one seeing no sleep with his eyes, either by day or by night.

17 And I saw all the work of the true God, how mankind are not able to find out the work that has been done under the sun; however much mankind keep working hard to seek, yet they do not find out. And even if they should say they are wise enough to know, they would be unable to find out.

Song of Solomon

2 “A mere saffron of the coastal plain I am, a lily of the low plains.”

2 “Like a lily among thorny weeds, so is my girl companion among the daughters.”

3 “Like an apple tree among the trees of the forest, so is my dear one among the sons. His shade I have passionately desired, and there I have sat down, and his fruit has been sweet to my palate. 4 He brought me into the house of wine, and his banner over me was love. 5 Do YOU people refresh me with cakes of raisins, sustain me with apples; for I am lovesick. 6 His left hand is under my head; and his right hand—it embraces me. 7 I have put YOU under oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the female gazelles or by the hinds of the field, that YOU try not to awaken or arouse love in me until it feels inclined.

8 “The sound of my dear one! Look! This one is coming, climbing upon the mountains, leaping upon the hills. 9 My dear one is resembling a gazelle or the young of the stags. Look! This one is standing behind our wall, gazing through the windows, glancing through the lattices. 10 My dear one has answered and said to me, ‘Rise up, you girl companion of mine, my beautiful one, and come away. 11 For, look! the rainy season itself has passed, the downpour itself is over, it has gone its way. 12 Blossoms themselves have appeared in the land, the very time of vine trimming has arrived, and the voice of the turtledove itself has been heard in our land. 13 As for the fig tree, it has gained a mature color for its early figs; and the vines are abloom, they have given their fragrance. Rise up, come, O girl companion of mine, my beautiful one, and come away. 14 O my dove in the retreats of the crag, in the concealed place of the steep way, show me your form, let me hear your voice, for your voice is pleasurable and your form is comely.’”

15 “Do YOU people grab hold of the foxes for us, the little foxes that are making spoil of the vineyards, as our vineyards are abloom.”

16 “My dear one is mine and I am his. He is shepherding among the lilies. 17 Until the day breathes and the shadows have fled, turn around, O my dear one; be like the gazelle or like the young of the stags upon the mountains of separation.

Isaiah

2 The thing that Isaiah the son of A′moz visioned concerning Judah and Jerusalem: 2 And it must occur in the final part of the days that the mountain of the house of Jehovah will become firmly established above the top of the mountains, and it will certainly be lifted up above the hills; and to it all the nations must stream. 3 And many peoples will certainly go and say: “Come, YOU people, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will instruct us about his ways, and we will walk in his paths.” For out of Zion law will go forth, and the word of Jehovah out of Jerusalem. 4 And he will certainly render judgment among the nations and set matters straight respecting many peoples. And they will have to beat their swords into plowshares and their spears into pruning shears. Nation will not lift up sword against nation, neither will they learn war anymore.

5 O men of the house of Jacob, come and let us walk in the light of Jehovah.

6 For you have forsaken your people, the house of Jacob. For they have become full of what is from the East, and they are practicers of magic like the Phi·lis′tines, and with the children of foreigners they abound. 7 And their land is filled with silver and gold, and there is no limit to their treasures. And their land is filled with horses, and there is no limit to their chariots. 8 And their land is filled with valueless gods. To the work of one’s hands they bow down, to that which one’s fingers have made. 9 And earthling man bows down, and man becomes low, and you cannot possibly pardon them.

10 Enter into the rock and hide yourself in the dust because of the dreadfulness of Jehovah, and from his splendid superiority. 11 The haughty eyes of earthling man must become low, and the loftiness of men must bow down; and Jehovah alone must be put on high in that day. 12 For it is the day belonging to Jehovah of armies. It is upon everyone self-exalted and lofty and upon everyone lifted up or low; 13 and upon all the cedars of Leb′a·non that are lofty and lifted up and upon all the massive trees of Ba′shan; 14 and upon all the lofty mountains and upon all the hills that are lifted up; 15 and upon every high tower and upon every fortified wall; 16 and upon all the ships of Tar′shish and upon all desirable boats. 17 And the haughtiness of the earthling man must bow down, and the loftiness of men must become low; and Jehovah alone must be put on high in that day.

18 And the valueless gods themselves will pass away completely. 19 And people will enter into the caves of the rocks and into the holes of the dust because of the dreadfulness of Jehovah and from his splendid superiority, when he rises up for the earth to suffer shocks. 20 In that day the earthling man will throw his worthless gods of silver and his valueless gods of gold that they had made for him to bow before to the shrewmice and to the bats, 21 in order to enter into the holes in the rocks and into the clefts of the crags, because of the dreadfulness of Jehovah and from his splendid superiority, when he rises up for the earth to suffer shocks. 22 For YOUR own sakes, hold off from the earthling man, whose breath is in his nostrils, for on what basis is he himself to be taken into account?

Isaiah

17 The pronouncement against Damascus: “Look! Damascus removed from being a city, and she has become a heap, a decaying ruin. 2 The cities of A·ro′er that have been left behind become mere places for droves, where they actually lie down, with no one to make them tremble. 3 And the fortified city has been made to cease out of E′phra·im, and the kingdom out of Damascus; and those of Syria remaining over will become just like the glory of the sons of Israel,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies.

4 “And it must occur in that day that the glory of Jacob will become lowly, and even the fatness of his flesh will be made lean. 5 And it must occur that when the harvester is gathering the standing grain and his own arm harvests the ears of grain, he must even become like one gleaning ears of grain in the low plain of Reph′a·im. 6 And there must remain in it a gleaning as when there is a beating off of the olive tree: two or three ripe olives in the top of the branch; four or five on the fruit-bearing boughs thereof,” is the utterance of Jehovah the God of Israel.

7 In that day earthling man will look up to his Maker, and his own eyes will gaze at the Holy One of Israel himself. 8 And he will not look to the altars, the work of his hands; and at what his fingers have made he will not gaze, either at the sacred poles or at the incense stands. 9 In that day his fortress cities will become like a place left entirely in the woodland, even the branch that they have left entirely on account of the sons of Israel; and it must become a desolate waste. 10 For you have forgotten the God of your salvation; and the Rock of your fortress you have not remembered. That is why you plant pleasant plantations, and with the shoot of a stranger you set it. 11 In the day you may carefully fence about the plantation of yours, and in the morning you may cause the seed of yours to sprout, but the harvest will certainly flee in the day of the disease and incurable pain.

12 Ha for the commotion of many peoples, who are boisterous as with the boisterousness of the seas! And for the noise of national groups, who make a din just like the noise of mighty waters! 13 The national groups themselves will make a din just like the noise of many waters. And He will certainly rebuke it, and it must flee far away and be chased like the chaff of the mountains before a wind and like a thistle whirl before a storm wind. 14 At evening time, why, look! there is sudden terror. Before morning—it is no more. This is the share of those pillaging us, and the lot belonging to those plundering us.

Isaiah

19 The pronouncement against Egypt: Look! Jehovah is riding on a swift cloud and coming into Egypt. And the valueless gods of Egypt will certainly quiver because of him, and the very heart of Egypt will melt in the midst of it.

2 “And I will goad Egyptians against Egyptians, and they will certainly war each one against his brother, and each one against his companion, city against city, kingdom against kingdom. 3 And the spirit of Egypt must become bewildered in the midst of it, and I shall confuse its own counsel. And they will be certain to resort to the valueless gods and to the charmers and to the spirit mediums and to the professional foretellers of events. 4 And I will deliver up Egypt into the hand of a hard master, and strong will be the king that will rule over them,” is the utterance of the true Lord, Jehovah of armies.

5 And the water will certainly be dried up from the sea, and the river itself will become parched and actually run dry. 6 And the rivers must stink; the Nile canals of Egypt must become low and parched. The reed and the rush themselves must molder. 7 The bare places by the Nile River, at the mouth of the Nile River, and every seedland of the Nile River will dry up. It will certainly be driven away, and it will be no more. 8 And the fishers will have to mourn, and all those casting fishhooks into the Nile River must express sorrow, and even those spreading fishing nets upon the surface of the water will actually fade away. 9 And the workers in carded flax must become ashamed; also the loom workers on white fabrics. 10 And her weavers must become crushed, all the wage workers grieved in soul.

11 The princes of Zo′an are indeed foolish. As regards the wise ones of Phar′aoh’s counselors, their counsel is something unreasonable. How will YOU men say to Phar′aoh: “I am the son of wise ones, the son of kings of ancient time”? 12 Where, then, are they—the wise men of yours—that they may now tell you and that they may know what Jehovah of armies has counseled concerning Egypt? 13 The princes of Zo′an have acted foolishly, the princes of Noph have been deceived, the keymen of her tribes have caused Egypt to wander about. 14 Jehovah himself has mingled in the midst of her the spirit of disconcertedness; and they have caused Egypt to wander about in all its work, just as someone drunk is made to wander about in his vomit. 15 And Egypt will not come to have any work that the head or the tail, the shoot or the rush, can do.

16 In that day Egypt will become like women, and it will certainly tremble and be in dread because of the waving of the hand of Jehovah of armies which he is waving against it. 17 And the ground of Judah must become to Egypt a cause for reeling. Everybody to whom one mentions it is in dread because of the counsel of Jehovah of armies that he is counseling against him.

18 In that day there will prove to be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the language of Ca′naan and swearing to Jehovah of armies. The City of Tearing Down will one city be called.

19 In that day there will prove to be an altar to Jehovah in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar to Jehovah beside its boundary. 20 And it must prove to be for a sign and for a witness to Jehovah of armies in the land of Egypt; for they will cry out to Jehovah because of the oppressors, and he will send them a savior, even a grand one, who will actually deliver them. 21 And Jehovah will certainly become known to the Egyptians; and the Egyptians must know Jehovah in that day, and they must render sacrifice and gift and must make a vow to Jehovah and pay it. 22 And Jehovah will certainly deal Egypt a blow. There will be a dealing of a blow and a healing; and they must return to Jehovah, and he must let himself be entreated by them and must heal them.

23 In that day there will come to be a highway out of Egypt to As·syr′i·a, and As·syr′i·a will actually come into Egypt, and Egypt into As·syr′i·a; and they will certainly render service, Egypt with As·syr′i·a. 24 In that day Israel will come to be the third with Egypt and with As·syr′i·a, namely, a blessing in the midst of the earth, 25 because Jehovah of armies will have blessed it, saying: “Blessed be my people, Egypt, and the work of my hands, As·syr′i·a, and my inheritance, Israel.”

Isaiah

23 The pronouncement of Tyre: Howl, YOU ships of Tar′shish! for it has been despoiled from being a port, from being a place to enter in. From the land of Kit′tim it has been revealed to them. 2 Be silent, YOU inhabitants of the coastland. The merchants from Si′don, the ones crossing over the sea—they have filled you. 3 And on many waters has been the seed of Shi′hor, the harvest of the Nile, her revenue; and it came to be the profit of the nations.

4 Be ashamed, O Si′don; because the sea, O you stronghold of the sea, has said: “I have not had birth pains, and I have not given birth, nor have I brought up young men, raised up virgins.” 5 Just as at the report pertaining to Egypt, people will likewise be in severe pains at the report on Tyre. 6 Cross over to Tar′shish; howl, YOU inhabitants of the coastland. 7 Is this YOUR city that was exultant from days of long ago, from her early times? Her feet used to bring her far away to reside as an alien.

8 Who is it that has given this counsel against Tyre, the bestower of crowns, whose merchants were princes, whose tradesmen were the honorable ones of the earth?

9 Jehovah of armies himself has given this counsel, to profane the pride of all beauty, to treat with contempt all the honorable ones of the earth.

10 Cross over your land like the Nile River, O daughter of Tar′shish. There is no shipyard any longer. 11 His hand he has stretched out over the sea; he has caused kingdoms to be agitated. Jehovah himself has given a command against Phoe·ni′cia, to annihilate her strongholds. 12 And he says: “You must never again exult, O oppressed one, the virgin daughter of Si′don. Get up, cross over to Kit′tim itself. Even there it will not be restful for you.”

13 Look! The land of the Chal·de′ans. This is the people—As·syr′i·a did not prove to be the one—they founded her for the desert haunters. They have erected their siege towers; they have stripped bare her dwelling towers; one has set her as a crumbling ruin.

14 Howl, YOU ships of Tar′shish, for YOUR stronghold has been despoiled.

15 And it must occur in that day that Tyre must be forgotten seventy years, the same as the days of one king. At the end of seventy years it will happen to Tyre as in the song of a prostitute: 16 “Take a harp, go around the city, O forgotten prostitute. Do your best at playing on the strings; make your songs many, in order that you may be remembered.”

17 And it must occur at the end of seventy years that Jehovah will turn his attention to Tyre, and she must return to her hire and commit prostitution with all the kingdoms of the earth upon the surface of the ground. 18 And her profit and her hire must become something holy to Jehovah. It will not be stored up, nor be laid up, because her hire will come to be for those dwelling before Jehovah, for eating to satisfaction and for elegant covering.

Isaiah

26 In that day this song will be sung in the land of Judah: “We have a strong city. He sets salvation itself for walls and rampart. 2 Open the gates, YOU men, that the righteous nation that is keeping faithful conduct may enter. 3 The inclination that is well supported you will safeguard in continuous peace, because it is in you that one is made to trust. 4 Trust in Jehovah, YOU people, for all times, for in Jah Jehovah is the Rock of times indefinite.

5 “For he has laid low those inhabiting the height, the elevated town. He abases it, he abases it to the earth; he brings it in touch with the dust. 6 The foot will trample it down, the feet of the afflicted one, the steps of the lowly ones.”

7 The path of the righteous one is uprightness. You being upright, you will smooth out the very course of a righteous one. 8 Yes, for the path of your judgments, O Jehovah, we have hoped in you. For your name and for your memorial the desire of the soul has been. 9 With my soul I have desired you in the night; yes, with my spirit within me I keep looking for you; because, when there are judgments from you for the earth, righteousness is what the inhabitants of the productive land will certainly learn. 10 Though the wicked one should be shown favor, he simply will not learn righteousness. In the land of straightforwardness he will act unjustly and will not see the eminence of Jehovah.

11 O Jehovah, your hand has become high, but they do not behold it. They will behold and be ashamed at the zeal for your people. Yes, the very fire for your own adversaries will eat them up. 12 O Jehovah, you will adjudge peace to us, because even all our works you have performed for us. 13 O Jehovah our God, other masters besides you have acted as owners of us. By you only shall we make mention of your name. 14 They are dead; they will not live. Impotent in death, they will not rise up. Therefore you have turned your attention that you might annihilate them and destroy all mention of them.

15 You have added to the nation; O Jehovah, you have added to the nation; you have glorified yourself. You have extended afar all the borders of the land. 16 O Jehovah, during distress they have turned their attention to you; they have poured out a whisper of prayer when they had your disciplining. 17 Just as a pregnant woman draws near to giving birth, has labor pains, cries out in her birth pangs, so we have become because of you, O Jehovah. 18 We have become pregnant, we have had labor pains; as it were, we have given birth to wind. No real salvation do we accomplish as regards the land, and no inhabitants for the productive land proceed to fall in birth.

19 “Your dead ones will live. A corpse of mine—they will rise up. Awake and cry out joyfully, YOU residents in the dust! For your dew is as the dew of mallows, and the earth itself will let even those impotent in death drop in birth.

20 “Go, my people, enter into your interior rooms, and shut your doors behind you. Hide yourself for but a moment until the denunciation passes over. 21 For, look! Jehovah is coming forth from his place to call to account the error of the inhabitant of the land against him, and the land will certainly expose her bloodshed and will no longer cover over her killed ones.”

Isaiah

29 “Woe to Ar′i·el, to Ar′i·el, the town where David encamped! Add year upon year, YOU people; let the festivals run the round. 2 And I have to make things tight for Ar′i·el, and there must come to be mourning and lamentation, and she must become to me as the altar hearth of God. 3 And I must encamp on all sides against you, and I must lay siege to you with a palisade and raise up against you siegeworks. 4 And you must become low so that you will speak from the very earth, and as from the dust your saying will sound low. And like a spirit medium your voice must become even from the earth, and from the dust your own saying will chirp. 5 And the crowd of those strange to you must become just like fine powder, and the crowd of the tyrants just like the chaff that is passing away. And it must occur in an instant, suddenly. 6 From Jehovah of armies you will have attention with thunder and with quaking and with a great sound, storm wind and tempest, and the flame of a devouring fire.”

7 And it must occur just as in a dream, in a vision of the night, regarding the crowd of all the nations that are waging war against Ar′i·el, even all those waging war against her, and the siege towers against her and those making things tight for her. 8 Yes, it must occur just as when someone hungry dreams and here he is eating, and he actually awakes and his soul is empty; and just as when someone thirsty dreams and here he is drinking, and he actually awakes and here he is tired and his soul is dried out; thus it will occur with the crowd of all the nations that are waging war against Mount Zion.

9 Linger, YOU men, and be amazed; blind yourselves, and be blinded. They have become intoxicated, but not with wine; they have moved unsteadily, but not because of intoxicating liquor.

10 For upon YOU men Jehovah has poured a spirit of deep sleep; and he closes YOUR eyes, the prophets, and he has covered even YOUR heads, the visionaries. 11 And for YOU men the vision of everything becomes like the words of the book that has been sealed up, which they give to someone knowing the writing, saying: “Read this out loud, please,” and he has to say: “I am unable, for it is sealed up”; 12 and the book must be given to someone that does not know writing, somebody saying: “Read this out loud, please,” and he has to say: “I do not know writing at all.”

13 And Jehovah says: “For the reason that this people have come near with their mouth, and they have glorified me merely with their lips, and they have removed their heart itself far away from me, and their fear toward me becomes men’s commandment that is being taught, 14 therefore here I am, the One that will act wonderfully again with this people, in a wonderful manner and with something wonderful; and the wisdom of their wise men must perish, and the very understanding of their discreet men will conceal itself.”

15 Woe to those who are going very deep in concealing counsel from Jehovah himself, and whose deeds have occurred in a dark place, while they say: “Who is seeing us, and who is knowing of us?” 16 The perversity of YOU men! Should the potter himself be accounted just like the clay? For should the thing made say respecting its maker: “He did not make me”? And does the very thing formed actually say respecting its former: “He showed no understanding”?

17 Is it not yet but a very little time and Leb′a·non must be turned into an orchard and the orchard itself will be accounted just as a forest? 18 And in that day the deaf ones will certainly hear the words of the book, and out of the gloom and out of the darkness even the eyes of the blind ones will see. 19 And the meek ones will certainly increase their rejoicing in Jehovah himself, and even the poor ones of mankind will be joyful in the Holy One of Israel himself, 20 because the tyrant must reach his end, and the bragger must come to his finish, and all those keeping alert to do harm must be cut off, 21 those bringing a man into sin by his word, and those who lay bait even for the one reproving in the gate, and those who push aside the righteous one with empty arguments.

22 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said to the house of Jacob, he that redeemed Abraham: “Jacob will not now be ashamed, nor will his own face now grow pale; 23 for when he sees his children, the work of my hands, in the midst of him, they will sanctify my name, and they will certainly sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and the God of Israel they will regard with awe. 24 And those who are erring in their spirit will actually get to know understanding, and even those who are grumbling will learn instruction.”

Isaiah

31 Woe to those going down to Egypt for assistance, those who rely on mere horses, and who put their trust in war chariots, because they are numerous, and in steeds, because they are very mighty, but who have not looked to the Holy One of Israel and have not searched for Jehovah himself. 2 And he is also wise and will bring in what is calamitous, and he has not called back his own words; and he will certainly rise up against the house of evildoers and against the assistance of those practicing what is hurtful.

3 The Egyptians, though, are earthling men, and not God; and their horses are flesh, and not spirit. And Jehovah himself will stretch out his hand, and he that is offering help will have to stumble, and he that is being helped will have to fall, and at the same time they will all of them come to an end.

4 For this is what Jehovah has said to me: “Just as the lion growls, even the maned young lion, over its prey, when there is called out against it a full number of shepherds, and in spite of their voice he will not be terrified and in spite of their commotion he will not stoop; in the same way Jehovah of armies will come down to wage war over Mount Zion and over her hill. 5 Like birds flying, Jehovah of armies will in the same way defend Jerusalem. Defending her, he will also certainly deliver her. Sparing her, he must also cause her to escape.”

6 “Return, YOU people, to the One against whom the sons of Israel have gone deep in their revolt. 7 For in that day they will reject each one his worthless gods of silver and his valueless gods of gold, that YOUR hands have made for yourselves as a sin. 8 And the As·syr′i·an must fall by the sword, not that of a man; and a sword, not that of earthling man, will devour him. And he must flee because of the sword, and his own young men will come to be for forced labor itself. 9 And his own crag will pass away out of sheer fright, and because of the signal his princes must be terrified,” is the utterance of Jehovah, whose light is in Zion and whose furnace is in Jerusalem.

Isaiah

34 Come up close, YOU nations, to hear; and YOU national groups, pay attention. Let the earth and that which fills it listen, the productive land and all its produce. 2 For Jehovah has indignation against all the nations, and rage against all their army. He must devote them to destruction; he must give them to the slaughter. 3 And their slain ones will be thrown out; and as for their carcasses, their stink will ascend; and the mountains must melt because of their blood. 4 And all those of the army of the heavens must rot away. And the heavens must be rolled up, just like a book scroll; and their army will all shrivel away, just as the leafage shrivels off the vine and like a shriveled fig off the fig tree.

5 “For in the heavens my sword will certainly be drenched. Look! Upon E′dom it will descend, and upon the people devoted by me to destruction in justice. 6 Jehovah has a sword; it must be filled with blood; it must be made greasy with the fat, with the blood of young rams and he-goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams. For Jehovah has a sacrifice in Boz′rah, and a great slaughtering in the land of E′dom. 7 And the wild bulls must come down with them, and young bulls with the powerful ones; and their land must be drenched with blood, and their very dust will be made greasy with the fat.”

8 For Jehovah has a day of vengeance, a year of retributions for the legal case over Zion.

9 And her torrents must be changed into pitch, and her dust into sulphur; and her land must become as burning pitch. 10 By night or by day it will not be extinguished; to time indefinite its smoke will keep ascending. From generation to generation she will be parched; forever and ever no one will be passing across her. 11 And the pelican and the porcupine must take possession of her, and long-eared owls and ravens themselves will reside in her; and he must stretch out over her the measuring line of emptiness and the stones of wasteness. 12 Her nobles—there are none there whom they will call to the kingship itself, and her very princes will all become nothing. 13 On her dwelling towers thorns must come up, nettles and thorny weeds in her fortified places; and she must become an abiding place of jackals, the courtyard for the ostriches. 14 And haunters of waterless regions must meet up with howling animals, and even the goat-shaped demon will call to its companion. Yes, there the nightjar will certainly take its ease and find for itself a resting-place. 15 There the arrow snake has made its nest and lays eggs, and it must hatch them and gather them together under its shadow. Yes, there the gledes must collect themselves together, each one with her mate.

16 Search for yourselves in the book of Jehovah and read out loud: not one has been missing of them; they actually do not fail to have each one her mate, for it is the mouth of Jehovah that has given the command, and it is his spirit that has collected them together. 17 And it is He that has cast for them the lot, and his own hand has apportioned the place to them by the measuring line. To time indefinite they will take possession of it; for generation after generation they will reside in it.

Isaiah

35 The wilderness and the waterless region will exult, and the desert plain will be joyful and blossom as the saffron. 2 Without fail it will blossom, and it will really be joyful with joyousness and with glad crying out. The glory of Leb′a·non itself must be given to it, the splendor of Car′mel and of Shar′on. There will be those who will see the glory of Jehovah, the splendor of our God.

3 Strengthen the weak hands, YOU people, and make the knees that are wobbling firm. 4 Say to those who are anxious at heart: “Be strong. Do not be afraid. Look! YOUR own God will come with vengeance itself, God even with a repayment. He himself will come and save YOU people.”

5 At that time the eyes of the blind ones will be opened, and the very ears of the deaf ones will be unstopped. 6 At that time the lame one will climb up just as a stag does, and the tongue of the speechless one will cry out in gladness. For in the wilderness waters will have burst out, and torrents in the desert plain. 7 And the heat-parched ground will have become as a reedy pool, and the thirsty ground as springs of water. In the abiding place of jackals, a resting-place for them, there will be green grass with reeds and papyrus plants.

8 And there will certainly come to be a highway there, even a way; and the Way of Holiness it will be called. The unclean one will not pass over it. And it will be for the one walking on the way, and no foolish ones will wander about on it. 9 No lion will prove to be there, and the rapacious sort of wild beasts will not come up on it. None will be found there; and the repurchased ones must walk there. 10 And the very ones redeemed by Jehovah will return and certainly come to Zion with a joyful cry; and rejoicing to time indefinite will be upon their head. To exultation and rejoicing they will attain, and grief and sighing must flee away.

Isaiah

42 Look! My servant, on whom I keep fast hold! My chosen one, whom my soul has approved! I have put my spirit in him. Justice to the nations is what he will bring forth. 2 He will not cry out or raise his voice, and in the street he will not let his voice be heard. 3 No crushed reed will he break; and as for a dim flaxen wick, he will not extinguish it. In trueness he will bring forth justice. 4 He will not grow dim nor be crushed until he sets justice in the earth itself; and for his law the islands themselves will keep waiting.

5 This is what the true God, Jehovah, has said, the Creator of the heavens and the Grand One stretching them out; the One laying out the earth and its produce, the One giving breath to the people on it, and spirit to those walking in it: 6 “I myself, Jehovah, have called you in righteousness, and I proceeded to take hold of your hand. And I shall safeguard you and give you as a covenant of the people, as a light of the nations, 7 for you to open the blind eyes, to bring forth out of the dungeon the prisoner, out of the house of detention those sitting in darkness.

8 “I am Jehovah. That is my name; and to no one else shall I give my own glory, neither my praise to graven images.

9 “The first things—here they have come, but new things I am telling out. Before they begin to spring up, I cause YOU people to hear them.”

10 Sing to Jehovah a new song, his praise from the extremity of the earth, YOU men that are going down to the sea and to that which fills it, YOU islands and YOU inhabiting them. 11 Let the wilderness and its cities raise their voice, the settlements that Ke′dar inhabits. Let the inhabitants of the crag cry out in joy. From the top of the mountains let people cry aloud. 12 Let them attribute to Jehovah glory, and in the islands let them tell forth even his praise.

13 Like a mighty man Jehovah himself will go forth. Like a warrior he will awaken zeal. He will shout, yes, he will let out a war cry; over his enemies he will show himself mightier.

14 “I have kept quiet for a long time. I continued silent. I kept exercising self-control. Like a woman giving birth I am going to groan, pant, and gasp at the same time. 15 I shall devastate mountains and hills, and all their vegetation I shall dry up. And I will turn rivers into islands, and reedy pools I shall dry up. 16 And I will make the blind ones walk in a way that they have not known; in a roadway that they have not known I shall cause them to tread. I shall turn a dark place before them into light, and rugged terrain into level land. These are the things that I will do for them, and I will not leave them.”

17 They must be turned back, they will be very much ashamed, those who are putting trust in the carved image, those who are saying to a molten image: “YOU are our gods.”

18 Hear, YOU deaf ones; and look forth to see, YOU blind ones. 19 Who is blind, if not my servant, and who is deaf as my messenger whom I send? Who is blind as the one rewarded, or blind as the servant of Jehovah? 20 It was a case of seeing many things, but you did not keep watching. It was a case of opening the ears, but you did not keep listening. 21 Jehovah himself for the sake of his righteousness has taken a delight in that he should magnify the law and make it majestic. 22 But it is a people plundered and pillaged, all of them being trapped in the holes, and in the houses of detention they have been kept hidden. They have come to be for plunder without a deliverer, for pillage without anyone to say: “Bring back!”

23 Who among YOU people will give ear to this? Who will pay attention and listen for later times? 24 Who has given Jacob for mere pillage, and Israel to the plunderers? Is it not Jehovah, the One against whom we have sinned, and in whose ways they did not want to walk and to whose law they did not listen? 25 So He kept pouring out upon him rage, his anger, and the strength of war. And it kept consuming him all around, but he took no note; and it kept blazing up against him, but he would lay nothing to heart.

Isaiah

47 Come down and sit down in the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon. Sit down on the earth where there is no throne, O daughter of the Chal·de′ans. For you will not experience again that people call you delicate and dainty. 2 Take a hand mill and grind out flour. Uncover your veil. Strip off the flowing skirt. Uncover the leg. Cross over the rivers. 3 You ought to uncover your nakedness. Also, your reproach ought to be seen. Vengeance is what I shall take, and I shall not meet any man kindly.

4 “There is One repurchasing us. Jehovah of armies is his name, the Holy One of Israel.”

5 Sit down silently and come into the darkness, O daughter of the Chal·de′ans; for you will not experience again that people call you Mistress of Kingdoms. 6 I grew indignant at my people. I profaned my inheritance, and I proceeded to give them into your hand. You showed them no mercies. Upon the old man you made your yoke very heavy. 7 And you kept saying: “To time indefinite I shall prove to be Mistress, forever.” You did not take these things to your heart; you did not remember the finale of the matter.

8 And now hear this, you pleasure-given woman, the one sitting in security, the one saying in her heart: “I am, and there is nobody else. I shall not sit as a widow, and I shall not know the loss of children.” 9 But to you these two things will come suddenly, in one day: loss of children and widowhood. In their complete measure they must come upon you, for the abundance of your sorceries, for the full might of your spells—exceedingly. 10 And you kept trusting in your badness. You have said: “There is no one seeing me.” Your wisdom and your knowledge—this is what has led you away; and you keep saying in your heart: “I am, and there is nobody else.” 11 And upon you calamity must come; you will know no charming against it. And upon you adversity will fall; you will not be able to avert it. And upon you there will suddenly come a ruin that you are not accustomed to know.

12 Stand still, now, with your spells and with the abundance of your sorceries, in which you have toiled from your youth; that perhaps you might be able to benefit, that perhaps you might strike people with awe. 13 You have grown weary with the multitude of your counselors. Let them stand up, now, and save you, the worshipers of the heavens, the lookers at the stars, those giving out knowledge at the new moons concerning the things that will come upon you. 14 Look! They have become like stubble. A fire itself will certainly burn them up. They will not deliver their soul from the power of the flame. There will be no glow of charcoals for people to warm themselves, no firelight in front of which to sit down. 15 Thus they will certainly become to you, with whom you have toiled as your charmers from your youth. They will actually wander, each one to his own region. There will be no one to save you.

Isaiah

51 “Listen to me, YOU people who are pursuing after righteousness, YOU who are seeking to find Jehovah. Look to the rock from which YOU were hewn out, and to the hollow of the pit from which YOU were dug out. 2 Look to Abraham YOUR father and to Sarah who gradually brought YOU forth with childbirth pains. For he was one when I called him, and I proceeded to bless him and to make him many. 3 For Jehovah will certainly comfort Zion. He will for certain comfort all her devastated places, and he will make her wilderness like E′den and her desert plain like the garden of Jehovah. Exultation and rejoicing themselves will be found in her, thanksgiving and the voice of melody.

4 “Pay attention to me, O my people; and you national group of mine, to me give ear. For from me a law itself will go forth, and my judicial decision I shall cause to repose even as a light to the peoples. 5 My righteousness is near. My salvation will certainly go forth, and my own arms will judge even the peoples. In me the islands themselves will hope, and for my arm they will wait.

6 “Raise YOUR eyes to the heavens themselves, and look at the earth beneath. For the very heavens must be dispersed in fragments just like smoke, and like a garment the earth itself will wear out, and its inhabitants themselves will die like a mere gnat. But as for my salvation, it will prove to be even to time indefinite, and my own righteousness will not be shattered.

7 “Listen to me, YOU the ones knowing righteousness, the people in whose heart is my law. Do not be afraid of the reproach of mortal men, and do not be struck with terror just because of their abusive words. 8 For the moth will eat them up just as if a garment, and the clothes moth will eat them up just as if wool. But as for my righteousness, it will prove to be even to time indefinite, and my salvation to unnumbered generations.”

9 Awake, awake, clothe yourself with strength, O arm of Jehovah! Awake as in the days of long ago, as during the generations of times long past. Are you not the one that broke Ra′hab to pieces, that pierced the sea monster? 10 Are you not the one that dried up the sea, the waters of the vast deep? The one that made the depths of the sea a way for the repurchased ones to go across? 11 Then the redeemed ones of Jehovah themselves will return and must come to Zion with a joyful outcry, and rejoicing to time indefinite will be upon their head. To exultation and rejoicing they will attain. Grief and sighing will certainly flee away.

12 “I—I myself am the One that is comforting YOU people.

“Who are you that you should be afraid of a mortal man that will die, and of a son of mankind that will be rendered as mere green grass? 13 And that you should forget Jehovah your Maker, the One stretching out the heavens and laying the foundation of the earth, so that you were in dread constantly the whole day long on account of the rage of the one hemming you in, as though he was all set to bring you to ruin? And where is the rage of the one hemming you in?

14 “The one stooping in chains will certainly be loosened speedily, that he may not go in death to the pit and that his bread may not be lacking.

15 “But I, Jehovah, am your God, the One stirring up the sea that its waves may be boisterous. Jehovah of armies is his name. 16 And I shall put my words in your mouth, and with the shadow of my hand I shall certainly cover you, in order to plant the heavens and lay the foundation of the earth and say to Zion, ‘You are my people.’

17 “Rouse yourself, rouse yourself, rise up, O Jerusalem, you who have drunk at the hand of Jehovah his cup of rage. The goblet, the cup causing reeling, you have drunk, you have drained out. 18 There was none of all the sons that she brought to birth conducting her, and there was none of all the sons that she brought up taking hold of her hand. 19 Those two things were befalling you. Who will sympathize with you? Despoiling and breakdown, and hunger and sword! Who will comfort you? 20 Your own sons have swooned away. They have lain down at the head of all the streets like the wild sheep in the net, as those who are full of the rage of Jehovah, the rebuke of your God.”

21 Therefore listen to this, please, O woman afflicted and drunk, but not with wine. 22 This is what your Lord, Jehovah, even your God, who contends for his people, has said: “Look! I will take away from your hand the cup causing reeling. The goblet, my cup of rage—you will not repeat the drinking of it anymore. 23 And I will put it in the hand of the ones irritating you, who have said to your soul, ‘Bow down that we may cross over,’ so that you used to make your back just like the earth, and like the street for those crossing over.”

Isaiah

53 Who has put faith in the thing heard by us? And as for the arm of Jehovah, to whom has it been revealed? 2 And he will come up like a twig before one, and like a root out of waterless land. No stately form does he have, nor any splendor; and when we shall see him, there is not the appearance so that we should desire him.

3 He was despised and was avoided by men, a man meant for pains and for having acquaintance with sickness. And there was as if the concealing of one’s face from us. He was despised, and we held him as of no account. 4 Truly our sicknesses were what he himself carried; and as for our pains, he bore them. But we ourselves accounted him as plagued, stricken by God and afflicted. 5 But he was being pierced for our transgression; he was being crushed for our errors. The chastisement meant for our peace was upon him, and because of his wounds there has been a healing for us. 6 Like sheep we have all of us wandered about; it was each one to his own way that we have turned; and Jehovah himself has caused the error of us all to meet up with that one. 7 He was hard pressed, and he was letting himself be afflicted; yet he would not open his mouth. He was being brought just like a sheep to the slaughtering; and like a ewe that before her shearers has become mute, he also would not open his mouth.

8 Because of restraint and of judgment he was taken away; and who will concern himself even with the details of his generation? For he was severed from the land of the living ones. Because of the transgression of my people he had the stroke. 9 And he will make his burial place even with the wicked ones, and with the rich class in his death, despite the fact that he had done no violence and there was no deception in his mouth.

10 But Jehovah himself took delight in crushing him; he made him sick. If you will set his soul as a guilt offering, he will see his offspring, he will prolong his days, and in his hand what is the delight of Jehovah will succeed. 11 Because of the trouble of his soul he will see, he will be satisfied. By means of his knowledge the righteous one, my servant, will bring a righteous standing to many people; and their errors he himself will bear. 12 For that reason I shall deal him a portion among the many, and it will be with the mighty ones that he will apportion the spoil, due to the fact that he poured out his soul to the very death, and it was with the transgressors that he was counted in; and he himself carried the very sin of many people, and for the transgressors he proceeded to interpose.

Isaiah

54 “Cry out joyfully, you barren woman that did not give birth! Become cheerful with a joyful outcry and cry shrilly, you that had no childbirth pains, for the sons of the desolated one are more numerous than the sons of the woman with a husbandly owner,” Jehovah has said. 2 “Make the place of your tent more spacious. And let them stretch out the tent cloths of your grand tabernacle. Do not hold back. Lengthen out your tent cords, and make those tent pins of yours strong. 3 For to the right and to the left you will break forth, and your own offspring will take possession even of nations, and they will inhabit even the desolated cities. 4 Do not be afraid, for you will not be put to shame; and do not feel humiliated, for you will not be disappointed. For you will forget even the shame of your time of youth, and the reproach of your continuous widowhood you will remember no more.”

5 “For your Grand Maker is your husbandly owner, Jehovah of armies being his name; and the Holy One of Israel is your Repurchaser. The God of the whole earth he will be called. 6 For Jehovah called you as if you were a wife left entirely and hurt in spirit, and as a wife of the time of youth who was then rejected,” your God has said.

7 “For a little moment I left you entirely, but with great mercies I shall collect you together. 8 With a flood of indignation I concealed my face from you for but a moment, but with loving-kindness to time indefinite I will have mercy upon you,” your Repurchaser, Jehovah, has said.

9 “This is just as the days of Noah to me. Just as I have sworn that the waters of Noah shall no more pass over the earth, so I have sworn that I will not become indignant toward you nor rebuke you. 10 For the mountains themselves may be removed, and the very hills may stagger, but my loving-kindness itself will not be removed from you, nor will my covenant of peace itself stagger,” Jehovah, the One having mercy upon you, has said.

11 “O woman afflicted, tempest-tossed, uncomforted, here I am laying with hard mortar your stones, and I will lay your foundation with sapphires. 12 And I will make your battlements of rubies, and your gates of fiery glowing stones, and all your boundaries of delightsome stones. 13 And all your sons will be persons taught by Jehovah, and the peace of your sons will be abundant. 14 You will prove to be firmly established in righteousness itself. You will be far away from oppression—for you will fear none—and from anything terrifying, for it will not come near you. 15 If anyone should at all make an attack, it will not be at my orders. Whoever is making an attack upon you will fall even on account of you.”

16 “Look! I myself have created the craftsman, the one blowing upon the fire of charcoal and bringing forth a weapon as his workmanship. I myself, too, have created the ruinous man for wrecking work. 17 Any weapon whatever that will be formed against you will have no success, and any tongue at all that will rise up against you in the judgment you will condemn. This is the hereditary possession of the servants of Jehovah, and their righteousness is from me,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

Isaiah

55 Hey there, all YOU thirsty ones! Come to the water. And the ones that have no money! Come, buy and eat. Yes, come, buy wine and milk even without money and without price. 2 Why do YOU people keep paying out money for what is not bread, and why is YOUR toil for what results in no satisfaction? Listen intently to me, and eat what is good, and let YOUR soul find its exquisite delight in fatness itself. 3 Incline YOUR ear and come to me. Listen, and YOUR soul will keep alive, and I shall readily conclude with YOU people an indefinitely lasting covenant respecting the loving-kindnesses to David that are faithful. 4 Look! As a witness to the national groups I have given him, as a leader and commander to the national groups.

5 Look! A nation that you do not know you will call, and those of a nation who have not known you will run even to you, for the sake of Jehovah your God, and for the Holy One of Israel, because he will have beautified you.

6 Search for Jehovah, YOU people, while he may be found. Call to him while he proves to be near. 7 Let the wicked man leave his way, and the harmful man his thoughts; and let him return to Jehovah, who will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will forgive in a large way.

8 “For the thoughts of YOU people are not my thoughts, nor are my ways YOUR ways,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 9 “For as the heavens are higher than the earth, so my ways are higher than YOUR ways, and my thoughts than YOUR thoughts. 10 For just as the pouring rain descends, and the snow, from the heavens and does not return to that place, unless it actually saturates the earth and makes it produce and sprout, and seed is actually given to the sower and bread to the eater, 11 so my word that goes forth from my mouth will prove to be. It will not return to me without results, but it will certainly do that in which I have delighted, and it will have certain success in that for which I have sent it.

12 “For with rejoicing YOU people will go forth, and with peace YOU will be brought in. The mountains and the hills themselves will become cheerful before YOU with a joyful outcry, and the very trees of the field will all clap their hands. 13 Instead of the thicket of thorns the juniper tree will come up. Instead of the stinging nettle the myrtle tree will come up. And it must become for Jehovah something famous, a sign to time indefinite that will not be cut off.”

Isaiah

56 This is what Jehovah has said: “Keep justice, YOU people, and do what is righteous. For my salvation is at hand to come in, and my righteousness to be revealed. 2 Happy is the mortal man that does this, and the son of mankind that lays hold of it, keeping the sabbath in order not to profane it, and keeping his hand in order not to do any kind of badness. 3 And let not the foreigner that has joined himself to Jehovah say, ‘Without doubt Jehovah will divide me off from his people.’ Neither let the eunuch say, ‘Look! I am a dry tree.’”

4 For this is what Jehovah has said to the eunuchs that keep my sabbaths and that have chosen what I have delighted in and that are laying hold of my covenant: 5 “I will even give to them in my house and within my walls a monument and a name, something better than sons and daughters. A name to time indefinite I shall give them, one that will not be cut off.

6 “And the foreigners that have joined themselves to Jehovah to minister to him and to love the name of Jehovah, in order to become servants to him, all those keeping the sabbath in order not to profane it and laying hold of my covenant, 7 I will also bring them to my holy mountain and make them rejoice inside my house of prayer. Their whole burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be for acceptance upon my altar. For my own house will be called even a house of prayer for all the peoples.”

8 The utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, who is collecting together the dispersed ones of Israel, is: “I shall collect together to him others besides those already collected together of his.”

9 All YOU wild animals of the open field, come to eat, all YOU wild animals in the forest. 10 His watchmen are blind. None of them have taken note. All of them are speechless dogs; they are not able to bark, panting, lying down, loving to slumber. 11 They are even dogs strong in soulful desire; they have known no satisfaction. They are also shepherds that have not known how to understand. They have all of them turned to their own way, each one for his unjust gain from his own border: 12 “Come, men! Let me take some wine; and let us drink intoxicating liquor to the limit. And tomorrow will certainly turn out just as today, great in a very much larger way.”

Isaiah

60 “Arise, O woman, shed forth light, for your light has come and upon you the very glory of Jehovah has shone forth. 2 For, look! darkness itself will cover the earth, and thick gloom the national groups; but upon you Jehovah will shine forth, and upon you his own glory will be seen. 3 And nations will certainly go to your light, and kings to the brightness of your shining forth.

4 “Raise your eyes all around and see! They have all of them been collected together; they have come to you. From far away your own sons keep coming, and your daughters who will be taken care of on the flank. 5 At that time you will see and certainly become radiant, and your heart will actually quiver and expand, because to you the wealthiness of the sea will direct itself; the very resources of the nations will come to you. 6 The heaving mass of camels itself will cover you, the young male camels of Mid′i·an and of E′phah. All those from She′ba—they will come. Gold and frankincense they will carry. And the praises of Jehovah they will announce. 7 All the flocks of Ke′dar—they will be collected together to you. The rams of Ne·ba′ioth—they will minister to you. With approval they will come up upon my altar, and I shall beautify my own house of beauty.

8 “Who are these that come flying just like a cloud, and like doves to their birdhouse holes? 9 For in me the islands themselves will keep hoping, the ships of Tar′shish also as at the first, in order to bring your sons from far away, their silver and their gold being with them, to the name of Jehovah your God and to the Holy One of Israel, for he will have beautified you. 10 And foreigners will actually build your walls, and their own kings will minister to you; for in my indignation I shall have struck you, but in my goodwill I shall certainly have mercy upon you.

11 “And your gates will actually be kept open constantly; they will not be closed even by day or by night, in order to bring to you the resources of the nations, and their kings will be taking the lead. 12 For any nation and any kingdom that will not serve you will perish; and the nations themselves will without fail come to devastation.

13 “To you the very glory of Leb′a·non will come, the juniper tree, the ash tree and the cypress at the same time, in order to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I shall glorify the very place of my feet.

14 “And to you the sons of those afflicting you must go, bowing down; and all those treating you disrespectfully must bend down at the very soles of your feet, and they will have to call you the city of Jehovah, Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

15 “Instead of your proving to be one left entirely and hated, with nobody passing through, I will even set you as a thing of pride to time indefinite, an exultation for generation after generation. 16 And you will actually suck the milk of nations, and the breast of kings you will suck; and you will be certain to know that I, Jehovah, am your Savior, and the Powerful One of Jacob is your Repurchaser. 17 Instead of the copper I shall bring in gold, and instead of the iron I shall bring in silver, and instead of the wood, copper, and instead of the stones, iron; and I will appoint peace as your overseers and righteousness as your task assigners.

18 “No more will violence be heard in your land, despoiling or breakdown within your boundaries. And you will certainly call your own walls Salvation and your gates Praise. 19 For you the sun will no more prove to be a light by day, and for brightness the moon itself will no more give you light. And Jehovah must become to you an indefinitely lasting light, and your God your beauty. 20 No more will your sun set, nor will your moon go on the wane; for Jehovah himself will become for you an indefinitely lasting light, and the days of your mourning will have come to completion. 21 And as for your people, all of them will be righteous; to time indefinite they will hold possession of the land, the sprout of my planting, the work of my hands, for me to be beautified. 22 The little one himself will become a thousand, and the small one a mighty nation. I myself, Jehovah, shall speed it up in its own time.”

Isaiah

65 “I have let myself be searched for by those who had not asked for me. I have let myself be found by those who had not looked for me. I have said, ‘Here I am, here I am!’ to a nation that was not calling upon my name.

2 “I have spread out my hands all day long to a stubborn people, those who are walking in the way that is not good, after their thoughts; 3 the people made up of those offending me right to my face constantly, sacrificing in the gardens and making sacrificial smoke upon the bricks, 4 seating themselves among the burial places, who also pass the night even in the watch huts, eating the flesh of the pig, even the broth of foul things being in their vessels; 5 those who are saying, ‘Keep close to yourself. Do not approach me, for I shall certainly convey holiness to you.’ These are a smoke in my nostrils, a fire burning all day long.

6 “Look! It is written before me. I shall not keep still, but I will render a reward; I will even render the reward into their own bosom, 7 for their own errors and for the errors of their forefathers at the same time,” Jehovah has said. “Because they have made sacrificial smoke upon the mountains, and upon the hills they have reproached me, I will also measure out their wages first of all into their own bosom.”

8 This is what Jehovah has said: “In the same way that the new wine is found in the cluster and someone has to say, ‘Do not ruin it, because there is a blessing in it,’ so I shall do for the sake of my servants in order not to bring everybody to ruin. 9 And I will bring forth out of Jacob an offspring and out of Judah the hereditary possessor of my mountains; and my chosen ones must take possession of it, and my own servants will reside there. 10 And Shar′on must become a pasture ground for sheep and the low plain of A′chor a resting-place for cattle, for my people who will have looked for me.

11 “But YOU men are those leaving Jehovah, those forgetting my holy mountain, those setting in order a table for the god of Good Luck and those filling up mixed wine for the god of Destiny. 12 And I will destine YOU men to the sword, and YOU will all of YOU bow down to being slaughtered; for the reason that I called, but YOU did not answer; I spoke, but YOU did not listen; and YOU kept doing what was bad in my eyes, and the thing in which I took no delight YOU chose.”

13 Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Look! My own servants will eat, but YOU yourselves will go hungry. Look! My own servants will drink, but YOU yourselves will go thirsty. Look! My own servants will rejoice, but YOU yourselves will suffer shame. 14 Look! My own servants will cry out joyfully because of the good condition of the heart, but YOU yourselves will make outcries because of the pain of heart and YOU will howl because of sheer breakdown of spirit. 15 And YOU men will certainly lay up YOUR name for an oath by my chosen ones, and the Sovereign Lord Jehovah will actually put YOU individually to death, but his own servants he will call by another name; 16 so that anyone blessing himself in the earth will bless himself by the God of faith, and anyone making a sworn statement in the earth will swear by the God of faith; because the former distresses will actually be forgotten and because they will actually be concealed from my eyes.

17 “For here I am creating new heavens and a new earth; and the former things will not be called to mind, neither will they come up into the heart. 18 But exult, YOU people, and be joyful forever in what I am creating. For here I am creating Jerusalem a cause for joyfulness and her people a cause for exultation. 19 And I will be joyful in Jerusalem and exult in my people; and no more will there be heard in her the sound of weeping or the sound of a plaintive cry.”

20 “No more will there come to be a suckling a few days old from that place, neither an old man that does not fulfill his days; for one will die as a mere boy, although a hundred years of age; and as for the sinner, although a hundred years of age he will have evil called down upon him. 21 And they will certainly build houses and have occupancy; and they will certainly plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 22 They will not build and someone else have occupancy; they will not plant and someone else do the eating. For like the days of a tree will the days of my people be; and the work of their own hands my chosen ones will use to the full. 23 They will not toil for nothing, nor will they bring to birth for disturbance; because they are the offspring made up of the blessed ones of Jehovah, and their descendants with them. 24 And it will actually occur that before they call out I myself shall answer; while they are yet speaking, I myself shall hear.

25 “The wolf and the lamb themselves will feed as one, and the lion will eat straw just like the bull; and as for the serpent, his food will be dust. They will do no harm nor cause any ruin in all my holy mountain,” Jehovah has said.

Jeremiah

14 This is what occurred as the word of Jehovah to Jeremiah concerning the matters of the droughts: 2 Judah has gone mourning, and its very gates have faded away. They have become dejected to the earth, and even the outcry of Jerusalem has gone up. 3 And their majestic ones themselves have sent their insignificant ones for water. They have come to the ditches. They have found no water. They have returned with their vessels empty. They have been put to shame and have been disappointed, and they have covered their head. 4 On account of the soil that has been shattered because there has occurred no downpour upon the land, the farmers have become ashamed; they have covered their head. 5 For even the hind in the field has given birth, but leaving it, because there proved to be no tender grass. 6 And the zebras themselves have stood still upon the bare hills; they have snuffed up the wind like the jackals; their eyes have failed because there is no vegetation. 7 Even if our own errors do testify against us, O Jehovah, act for the sake of your name; for our acts of unfaithfulness have become many; it is against you that we have sinned.

8 O you the hope of Israel, the Savior of him in the time of distress, why do you become like an alien resident in the land, and like a traveler that has turned aside to spend the night? 9 Why do you become like a man astounded, like a mighty man that is unable to do any saving? Yet you yourself are in the midst of us, O Jehovah, and upon us it is that your own name has been called. Do not let us down.

10 This is what Jehovah has said concerning this people: “Thus they have loved to wander about; their feet they have not kept in check. So Jehovah himself has taken no pleasure in them. Now he will remember their error and will give attention to their sins.”

11 And Jehovah proceeded to say to me: “Do not pray in behalf of this people for any good. 12 When they fast, I am not listening to their entreating cry; and when they offer up the whole burnt offering and the grain offering, I am taking no pleasure in them; for by the sword and by famine and by pestilence I am bringing them to their end.”

13 At this I said: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Here the prophets are saying to them, ‘YOU will see no sword, and there will be no famine to happen to YOU, but true peace is what I shall give YOU in this place.’”

14 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Falsehood is what the prophets are prophesying in my name. I have not sent them, nor have I commanded them or spoken to them. A false vision and divination and a valueless thing and the trickiness of their heart they are speaking prophetically to YOU people. 15 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said concerning the prophets who are prophesying in my name and whom I myself did not send and who are saying that no sword or famine will occur in this land, ‘By sword and by famine those prophets will come to their finish. 16 And the very people to whom they are prophesying will become people cast out into the streets of Jerusalem because of the famine and the sword, with no one to do the burying of them—them, their wives and their sons and their daughters. And I will pour out upon them their calamity.’

17 “And you must say to them this word, ‘Let my eyes run down with tears night and day and let them not keep still, for with a great crash the virgin daughter of my people has been broken, with an extremely sickish stroke. 18 If I actually go out into the field, look, now, those slain by the sword! And if I actually come into the city, look, also, the maladies from the famine! For both the prophet and the priest themselves have gone around to a land that they have not known.’”

19 Have you absolutely rejected Judah, or has your soul abhorred even Zion? Why is it that you have struck us, so that there is no healing for us? There was a hoping for peace, but no good came; and for a time of healing, and, look! terror! 20 We do acknowledge, O Jehovah, our wickedness, the error of our forefathers, for we have sinned against you. 21 Do not disrespect us for the sake of your name; do not despise your glorious throne. Remember; do not break your covenant with us. 22 Do there exist among the vain idols of the nations any that can pour down rain, or can even the heavens themselves give copious showers? Are you not the One, O Jehovah our God? And we hope in you, for you yourself have done all these things.

Jeremiah

17 “The sin of Judah is written down with an iron stylus. With a diamond point it is engraved on the tablet of their heart, and on the horns of their altars, 2 when their sons remember their altars and their sacred poles beside a luxuriant tree, upon the high hills, 3 on the mountains in the field. Your resources, all your treasures, I shall give for mere plunder—your high places because of sin throughout all your territories. 4 And you let loose, even of your own accord, from your hereditary possession that I had given you. I also will make you serve your enemies in the land that you have not known; for as a fire YOU people have been ignited in my anger. To time indefinite it will keep kindled.”

5 This is what Jehovah has said: “Cursed is the able-bodied man who puts his trust in earthling man and actually makes flesh his arm, and whose heart turns away from Jehovah himself. 6 And he will certainly become like a solitary tree in the desert plain and will not see when good comes; but he must reside in parched places in the wilderness, in a salt country that is not inhabited. 7 Blessed is the able-bodied man who puts his trust in Jehovah, and whose confidence Jehovah has become. 8 And he will certainly become like a tree planted by the waters, that sends out its roots right by the watercourse; and he will not see when heat comes, but his foliage will actually prove to be luxuriant. And in the year of drought he will not become anxious, nor will he leave off from producing fruit.

9 “The heart is more treacherous than anything else and is desperate. Who can know it? 10 I, Jehovah, am searching the heart, examining the kidneys, even to give to each one according to his ways, according to the fruitage of his dealings. 11 As the partridge that has gathered together what it has not laid is the one making riches, but not with justice. At the half of his days he will leave them, and in his finale he will prove to be senseless.”

12 There is the glorious throne on high from the start; it is the place of our sanctuary. 13 O Jehovah, the hope of Israel, all those who are leaving you will be put to shame. Those apostatizing from me will be written down even in the earth, because they have left the source of living water, Jehovah. 14 Heal me, O Jehovah, and I shall be healed. Save me, and I will be saved; for you are my praise.

15 Look! There are those saying to me: “Where is the word of Jehovah? Let it come in, please.” 16 But as for me, I did not hasten from being a shepherd following you, and for the desperate day I did not show any craving. You yourself have known the expression of my lips; in front of your face it has occurred. 17 Do not become something terrifying to me. You are my refuge in the day of calamity. 18 Let my persecutors be put to shame, but let me personally be put to no shame. Let them be the ones to be struck with terror, but let me personally not be struck with terror. Bring upon them the day of calamity, and break them even with twice as much breakdown.

19 This is what Jehovah has said to me: “Go, and you must stand in the gate of the sons of the people by which the kings of Judah enter in and by which they go out, and in all the gates of Jerusalem. 20 And you must say to them, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, YOU kings of Judah and all Judah and all YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem, who are entering in by these gates. 21 This is what Jehovah has said: “Watch out for YOUR souls, and do not carry on the sabbath day any load that YOU must bring in through the gates of Jerusalem. 22 And YOU must bring no load out of YOUR homes on the sabbath day; and no work at all must YOU do. And YOU must sanctify the sabbath day, just as I commanded YOUR forefathers; 23 but they did not listen or incline their ear, and they proceeded to harden their neck in order not to hear and in order to receive no discipline.”’

24 “‘“And it must occur that, if YOU strictly obey me,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “to bring in no load through the gates of this city on the sabbath day and to sanctify the sabbath day by not doing on it any work, 25 there will also certainly enter in by the gates of this city kings with princes, sitting on the throne of David, riding in the chariot and upon horses, they and their princes, the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and this city will certainly be inhabited to time indefinite. 26 And people will actually come from the cities of Judah and from round about Jerusalem and from the land of Benjamin and from the lowland and from the mountainous region and from the Neg′eb, bringing whole burnt offering and sacrifice and grain offering and frankincense and bringing thanksgiving sacrifice into the house of Jehovah.

27 “‘“But if YOU will not obey me by sanctifying the sabbath day and not carrying a load, but there is a coming in with it through the gates of Jerusalem on the sabbath day, I will also set a fire ablaze in her gates, and it will certainly devour the dwelling towers of Jerusalem and will not be extinguished.”’”

Jeremiah

18 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “Rise up, and you must go down to the house of the potter, and there I shall cause you to hear my words.”

3 And I proceeded to go down to the house of the potter, and there he was doing work upon the potter’s wheels. 4 And the vessel that he was making with the clay was spoiled by the potter’s hand, and he turned back and went making it into another vessel, just as it looked right in the eyes of the potter to make.

5 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 6 “‘Am I not able to do just like this potter to YOU people, O house of Israel?’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘Look! As the clay in the hand of the potter, so YOU are in my hand, O house of Israel. 7 At any moment that I may speak against a nation and against a kingdom to uproot it and to pull it down and to destroy it, 8 and that nation actually turns back from its badness against which I spoke, I will also feel regret over the calamity that I had thought to execute upon it. 9 But at any moment that I may speak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom to build it up and to plant it, 10 and it actually does what is bad in my eyes by not obeying my voice, I will also feel regret over the good that I said to myself to do for its good.’

11 “And now say, please, to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am forming against YOU a calamity and thinking against YOU a thought. Turn back, please, each one from his bad way, and make YOUR ways and YOUR dealings good.”’”

12 And they said: “It is hopeless! For after our own thoughts we shall walk, and we are going to carry out each one the stubbornness of his bad heart.”

13 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “Ask for yourselves, please, among the nations. Who has heard things like these? There is a horrible thing that the virgin of Israel has done to an excess. 14 Will the snow of Leb′a·non go away from the rock of the open field? Or will strange waters, cool, trickling, be dried up? 15 For my people have forgotten me in that they make sacrificial smoke to something worthless, and in that they make men stumble in their ways, the paths of long ago, to walk in roadways, a way not banked up, 16 in order to make their land an object of astonishment, for whistling at to time indefinite. Every last one passing along by it will stare in astonishment and shake his head. 17 As with an east wind I shall scatter them before the enemy. The back, and not the face, I shall show them in the day of their disaster.”

18 And they proceeded to say: “Come, men, and let us think out against Jeremiah some thoughts, for the law will not perish from the priest or counsel from the wise one or the word from the prophet. Come and let us strike him with the tongue, and let us pay no attention to any of his words.”

19 Do pay attention to me, O Jehovah, and listen to the voice of my opponents. 20 Should bad be repaid for good? For they have excavated a pit for my soul. Remember my standing before you to speak good even concerning them, to turn back your rage from them. 21 Therefore give their sons over to the famine, and deliver them over to the power of the sword; and may their wives become women bereaved of children, and widows. And may their own men become those killed with deadly plague, their young men those struck down with the sword in the battle. 22 Let a cry be heard out of their houses, when you bring upon them suddenly a marauder band. For they have excavated a pit to capture me, and traps they have hid for my feet.

23 But you yourself, O Jehovah, well know all their counsel against me for my death. Do not cover over their error, and do not wipe out that sin of theirs from before you; but let them become those who are made to stumble before you. In the time of your anger take action against them.

Lamentations

א [ʼA′leph]

1 O how she has come to sit solitary, the city that was abundant with people!

How she has become like a widow, she that was populous among the nations!

How she that was a princess among the jurisdictional districts has come to be for forced labor!

ב [Behth]

2 Profusely she weeps during the night, and her tears are upon her cheeks.

She has no one to comfort her from among all her lovers.

All her very own companions have dealt treacherously with her. They have become enemies to her.

ג [Gi′mel]

3 Judah has gone into exile because of the affliction and because of the abundance of servitude.

She herself has had to dwell among the nations. No resting-place has she found.

All those who were persecuting her have overtaken her among distressing circumstances.

ד [Da′leth]

4 The ways of Zion are mourning, because there are none coming to the festival.

All her gates are laid desolate; her priests are sighing.

Her virgins are grief-stricken, and she herself has bitterness.

ה [Heʼ]

5 Her adversaries have become the head. Those who are her enemies are unconcerned.

Because Jehovah himself has brought grief to her on account of the abundance of her transgressions,

Her own children have walked captive before the adversary.

ו [Waw]

6 And from the daughter of Zion there goes out all her splendor.

Her princes have proved to be like stags that have found no pasturage;

And they keep walking without power before the pursuer.

ז [Za′yin]

7 Jerusalem has remembered in the days of her affliction and of her homeless people

All her desirable things that happened to be from days of long ago.

When her people fell into the hand of the adversary and she had no helper,

The adversaries saw her. They laughed over her collapse.

ח [Chehth]

8 Jerusalem has committed outright sin. That is why she has become a mere abhorrent thing.

All who were honoring her have treated her as something cheap, for they have seen her nakedness.

She herself is also sighing and turns her back.

ט [Tehth]

9 Her uncleanness is in her skirts. She did not remember the future for her,

And down she goes in a wondrous manner. No comforter does she have.

O Jehovah, see my affliction, for the enemy has put on great airs.

י [Yohdh]

10 The adversary has spread out his own hand against all her desirable things.

For she has seen nations that have come into her sanctuary,

Whom you commanded that they should not come into the congregation belonging to you.

כ [Kaph]

11 All her people are sighing; they are looking for bread.

They have given their desirable things for something to eat, in order to refresh the soul.

See, O Jehovah, and do look, for I have become as a valueless woman.

ל [La′medh]

12 Is it nothing to all YOU who are passing along the way? Look and see.

Does there exist any pain like my pain that has been severely dealt out to me,

With which Jehovah has caused grief in the day of his burning anger?

מ [Mem]

13 From the height he has sent fire into my bones, and he subdues each one.

He has spread out a net for my feet. He has turned me backward.

He has made me a woman laid desolate. All the day I am ill.

נ [Nun]

14 He has kept himself alert against my transgressions. In his hand they intertwine one another.

They have come up upon my neck. My power has stumbled.

Jehovah has given me into the hand of those against whom I am unable to rise up.

ס [Sa′mekh]

15 All my powerful ones Jehovah has tossed aside from the midst of me.

He has called against me a meeting, in order to break my young men to pieces.

Jehovah has trodden the very winepress belonging to the virgin daughter of Judah.

ע [ʽA′yin]

16 Over these things I am weeping as a woman. My eye, my eye is running down with waters.

For a comforter has become far away from me, someone to refresh my soul.

My sons have become those laid desolate, for the enemy has put on great airs.

פ [Peʼ]

17 Zion has spread out her hands. No comforter does she have.

Jehovah has given a command concerning Jacob to all who are around him as his adversaries.

Jerusalem has become an abhorrent thing in among them.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

18 Jehovah is righteous, for it is against his mouth that I have rebelled.

Listen, now, all YOU peoples, and see my pain.

My own virgins and my own young men have gone into captivity.

ק [Qohph]

19 I have called to those intensely loving me. They themselves have tricked me.

In the city my own priests and my own old men have expired,

While they had to look for something to eat for themselves that they might refresh their soul.

ר [Rehsh]

20 See, O Jehovah, for I am in sore straits. My very intestines are in a ferment.

My heart has been overturned in the midst of me, for I have been absolutely rebellious.

Outside the sword caused bereavement of children. Within the house it is the same as death.

ש [Shin]

21 People have heard how I myself am sighing as a woman. There is no comforter for me.

All my enemies themselves have heard of my calamity. They have exulted, because you yourself have done it.

You will certainly bring the day that you have proclaimed, that they may become like me.

ת [Taw]

22 May all their badness come before you, and deal severely with them,

Just as you have dealt severely with me on account of all my transgressions.

For my sighs are many, and my heart is ill.

Lamentations

א [ʼA′leph]

2 O how Jehovah in his anger beclouds the daughter of Zion!

He has thrown down from heaven to earth the beauty of Israel.

And he has not remembered his footstool in the day of his anger.

ב [Behth]

2 Jehovah has swallowed up, he has shown no compassion upon any abiding places of Jacob.

In his fury he has torn down the fortified places of the daughter of Judah.

He has brought into contact with the earth, he has profaned the kingdom and her princes.

ג [Gi′mel]

3 In the heat of anger he has cut down every horn of Israel.

He has turned his right hand back from before the enemy;

And in Jacob he keeps burning like a flaming fire that has devoured all around.

ד [Da′leth]

4 He has trodden his bow like an enemy. His right hand has taken its position

Like an adversary, and he kept killing all those desirable to the eyes.

Into the tent of the daughter of Zion he has poured out his rage, just like fire.

ה [Heʼ]

5 Jehovah has become like an enemy. He has swallowed down Israel.

He has swallowed down all her dwelling towers; he has brought his fortified places to ruin.

And in the daughter of Judah he makes mourning and lamentation abound.

ו [Waw]

6 And he treats his booth violently like that in a garden. He has brought his festival to ruin.

Jehovah has caused to be forgotten in Zion festival and sabbath,

And in his angry denunciation he shows no respect for king and priest.

ז [Za′yin]

7 Jehovah has cast off his altar. He has spurned his sanctuary.

Into the hand of the enemy he has surrendered the walls of her dwelling towers.

In the house of Jehovah they have let out their own voice, as in the day of a festival.

ח [Chehth]

8 Jehovah has thought of bringing the wall of the daughter of Zion to ruin.

He has stretched out the measuring line. He has not turned back his hand from swallowing up.

And he causes rampart and wall to go mourning. Together they have faded away.

ט [Tehth]

9 Her gates have sunk down into the very earth. He has destroyed and broken her bars in pieces.

Her king and her princes are among the nations. There is no law.

Her own prophets also have found no vision from Jehovah.

י [Yohdh]

10 The older men of the daughter of Zion sit down on the earth, where they keep silence.

They have brought up dust upon their head. They have girded on sackcloth.

The virgins of Jerusalem have brought their head down to the very earth.

כ [Kaph]

11 My eyes have come to their end in sheer tears. My intestines are in a ferment.

My liver has been poured out to the very earth, on account of the crash of the daughter of my people,

Because of the fainting away of child and suckling in the public squares of the town.

ל [La′medh]

12 To their mothers they kept saying: “Where are grain and wine?”

Because of their fainting away like someone slain in the public squares of the city,

Because of their soul being poured out into the bosom of their mothers.

מ [Mem]

13 Of what shall I use you as a witness? What shall I liken to you, O daughter of Jerusalem?

What shall I make equal to you, that I may comfort you, O virgin daughter of Zion?

For your breakdown is just as great as the sea. Who can bring healing to you?

נ [Nun]

14 Your own prophets have visioned for you worthless and unsatisfying things,

And they have not uncovered your error in order to turn back your captivity,

But they kept visioning for you worthless and misleading pronouncements.

ס [Sa′mekh]

15 At you all those passing along on the road have clapped their hands.

They have whistled and kept wagging their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying:

“Is this the city of which they used to say, ‘It is the perfection of prettiness, an exultation for all the earth’?”

פ [Peʼ]

16 At you all your enemies have opened their mouth.

They have whistled and kept grinding the teeth. They have said: “We will swallow her down.

This indeed is the day that we have hoped for. We have found! We have seen!”

ע [ʽA′yin]

17 Jehovah has done what he had in mind. He has accomplished his saying,

What he had commanded from the days of long ago. He has torn down and shown no compassion.

And over you he causes the enemy to rejoice. He has made the horn of your adversaries high.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

18 Their heart has cried out to Jehovah, O wall of the daughter of Zion.

Cause tears to descend just like a torrent day and night.

Give no numbness to yourself. May the pupil of your eye not keep quiet.

ק [Qohph]

19 Rise up! Whine during the night at the start of the morning watches.

Pour out your heart before the face of Jehovah just like water.

Raise to him your palms on account of the soul of your children,

Who are fainting away because of famine at the head of all the streets.

ר [Rehsh]

20 See, O Jehovah, and do look to the one to whom you have dealt severely in this manner.

Should the women keep eating their own fruitage, the children born fully formed,

Or in the sanctuary of Jehovah should priest and prophet be killed?

ש [Shin]

21 Boy and old man have lain down on the earth of the streets.

My virgins and my young men themselves have fallen by the sword.

You have killed in the day of your anger. You have slaughtered; you have had no compassion.

ת [Taw]

22 As in the day of a festival you proceeded to call out my places of alien residence all around.

And in the day of the wrath of Jehovah there proved to be no escapee or survivor;

Those whom I brought forth fully formed and reared, my enemy himself exterminated them.

Ezekiel

3 And he proceeded to say to me: “Son of man, what you find, eat. Eat this roll, and go, speak to the house of Israel.”

2 So I opened my mouth, and he gradually made me eat this roll. 3 And he went on to say to me: “Son of man, you should cause your own belly to eat, that you may fill your very intestines with this roll that I am giving you.” And I began to eat it, and it came to be in my mouth like honey for sweetness.

4 And he continued saying to me: “Son of man, go, enter in among the house of Israel, and you must speak with my words to them. 5 For it is not to a people who are unintelligible in language or heavy of tongue that you are being sent—to the house of Israel, 6 not to numerous peoples unintelligible in language or heavy in tongue, whose words you cannot hear understandingly. If it was to them that I had sent you, those very ones would listen to you. 7 But as for the house of Israel, they will not want to listen to you, for they are not wanting to listen to me; because all those of the house of Israel are hardheaded and hardhearted. 8 Look! I have made your face exactly as hard as their faces and your forehead exactly as hard as their foreheads. 9 Like a diamond, harder than flint, I have made your forehead. You must not be afraid of them, and you must not be struck with terror at their faces, for they are a rebellious house.”

10 And he went on to say to me: “Son of man, all my words that I shall speak to you, take into your heart and hear with your own ears. 11 And go, enter in among the exiled people, among the sons of your people, and you must speak to them and say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said,’ regardless of whether they hear or they refrain.”

12 And a spirit proceeded to bear me along and I began to hear behind me the sound of a great rushing: “Blessed be the glory of Jehovah from his place.” 13 And there was the sound of the wings of the living creatures that were closely touching each other, and the sound of the wheels close beside them, and the sound of a great rushing. 14 And the spirit bore me along and proceeded to take me, so that I went bitterly in the rage of my spirit, and the hand of Jehovah upon me was strong. 15 So I entered in among the exiled people at Tel-a′bib, who were dwelling by the river Che′bar, and I began to dwell where they were dwelling; and I kept dwelling there for seven days, stunned in the midst of them.

16 And it came about at the end of seven days that the word of Jehovah proceeded to occur to me, saying:

17 “Son of man, a watchman is what I have made you to the house of Israel, and you must hear from my mouth speech and you must warn them from me. 18 When I say to someone wicked, ‘You will positively die,’ and you do not actually warn him and speak in order to warn the wicked one from his wicked way to preserve him alive, he being wicked, in his error he will die, but his blood I shall ask back from your own hand. 19 But as for you, in case you have warned someone wicked and he does not actually turn back from his wickedness and from his wicked way, he himself for his error will die; but as for you, you will have delivered your own soul. 20 And when someone righteous turns back from his righteousness and actually does injustice and I must put a stumbling block before him, he himself will die because you did not warn him. For his sin he will die, and his righteous acts that he did will not be remembered, but his blood I shall ask back from your own hand. 21 And as for you, in case you have warned someone righteous that the righteous one should not sin, and he himself does not actually sin, he will without fail keep on living because he had been warned, and you yourself will have delivered your own soul.”

22 And the hand of Jehovah came to be upon me there and he proceeded to say to me: “Get up, go forth to the valley plain, and there I shall speak with you.” 23 So I got up and went forth to the valley plain, and, look! the glory of Jehovah was standing there, like the glory that I had seen by the river Che′bar, and I went falling upon my face. 24 Then spirit entered into me and made me stand up on my feet, and he began to speak with me and say to me:

“Come, be shut up inside your house. 25 And you, O son of man, look! they will certainly put cords upon you and bind you with them so that you cannot go forth into the midst of them. 26 And your very tongue I will make stick to the roof of your mouth, and you will certainly become mute, and you will not become to them a man administering reproof, because they are a rebellious house. 27 And when I speak with you I shall open your mouth, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said.’ Let the one hearing hear, and let the one refraining refrain, because they are a rebellious house.

Ezekiel

4 “And you, O son of man, take for yourself a brick, and you must put it before you and engrave upon it a city, even Jerusalem. 2 And you must lay siege against it and build a siege wall against it and throw up a siege rampart against it and set encampments against it and put battering rams all around against it. 3 And as for you, take to yourself an iron griddle, and you must put it as an iron wall between you and the city, and you must fix your face against it, and it must get to be in a siege, and you must besiege it. It is a sign to the house of Israel.

4 “And as for you, lie upon your left side, and you must lay the error of the house of Israel upon it. For the number of the days that you will lie upon it you will carry their error. 5 And I myself must give to you the years of their error to the number of three hundred and ninety days, and you must carry the error of the house of Israel. 6 And you must complete them.

“And you must lie upon your right side in the second case, and you must carry the error of the house of Judah forty days. A day for a year, a day for a year, is what I have given you. 7 And to the siege of Jerusalem you will fix your face, with your arm bared, and you must prophesy against it.

8 “And, look! I will put cords upon you that you may not turn yourself from your one side to your other side, until you will have completed the days of your siege.

9 “And as for you, take for yourself wheat and barley and broad beans and lentils and millet and spelt, and you must put them in one utensil and make them into bread for you, for the number of the days that you are lying upon your side; three hundred and ninety days you will eat it. 10 And your food that you will eat will be by weight—twenty shekels a day. From time to time you will eat it.

11 “And water you will drink merely by measure, the sixth part of a hin. From time to time you will drink.

12 “And as a round cake of barley you will eat it; and as for it, upon dung cakes of the excrement of mankind you will bake it before their eyes.” 13 And Jehovah went on to say: “Just like this the sons of Israel will eat their bread unclean among the nations to which I shall disperse them.”

14 And I proceeded to say: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Look! My soul is not a defiled one; neither a body already dead nor a torn animal have I eaten from my youth up, even until now, and into my mouth there has come no foul flesh.”

15 Accordingly he said to me: “See, I have given you cattle manure instead of the dung cakes of mankind, and you must make your bread upon it.” 16 And he continued saying to me: “Son of man, here I am breaking the rods around which ring-shaped loaves are suspended, in Jerusalem, and they will have to eat bread by weight and in anxious care, and it will be by measure and in horror that they will drink water itself, 17 to the intent that they may be lacking bread and water and they may look astonished at one another and rot away in their error.

Ezekiel

10 And I continued to see, and, look! upon the expanse that was over the head of the cherubs there was something like sapphire stone, like the appearance of the likeness of a throne, appearing above them. 2 And he proceeded to say to the man clothed with the linen, even to say: “Enter in between the wheelwork, in under the cherubs, and fill the hollows of both your hands with coals of fire from between the cherubs and toss them over the city.” So he entered in before my eyes.

3 And the cherubs were standing to the right of the house when the man entered, and the cloud was filling the inner courtyard. 4 And the glory of Jehovah proceeded to rise up from the cherubs to the threshold of the house, and the house gradually became filled with the cloud, and the courtyard itself was full of the brightness of the glory of Jehovah. 5 And the very sound of the wings of the cherubs made itself heard to the outer courtyard, like the sound of God Almighty when he speaks.

6 And it came about, when he commanded the man clothed with the linen, saying: “Take fire from between the wheelwork, from between the cherubs,” that he proceeded to enter and stand beside the wheel. 7 Then the cherub thrust his hand out from between the cherubs to the fire that was between the cherubs and carried and put it into the hollows of the hands of the one clothed with the linen, who now took it and went out. 8 And there was seen belonging to the cherubs the representation of a hand of earthling man under their wings.

9 And I continued to see, and, look! there were four wheels beside the cherubs, one wheel beside the one cherub and one wheel beside the other cherub, and the appearance of the wheels was like the glow of a chrys′o·lite stone. 10 And as for their appearance, the four of them had one likeness, just as when a wheel proves to be in the midst of a wheel. 11 When they would go, to their four sides they would go. They would not change direction when they went, because the place to which the head would face, after it they would go. They would not change direction when they went. 12 And all their flesh and their backs and their hands and their wings and the wheels were full of eyes all around. The four of them had their wheels. 13 As regards the wheels, to them it was called out in my ears, “O wheelwork!”

14 And each one had four faces. The first face was the face of the cherub, and the second face was the face of earthling man, and the third was the face of a lion, and the fourth was the face of an eagle.

15 And the cherubs would rise—it was the same living creature that I had seen at the river Che′bar— 16 and when the cherubs went, the wheels would go alongside them; and when the cherubs lifted up their wings to be high above the earth, the wheels would not change direction, even they themselves, from alongside them. 17 When these stood still, they would stand still; and when these rose, they would rise with them, for the spirit of the living creature was in them.

18 And the glory of Jehovah proceeded to go forth from over the threshold of the house and to stand still over the cherubs. 19 And the cherubs now lifted up their wings and rose from the earth before my eyes. When they went forth, the wheels also were close alongside them; and they began standing at the eastern entrance of the gate of the house of Jehovah, and the glory of the God of Israel was over them, from above.

20 This is the living creature that I had seen under the God of Israel at the river Che′bar, so that I came to know that they were cherubs. 21 As for the four, each one had four faces and each one had four wings, and the likeness of the hands of earthling man was under their wings. 22 And as for the likeness of their faces, they were the faces the appearance of which I had seen by the river Che′bar, the very ones. They would go each one straight forward.

Ezekiel

19 “And as for you, raise a dirge concerning the chieftains of Israel, 2 and you must say, ‘What was your mother? A lioness among lions. She lay down in among maned young lions. She reared her cubs.

3 “‘And gradually she brought up one of her cubs. A maned young lion is what he became, and he began to learn how to tear apart prey. He devoured even earthling man. 4 And nations kept hearing about him. In their pit he was caught, and they proceeded to bring him by means of hooks to the land of Egypt.

5 “‘When she got to see that she had waited and her hope had perished, then she took another of her cubs. As a maned young lion she put him forth. 6 And he began to walk about in the midst of lions. A maned young lion is what he became. And he gradually learned how to tear apart prey. He devoured even earthling man. 7 And he got to know his dwelling towers, and he devastated even their cities, so that the land was laid desolate and he filled it with the sound of his roaring. 8 And nations all around from the jurisdictional districts began to set against him and got to spread over him their net. In their pit he was caught. 9 Finally they put him in the cage by means of hooks and brought him to the king of Babylon. They got to bring him by means of hunting nets, in order that his voice might no more be heard on the mountains of Israel.

10 “‘Your mother was like a vine in your blood, planted by waters. A bearer of fruit and full of branches she became because of abundant water. 11 And they came to be for her strong rods, meant for the scepters of rulers. And its height gradually became tall up among branches, and it got to be visible because of its tallness, because of the abundance of its foliage. 12 But she was finally uprooted in fury. To the earth she was thrown, and there was an east wind that dried up her fruit. Her strong rod was torn off and became dry. Fire itself devoured it. 13 And now she is planted in the wilderness, in a waterless and thirsty land. 14 And fire proceeded to come forth from her rod. It devoured her very shoots, her very fruit, and there proved to be in her no strong rod, no scepter for ruling.

“‘That is a dirge, and it will become a dirge.’”

Ezekiel

40 In the twenty-fifth year of our exile, in the start of the year, on the tenth day of the month, in the fourteenth year after the city had been struck down, on this very same day the hand of Jehovah proved to be upon me, so that he brought me to that place. 2 In the visions of God he brought me to the land of Israel and gradually set me down upon a very high mountain, on which there was something like the structure of a city to the south.

3 And he proceeded to bring me there, and, look! there was a man. His appearance was like the appearance of copper, and there was a flax cord in his hand, and a measuring reed, and he was standing in the gate. 4 And the man began to speak to me: “Son of man, see with your eyes, and with your ears hear, and set your heart upon all that I am showing you, because for the purpose of my showing you, you have been brought here. Tell everything that you are seeing to the house of Israel.”

5 And, look! there was a wall outside the house all round about. And in the hand of the man there was the measuring reed of six cubits, by a cubit and a handbreadth. And he began to measure the breadth of the thing built, one reed; and the height, one reed.

6 Then he came to the gate, the front of which is toward the east, and went up by its steps. And he began to measure the threshold of the gate, one reed in width, and the other threshold, one reed in width. 7 And the guard chamber was one reed in length and one reed in width, and between the guard chambers there were five cubits; and the threshold of the gate beside the porch of the gate toward the interior was one reed.

8 And he proceeded to measure the porch of the gate toward the interior, one reed. 9 So he measured the porch of the gate, eight cubits; and its side pillars, two cubits; and the porch of the gate was toward the interior.

10 And the guard chambers of the gate toward the east were three on this side and three on that side. The three of them were of the same measurement, and the side pillars were of the same measurement, on this side and on that side.

11 Then he measured the width of the entrance of the gate, ten cubits; the length of the gate, thirteen cubits.

12 And the fenced area in front of the guard chambers was one cubit, and there was a fenced area of one cubit on either side. And the guard chamber was six cubits on this side and six cubits on that side.

13 And he went on to measure the gate from the roof of the one guard chamber to the roof of the other, a width of twenty-five cubits; entrance was across from entrance. 14 Then he made side pillars of sixty cubits, even to the side pillars of the courtyard in the gates all around. 15 And by the front of the gate of the entryway to by the front of the porch of the inner gate was fifty cubits.

16 And there were windows of narrowing frames for the guard chambers and for their side pillars toward the inside of the gate all around, and that is the way it was for the porches. And the windows were all around toward the inside, and on the side pillars there were palm-tree figures.

17 And he gradually brought me into the outer courtyard, and, look! there were dining rooms, and a pavement made for the courtyard all around. There were thirty dining rooms upon the pavement. 18 And the pavement at the side of the gates was exactly as the length of the gates—the lower pavement.

19 And he proceeded to measure the width from in front of the lower gate to the front of the inner courtyard. Outside it was a hundred cubits, to the east and to the north.

20 And the outer courtyard had a gate the front of which was toward the north. He measured its length and its width. 21 And its guard chambers were three on this side and three on that side. And its own side pillars and its own porch proved to be according to the measurement of the first gate. Fifty cubits was its length, and its width was twenty-five in cubits. 22 And its windows and its porch and its palm-tree figures were of the same measurement as those of the gate the front of which is toward the east. And by seven steps people could go up into it, and its porch was to their front.

23 And the gate of the inner courtyard was opposite the gate to the north; also one to the east. And he proceeded to measure from gate to gate a hundred cubits.

24 And he gradually brought me toward the south, and, look! there was a gate toward the south, and he measured its side pillars and its porch as of the same measurements as these. 25 And it and its porch had windows all around, like these windows. Fifty cubits was the length, and the breadth was twenty-five cubits. 26 And there were seven steps for going up to it, and its porch was to their front. And it had palm-tree figures, one on this side and one on that side on its side pillars.

27 And the inner courtyard had a gate toward the south. And he measured from gate to gate toward the south a hundred cubits. 28 And he gradually brought me into the inner courtyard by the gate of the south. And he proceeded to measure the gate of the south as of the same measurements as these. 29 And its guard chambers and its side pillars and its porch were of the same measurements as these. And it and its porch had windows round about. Fifty cubits was the length, and the width was twenty-five cubits. 30 And there were porches all around; the length was twenty-five cubits, and the width five cubits. 31 And its porch was to the outer courtyard, and palm-tree figures were on its side pillars, and its ascent was eight steps.

32 And he gradually brought me into the inner courtyard by way of the east, and he proceeded to measure the gate as of the same measurements as these. 33 And its guard chambers and its side pillars and its porch were of the same measurements as these, and it and its porch had windows all around. The length was fifty cubits, and the width twenty-five cubits. 34 And its porch was toward the outer courtyard, and palm-tree figures were on its side pillars on this side and on that side. And its ascent was eight steps.

35 And he proceeded to bring me into the north gate, and he measured, with the same measurements as these, 36 its guard chambers, its side pillars and its porch. And it had windows all around. The length was fifty cubits, and the width twenty-five cubits. 37 And to the outer courtyard were its side pillars, and palm-tree figures were on its side pillars on this side and on that side. And its ascent was eight steps.

38 And a dining room with its entrance was by the side pillars of the gates. There it was that they would rinse the whole burnt offering.

39 And in the porch of the gate there were two tables on this side and two tables on that side, for slaughtering upon them the whole burnt offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering. 40 And on the outer side, as one goes up to the entrance of the north gate, there were two tables. And on the other side that belongs to the porch of the gate there were two tables. 41 There were four tables over here and four tables over there at the side of the gate—eight tables, upon which they would do the slaughtering. 42 And the four tables for the whole burnt offering were of hewn stone. The length was one cubit and a half, and the width one cubit and a half, and the height one cubit. Upon them they would also deposit the implements with which they would slaughter the whole burnt offering and the sacrifice. 43 And the ledges for setting down things were of one handbreadth, firmly fixed on the interior, all around; and upon the tables they would deposit the flesh of the gift offering.

44 And on the outside of the inner gate there were the dining rooms of the singers, in the inner courtyard, which is on the side of the north gate. And their front side was toward the south. There was one on the side of the east gate. The front was toward the north.

45 And he proceeded to speak to me: “This one, the dining room the front of which is toward the south, is for the priests who are taking care of the obligation of the house. 46 And the dining room the front of which is toward the north is for the priests who are taking care of the obligation of the altar. They are the sons of Za′dok, who, from the sons of Le′vi, are approaching Jehovah to minister to him.”

47 And he went measuring the inner courtyard. The length was a hundred cubits, and the width a hundred cubits, foursquare. And the altar was before the house.

48 And he proceeded to bring me into the porch of the house, and he went measuring the side pillar of the porch, five cubits on this side and five cubits on that side. And the width of the gate was three cubits on this side and three cubits on that side.

49 The length of the porch was twenty cubits, and the width eleven cubits. And by steps was how they would go up to it. And there were pillars by the side posts, one over here and one over there.

Ezekiel

41 And he proceeded to bring me into the temple, and he went measuring the side pillars, six cubits being the width over here and six cubits the width over there, the width of the side pillar. 2 And the width of the entrance was ten cubits, and the sides of the entrance were five cubits over here and five cubits over there. And he went measuring its length, forty cubits; and the width, twenty cubits.

3 And he went inside and proceeded to measure the side pillar of the entrance, two cubits; and the entrance, six cubits; and the width of the entrance was seven cubits. 4 And he went measuring its length, twenty cubits; and its width, twenty cubits, before the temple. Then he said to me: “This is the Most Holy.”

5 And he proceeded to measure the wall of the house, six cubits. And the width of the side chamber was four cubits, round about; all around the house it was, round about. 6 And the side chambers were side chamber upon side chamber, three stories, and for thirty times; and they were entering into the wall that belonged to the house, that is, the side chambers all around, in order that they might be held in, but they were not held in in the wall of the house. 7 And there was a widening out and turning around upward and upward to the side chambers, for the winding passage of the house was upward and upward all around the house. Therefore there was a widening to the house upward, and from the lowest story one could go up to the uppermost story, by the middle story.

8 And I saw that there was a high platform for the house all around. As regards the foundations of the side chambers, there was a full reed of six cubits to the joining. 9 The width of the wall that belonged to the side chamber, to the outside, was five cubits. And there was a space left open by the construction of the side chambers that belonged to the house.

10 And between the dining rooms the width was twenty cubits round about the house, all around. 11 And the entrance of the side chamber was to the space left open, one entrance being toward the north and one entrance to the south; and the width of the area of the space left open was five cubits, all around.

12 And the building that was before the separated area, the side of which was toward the west, was seventy cubits wide. And the wall of the building was five cubits in width, it being all around; and its length was ninety cubits.

13 And he measured the house, a hundred cubits in length; and the separated area and the building and its walls, a hundred cubits in length. 14 And the width of the front of the house and the separated area to the east was a hundred cubits.

15 And he measured the length of the building before the separated area that was behind it and its galleries on this side and on that side, a hundred cubits.

Also the temple and the inner place and the porches of the courtyard; 16 the thresholds, and the windows with narrowing frames, and the galleries were round about the three of them. In front of the threshold there was paneling of wood all around, and from the floor up to the windows; and the windows were covered ones. 17 To above the entrance and as far as the inner house and on the outside and upon the whole wall all around, on the inner house and on the outside, there were measurements, 18 even carved cherubs and palm-tree figures, with a palm-tree figure between a cherub and a cherub, and the cherub had two faces. 19 And the face of a man was toward the palm-tree figure on this side, and the face of a maned young lion was toward the palm-tree figure on that side, they being carved on the whole house all around. 20 From the floor to above the entrance there were carved cherubs and palm-tree figures, on the wall of the temple.

21 As for the temple, the doorpost was squared; and in front of the holy place there was an appearance like the following appearance: 22 the wooden altar was three cubits high, and its length was two cubits, and it had its corner posts. And its length and its walls were of wood. And he proceeded to speak to me: “This is the table that is before Jehovah.”

23 And the temple and the holy place had two doors. 24 And two door leaves belonged to the doors, the two being turnable. One door had two door leaves, and the other had two door leaves. 25 And there were made upon them, upon the doors of the temple, cherubs and palm-tree figures, like those made for the walls, and there was a canopy of wood over the front of the porch outside. 26 And there were windows of narrowing frames and palm-tree figures over here and over there along the sides of the porch and the side chambers of the house and the canopies.

Daniel

1 In the third year of the kingship of Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah, Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and proceeded to lay siege to it. 2 In time Jehovah gave into his hand Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah and a part of the utensils of the house of the true God, so that he brought them to the land of Shi′nar to the house of his god; and the utensils he brought to the treasure-house of his god.

3 Then the king said to Ash′pe·naz his chief court official to bring some of the sons of Israel and of the royal offspring and of the nobles, 4 children in whom there was no defect at all, but good in appearance and having insight into all wisdom and being acquainted with knowledge, and having discernment of what is known, in whom also there was ability to stand in the palace of the king; and to teach them the writing and the tongue of the Chal·de′ans. 5 Furthermore, to them the king appointed a daily allowance from the delicacies of the king and from his drinking wine, even to nourish them for three years, that at the end of these they might stand before the king.

6 Now there happened to be among them some of the sons of Judah, Daniel, Han·a·ni′ah, Mish′a·el and Az·a·ri′ah. 7 And to them the principal court official went assigning names. So he assigned to Daniel the name of Bel·te·shaz′zar; and to Han·a·ni′ah, Sha′drach; and to Mish′a·el, Me′shach; and to Az·a·ri′ah, A·bed′ne·go.

8 But Daniel determined in his heart that he would not pollute himself with the delicacies of the king and with his drinking wine. And he kept requesting of the principal court official that he might not pollute himself. 9 Accordingly the true God gave Daniel over to loving-kindness and to mercy before the principal court official. 10 So the principal court official said to Daniel: “I am in fear of my lord the king, who has appointed YOUR food and YOUR drink. Why, then, should he see YOUR faces dejected-looking in comparison with the children who are of the same age as YOURS, and why should YOU have to make my head guilty to the king?” 11 But Daniel said to the guardian whom the principal court official had appointed over Daniel, Han·a·ni′ah, Mish′a·el and Az·a·ri′ah: 12 “Please, put your servants to the test for ten days, and let them give us some vegetables that we may eat and water that we may drink; 13 and let our countenances and the countenance of the children who are eating the delicacies of the king appear before you, and according to what you see do with your servants.”

14 Finally he listened to them as regards this matter and put them to the test for ten days. 15 And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared better and fatter in flesh than all the children who were eating the delicacies of the king. 16 So the guardian kept on taking away their delicacies and their drinking wine and giving them vegetables. 17 And as for these children, the four of them, to them the true God gave knowledge and insight in all writing and wisdom; and Daniel himself had understanding in all sorts of visions and dreams.

18 And at the end of the days that the king had said to bring them in, the principal court official also proceeded to bring them in before Neb·u·chad·nez′zar. 19 And the king began to speak with them, and out of them all no one was found like Daniel, Han·a·ni′ah, Mish′a·el and Az·a·ri′ah; and they continued to stand before the king. 20 And as regards every matter of wisdom and understanding that the king inquired about from them, he even got to find them ten times better than all the magic-practicing priests and the conjurers that were in all his royal realm. 21 And Daniel continued on until the first year of Cyrus the king.

Daniel

2 And in the second year of the kingship of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, Neb·u·chad·nez′zar dreamed dreams; and his spirit began to feel agitated, and his very sleep was made to be something beyond him. 2 So the king said to call the magic-practicing priests and the conjurers and the sorcerers and the Chal·de′ans to tell the king his dreams. And they proceeded to come in and to stand before the king. 3 Then the king said to them: “There is a dream that I have dreamed, and my spirit is agitated to know the dream.” 4 At that the Chal·de′ans spoke to the king in the Ar·a·ma′ic language: “O king, live on even for times indefinite. Say what the dream is to your servants, and we shall show the very interpretation.”

5 The king was answering and saying to the Chal·de′ans: “The word is being promulgated by me: If YOU men do not make the dream known to me, and its interpretation, dismembered is what YOU will be, and into public privies YOUR own houses will be turned. 6 But if the dream and its interpretation YOU will show, gifts and a present and much dignity YOU will receive on my part. Therefore show me the very dream and its interpretation.”

7 They answered a second time and were saying: “Let the king say what the dream is to his servants, and we shall show its very interpretation.”

8 The king was answering and saying: “For a fact, I am aware that time is what YOU men are trying to gain, forasmuch as YOU have perceived that the word is being promulgated by me. 9 For if YOU do not make known to me the very dream, this one and only sentence is upon YOU. But it is a lying and wrong word that YOU have agreed to say before me, until the time itself is changed. Therefore tell me the very dream, and I shall know that YOU can show the very interpretation of it.”

10 The Chal·de′ans answered before the king, and they were saying: “There does not exist a man on the dry land that is able to show the matter of the king, forasmuch as no grand king or governor has asked such a thing as this of any magic-practicing priest or conjurer or Chal·de′an. 11 But the thing that the king himself is asking is difficult, and nobody else exists who can show it before the king except the gods, whose own dwelling does not exist with flesh at all.”

12 Because of this the king himself became angry and got very furious, and he said to destroy all the wise men of Babylon. 13 And the order itself went out, and the wise men were about to be killed; and they looked for Daniel and his companions, for them to be killed.

14 At that time Daniel, for his part, addressed himself with counsel and sensibleness to Ar′i·och the chief of the king’s bodyguard, who had gone out to kill the wise men of Babylon. 15 He was answering and saying to Ar′i·och the officer of the king: “For what reason is there such a harsh order on the part of the king?” Then it was that Ar′i·och made known the matter itself to Daniel. 16 So Daniel himself went in and asked from the king that he should give him time expressly to show the very interpretation to the king.

17 After that Daniel went to his own house; and to Han·a·ni′ah, Mish′a·el and Az·a·ri′ah his companions he made known the matter, 18 even for them to ask for mercies on the part of the God of heaven concerning this secret, in order that they might not destroy Daniel and his companions with the remainder of the wise men of Babylon.

19 Then it was that to Daniel in a night vision the secret was revealed. Consequently Daniel himself blessed the God of heaven. 20 Daniel was answering and saying: “Let the name of God become blessed from time indefinite even to time indefinite, for wisdom and mightiness—for they belong to him. 21 And he is changing times and seasons, removing kings and setting up kings, giving wisdom to the wise ones and knowledge to those knowing discernment. 22 He is revealing the deep things and the concealed things, knowing what is in the darkness; and with him the light does dwell. 23 To you, O God of my forefathers, I am giving praise and commendation, because wisdom and mightiness you have given to me. And now you have made known to me what we requested of you, for you have made known to us the very matter of the king.”

24 Because of this Daniel himself went in to Ar′i·och, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon. He went, and this is what he said to him: “Do not destroy any wise men of Babylon. Take me in before the king, that I may show the interpretation itself to the king.”

25 Then it was that Ar′i·och, in a hurry, took Daniel in before the king, and this is what he said to him: “I have found an able-bodied man of the exiles of Judah who can make known the interpretation itself to the king.” 26 The king was answering and saying to Daniel, whose name was Bel·te·shaz′zar: “Are you competent enough to make known to me the dream that I beheld, and its interpretation?” 27 Daniel was answering before the king and saying: “The secret that the king himself is asking, the wise men, the conjurers, the magic-practicing priests and the astrologers themselves are unable to show to the king. 28 However, there exists a God in the heavens who is a Revealer of secrets, and he has made known to King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar what is to occur in the final part of the days. Your dream and the visions of your head upon your bed—this it is:

29 “As for you, O king, on your bed your own thoughts came up as regards what is to occur after this, and the One who is the Revealer of secrets has made known to you what is to occur. 30 And as for me, it is not through any wisdom that exists in me more than in any others alive that this secret is revealed to me, except to the intent that the interpretation may be made known to the king himself and that the thoughts of your heart you may know.

31 “You, O king, happened to be beholding, and, look! a certain immense image. That image, which was large and the brightness of which was extraordinary, was standing in front of you, and its appearance was dreadful. 32 As regards that image, its head was of good gold, its breasts and its arms were of silver, its belly and its thighs were of copper, 33 its legs were of iron, its feet were partly of iron and partly of molded clay. 34 You kept on looking until a stone was cut out not by hands, and it struck the image on its feet of iron and of molded clay and crushed them. 35 At that time the iron, the molded clay, the copper, the silver and the gold were, all together, crushed and became like the chaff from the summer threshing floor, and the wind carried them away so that no trace at all was found of them. And as for the stone that struck the image, it became a large mountain and filled the whole earth.

36 “This is the dream, and its interpretation we shall say before the king. 37 You, O king, the king of kings, you to whom the God of heaven has given the kingdom, the might, and the strength and the dignity, 38 and into whose hand he has given, wherever the sons of mankind are dwelling, the beasts of the field and the winged creatures of the heavens, and whom he has made ruler over all of them, you yourself are the head of gold.

39 “And after you there will rise another kingdom inferior to you; and another kingdom, a third one, of copper, that will rule over the whole earth.

40 “And as for the fourth kingdom, it will prove to be strong like iron. Forasmuch as iron is crushing and grinding everything else, so, like iron that shatters, it will crush and shatter even all these.

41 “And whereas you beheld the feet and the toes to be partly of molded clay of a potter and partly of iron, the kingdom itself will prove to be divided, but somewhat of the hardness of iron will prove to be in it, forasmuch as you beheld the iron mixed with moist clay. 42 And as for the toes of the feet being partly of iron and partly of molded clay, the kingdom will partly prove to be strong and will partly prove to be fragile. 43 Whereas you beheld iron mixed with moist clay, they will come to be mixed with the offspring of mankind; but they will not prove to be sticking together, this one to that one, just as iron is not mixing with molded clay.

44 “And in the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be brought to ruin. And the kingdom itself will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it itself will stand to times indefinite; 45 forasmuch as you beheld that out of the mountain a stone was cut not by hands, and that it crushed the iron, the copper, the molded clay, the silver and the gold. The Grand God himself has made known to the king what is to occur after this. And the dream is reliable, and the interpretation of it is trustworthy.”

46 At that time King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar himself fell down upon his face, and to Daniel he paid homage, and he said to offer even a present and incense to him. 47 The king was answering Daniel and saying: “Truly the God of YOU men is a God of gods and a Lord of kings and a Revealer of secrets, because you were able to reveal this secret.” 48 Consequently the king made Daniel someone great, and many big gifts he gave to him, and he made him the ruler over all the jurisdictional district of Babylon and the chief prefect over all the wise men of Babylon. 49 And Daniel, for his part, made a request of the king, and he appointed over the administration of the jurisdictional district of Babylon Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, but Daniel was in the court of the king.

Daniel

6 It seemed good to Da·ri′us, and he set up over the kingdom one hundred and twenty satraps, who were to be over the whole kingdom; 2 and over them three high officials, of whom Daniel was one, in order that these satraps might continually be giving to them the report and the king himself might not become the loser. 3 Then it was that this Daniel was steadily distinguishing himself over the high officials and the satraps, forasmuch as an extraordinary spirit was in him; and the king was intending to elevate him over all the kingdom.

4 At that time the high officials and the satraps themselves were constantly seeking to find some pretext against Daniel respecting the kingdom; but there was no pretext or corrupt thing at all that they were able to find, forasmuch as he was trustworthy and no negligence or corrupt thing at all was found in him. 5 Consequently these able-bodied men were saying: “We shall find in this Daniel no pretext at all, except we have to find it against him in the law of his God.”

6 Accordingly these high officials and satraps themselves entered as a throng to the king, and this is what they were saying to him: “O Da·ri′us the king, live on even for times indefinite. 7 All the high officials of the kingdom, the prefects and the satraps, the high royal officers and the governors, have taken counsel together to establish a royal statute and to enforce an interdict, that whoever makes a petition to any god or man for thirty days except to you, O king, should be thrown to the lions’ pit. 8 Now, O king, may you establish the statute and sign the writing, in order for it not to be changed, according to the law of the Medes and the Persians, which is not annulled.”

9 In accord with this, King Da·ri′us himself signed the writing and the interdict.

10 But Daniel, as soon as he knew that the writing had been signed, entered into his house, and, the windows in his roof chamber being open for him toward Jerusalem, even three times in a day he was kneeling on his knees and praying and offering praise before his God, as he had been regularly doing prior to this. 11 At that time these able-bodied men themselves crowded in and found Daniel petitioning and imploring favor before his God.

12 Then it was that they approached and were saying before the king concerning the interdict of the king: “Is there not an interdict that you have signed that any man that asks a petition from any god or man for thirty days except from you, O king, he should be thrown to the lions’ pit?” The king was answering and saying: “The matter is well established according to the law of the Medes and the Persians, which is not annulled.” 13 Immediately they answered, and they were saying before the king: “Daniel, who is of the exiles of Judah, has paid no regard to you, O king, nor to the interdict that you signed, but three times in a day he is making his petition.” 14 Consequently the king, as soon as he heard the word, it was very displeasing to him, and toward Daniel he set his mind in order to rescue him; and till the setting of the sun he kept on striving to deliver him. 15 Finally these able-bodied men themselves entered as a throng to the king, and they were saying to the king: “Take note, O king, that the law belonging to the Medes and the Persians is that any interdict or statute that the king himself establishes is not to be changed.”

16 Accordingly the king himself commanded, and they brought Daniel and threw him into the pit of the lions. The king was answering and saying to Daniel: “Your God whom you are serving with constancy, he himself will rescue you.” 17 And a stone was brought and placed on the mouth of the pit, and the king sealed it with his signet ring and with the signet ring of his grandees, in order that nothing should be changed in the case of Daniel.

18 At that time the king went to his palace and spent the night fasting, and no musical instruments were brought in before him, and his very sleep fled from him. 19 Finally the king himself, at dawn, proceeded to get up in the daylight, and in a hurry he went right to the lions’ pit. 20 And as he got near to the pit, he cried out with a sad voice even to Daniel. The king was speaking up and saying to Daniel: “O Daniel, servant of the living God, has your God whom you are serving with constancy been able to rescue you from the lions?” 21 Immediately Daniel himself spoke even with the king: “O king, live on even to times indefinite. 22 My own God sent his angel and shut the mouth of the lions, and they have not brought me to ruin, forasmuch as before him innocence itself was found in me; and also before you, O king, no hurtful act have I done.”

23 Then it was that the king himself became very glad, and Daniel himself he commanded to be lifted up out of the pit. And Daniel was lifted up out of the pit, and there was no hurt at all found on him, because he had trusted in his God.

24 And the king commanded, and they brought these able-bodied men who had accused Daniel, and into the lions’ pit they threw them, their sons and their wives; and they had not reached the bottom of the pit before the lions had got the mastery over them, and all their bones they crushed.

25 Then it was that Da·ri′us the king himself wrote to all the peoples, the national groups and the tongues that are dwelling in all the earth: “May YOUR peace grow very much! 26 From before me there has been put through an order that, in every dominion of my kingdom, people are to be quaking and fearing before the God of Daniel. For he is the living God and One enduring to times indefinite, and his kingdom is one that will not be brought to ruin, and his dominion is forever. 27 He is rescuing and delivering and performing signs and wonders in the heavens and on the earth, for he has rescued Daniel from the paw of the lions.”

28 And as for this Daniel, he prospered in the kingdom of Da·ri′us and in the kingdom of Cyrus the Persian.

Daniel

7 In the first year of Bel·shaz′zar the king of Babylon, Daniel himself beheld a dream and visions of his head upon his bed. At that time he wrote down the dream itself. The complete account of the matters he told. 2 Daniel was speaking up and saying:

“I happened to be beholding in my visions during the night, and, see there! the four winds of the heavens were stirring up the vast sea. 3 And four huge beasts were coming up out of the sea, each one being different from the others.

4 “The first one was like a lion, and it had the wings of an eagle. I kept on beholding until its wings were plucked out, and it was lifted up from the earth and was made to stand up on two feet just like a man, and there was given to it the heart of a man.

5 “And, see there! another beast, a second one, it being like a bear. And on one side it was raised up, and there were three ribs in its mouth between its teeth; and this is what they were saying to it, ‘Get up, eat much flesh.’

6 “After this I kept on beholding, and, see there! another beast, one like a leopard, but it had four wings of a flying creature on its back. And the beast had four heads, and there was given to it rulership indeed.

7 “After this I kept on beholding in the visions of the night, and, see there! a fourth beast, fearsome and terrible and unusually strong. And it had teeth of iron, big ones. It was devouring and crushing, and what was left it was treading down with its feet. And it was something different from all the other beasts that were prior to it, and it had ten horns. 8 I kept on considering the horns, and, look! another horn, a small one, came up in among them, and there were three of the first horns that were plucked up from before it. And, look! there were eyes like the eyes of a man in this horn, and there was a mouth speaking grandiose things.

9 “I kept on beholding until there were thrones placed and the Ancient of Days sat down. His clothing was white just like snow, and the hair of his head was like clean wool. His throne was flames of fire; its wheels were a burning fire. 10 There was a stream of fire flowing and going out from before him. There were a thousand thousands that kept ministering to him, and ten thousand times ten thousand that kept standing right before him. The Court took its seat, and there were books that were opened.

11 “I kept on beholding at that time because of the sound of the grandiose words that the horn was speaking; I kept on beholding until the beast was killed and its body was destroyed and it was given to the burning fire. 12 But as for the rest of the beasts, their rulerships were taken away, and there was a lengthening in life given to them for a time and a season.

13 “I kept on beholding in the visions of the night, and, see there! with the clouds of the heavens someone like a son of man happened to be coming; and to the Ancient of Days he gained access, and they brought him up close even before that One. 14 And to him there were given rulership and dignity and kingdom, that the peoples, national groups and languages should all serve even him. His rulership is an indefinitely lasting rulership that will not pass away, and his kingdom one that will not be brought to ruin.

15 “As for me, Daniel, my spirit was distressed within on account of it, and the very visions of my head began to frighten me. 16 I went up close to one of those who were standing, that I might request from him reliable information on all this. And he said to me, as he went on to make known to me the very interpretation of the matters,

17 “‘As for these huge beasts, because they are four, there are four kings that will stand up from the earth. 18 But the holy ones of the Supreme One will receive the kingdom, and they will take possession of the kingdom for time indefinite, even for time indefinite upon times indefinite.’

19 “Then it was that I desired to make certain concerning the fourth beast, which proved to be different from all the others, extraordinarily fearsome, the teeth of which were of iron and the claws of which were of copper, which was devouring and crushing, and which was treading down even what was left with its feet; 20 and concerning the ten horns that were on its head, and the other horn that came up and before which three fell, even that horn that had eyes and a mouth speaking grandiose things and the appearance of which was bigger than that of its fellows.

21 “I kept on beholding when that very horn made war upon the holy ones, and it was prevailing against them, 22 until the Ancient of Days came and judgment itself was given in favor of the holy ones of the Supreme One, and the definite time arrived that the holy ones took possession of the kingdom itself.

23 “This is what he said, ‘As for the fourth beast, there is a fourth kingdom that will come to be on the earth, that will be different from all the other kingdoms; and it will devour all the earth and will trample it down and crush it. 24 And as for the ten horns, out of that kingdom there are ten kings that will rise up; and still another one will rise up after them, and he himself will be different from the first ones, and three kings he will humiliate. 25 And he will speak even words against the Most High, and he will harass continually the holy ones themselves of the Supreme One. And he will intend to change times and law, and they will be given into his hand for a time, and times and half a time. 26 And the Court itself proceeded to sit, and his own rulership they finally took away, in order to annihilate him and to destroy him totally.

27 “‘And the kingdom and the rulership and the grandeur of the kingdoms under all the heavens were given to the people who are the holy ones of the Supreme One. Their kingdom is an indefinitely lasting kingdom, and all the rulerships will serve and obey even them.’

28 “Up to this point is the end of the matter. As for me, Daniel, my own thoughts kept frightening me a great deal, so that my very complexion changed in me; but the matter itself I kept in my own heart.”

Daniel

8 In the third year of the kingship of Bel·shaz′zar the king, there was a vision that appeared to me, even me, Daniel, after the one appearing to me at the start. 2 And I began to see in the vision; and it came about, while I was seeing, that I was in Shu′shan the castle, which is in E′lam the jurisdictional district; and I proceeded to see in the vision, and I myself happened to be by the watercourse of U′lai. 3 When I raised my eyes, then I saw, and, look! a ram standing before the watercourse, and it had two horns. And the two horns were tall, but the one was taller than the other, and the taller was the one that came up afterward. 4 I saw the ram making thrusts to the west and to the north and to the south, and no wild beasts kept standing before it, and there was no one doing any delivering out of its hand. And it did according to its will, and it put on great airs.

5 And I, for my part, kept on considering, and, look! there was a male of the goats coming from the sunset upon the surface of the whole earth, and it was not touching the earth. And as regards the he-goat, there was a conspicuous horn between its eyes. 6 And it kept coming all the way to the ram possessing the two horns, which I had seen standing before the watercourse; and it came running toward it in its powerful rage.

7 And I saw it coming into close touch with the ram, and it began showing bitterness toward it, and it proceeded to strike down the ram and to break its two horns, and there proved to be no power in the ram to stand before it. So it threw it to the earth and trampled it down, and the ram proved to have no deliverer out of its hand.

8 And the male of the goats, for its part, put on great airs to an extreme; but as soon as it became mighty, the great horn was broken, and there proceeded to come up conspicuously four instead of it, toward the four winds of the heavens.

9 And out of one of them there came forth another horn, a small one, and it kept getting very much greater toward the south and toward the sunrising and toward the Decoration. 10 And it kept getting greater all the way to the army of the heavens, so that it caused some of the army and some of the stars to fall to the earth, and it went trampling them down. 11 And all the way to the Prince of the army it put on great airs, and from him the constant feature was taken away, and the established place of his sanctuary was thrown down. 12 And an army itself was gradually given over, together with the constant feature, because of transgression; and it kept throwing truth to the earth, and it acted and had success.

13 And I got to hear a certain holy one speaking, and another holy one proceeded to say to the particular one who was speaking: “How long will the vision be of the constant feature and of the transgression causing desolation, to make both the holy place and the army things to trample on?” 14 So he said to me: “Until two thousand three hundred evenings and mornings; and the holy place will certainly be brought into its right condition.”

15 Then it came about that, while I myself, Daniel, was seeing the vision and seeking an understanding, why, look! there was standing in front of me someone in appearance like an able-bodied man. 16 And I began to hear the voice of an earthling man in the midst of the U′lai, and he proceeded to call out and say: “Ga′bri·el, make that one there understand the thing seen.” 17 So he came beside where I was standing, but when he came I got terrified so that I fell upon my face. And he proceeded to say to me: “Understand, O son of man, that the vision is for the time of the end.” 18 And while he was speaking with me, I had become fast asleep on my face on the earth. So he touched me and made me stand up where I had been standing. 19 And he went on to say: “Here I am causing you to know what will occur in the final part of the denunciation, because it is for the appointed time of the end.

20 “The ram that you saw possessing the two horns stands for the kings of Me′di·a and Persia. 21 And the hairy he-goat stands for the king of Greece; and as for the great horn that was between its eyes, it stands for the first king. 22 And that one having been broken, so that there were four that finally stood up instead of it, there are four kingdoms from his nation that will stand up, but not with his power.

23 “And in the final part of their kingdom, as the transgressors act to a completion, there will stand up a king fierce in countenance and understanding ambiguous sayings. 24 And his power must become mighty, but not by his own power. And in a wonderful way he will cause ruin, and he will certainly prove successful and do effectively. And he will actually bring mighty ones to ruin, also the people made up of the holy ones. 25 And according to his insight he will also certainly cause deception to succeed in his hand. And in his heart he will put on great airs, and during a freedom from care he will bring many to ruin. And against the Prince of princes he will stand up, but it will be without hand that he will be broken.

26 “And the thing seen concerning the evening and the morning, which has been said, it is true. And you, for your part, keep secret the vision, because it is yet for many days.”

27 And as for me, Daniel, I felt exhausted and was made sick for some days. Then I got up and did the work of the king; but I kept showing myself numbed on account of the thing seen, and there was nobody understanding it.

Hosea

5 “Hear this, O priests, and pay attention, O house of Israel, and YOU, O house of the king, give ear, for with YOU people the judgment has to do; because a trap is what YOU have become to Miz′pah and as a net spread over Ta′bor. 2 And in slaughter work those falling away have gone deep down, and I was an exhortation to all of them. 3 I personally have known E′phra·im, and Israel itself has not been hidden from me. For now, O E′phra·im, you have treated women like harlots; Israel has defiled itself. 4 Their dealings do not permit of a returning to their God, because there is a spirit of fornication in the midst of them; and Jehovah himself they have not acknowledged. 5 And the pride of Israel has testified to his face; and Israel and E′phra·im themselves are made to stumble in their error. Judah has also stumbled with them. 6 With their flock and with their herd they proceeded to go and look for Jehovah, but they could not find him. He had drawn away from them. 7 With Jehovah himself they have dealt treacherously, for it is to strange sons that they have become father. Now a month will devour them with their portions.

8 “BLOW a horn in Gib′e·ah, a trumpet in Ra′mah! SHOUT a war cry at Beth-a′ven—after you, O Benjamin! 9 O E′phra·im, a mere object of astonishment you will become in the day of rebuke. Among the tribes of Israel I have made known trustworthy words. 10 The princes of Judah have become just like those moving back a boundary. Upon them I shall pour out my fury just like water. 11 E′phra·im is oppressed, crushed in justice, for he had taken it upon himself to walk after his adversary. 12 And I was like the moth to E′phra·im and just like rottenness to the house of Judah.

13 “And E′phra·im got to see his sickness, and Judah his ulcer. And E′phra·im proceeded to go to As·syr′i·a and send to a great king. But that one himself was unable to give healing to YOU people, and he could not take from YOU an ulcer with any cure. 14 For I shall be like a young lion to E′phra·im and like a maned young lion to the house of Judah. I, I myself shall tear to pieces and I shall go and carry off, and there will be no deliverer. 15 I shall go, I will return to my place until they bear their guilt; and they will certainly seek my face. When they are in sore straits, they will seek me.”

Hosea

6 “Come, YOU people, and do let us return to Jehovah, for he himself has torn in pieces but he will heal us. He kept striking, but he will bind us up. 2 He will make us alive after two days. On the third day he will make us get up, and we shall live before him. 3 And we will know, we will pursue to know Jehovah. Like dawn, his going forth is firmly established. And he will come in like a pouring rain to us; like a spring rain that saturates the earth.”

4 “What shall I do to you, O E′phra·im? What shall I do to you, O Judah, when the loving-kindness of YOU people is like the morning clouds and like the dew that early goes away? 5 That is why I shall have to hew them by the prophets; I shall have to kill them by the sayings of my mouth. And the judgments upon you will be as the light that goes forth. 6 For in loving-kindness I have taken delight, and not in sacrifice; and in the knowledge of God rather than in whole burnt offerings. 7 But they themselves, like earthling man, have overstepped the covenant. There is where they have dealt treacherously with me. 8 Gil′e·ad is a town of practicers of what is harmful; their footprints are blood. 9 And as in the lying in wait for a man, the association of priests are marauding bands. By the wayside they commit murder at She′chem, because they have carried on nothing but loose conduct. 10 In the house of Israel I have seen a horrible thing. There there is fornication on the part of E′phra·im. Israel has defiled itself. 11 Furthermore, O Judah, a harvest has been fixed for you, when I gather back the captive ones of my people.”

Hosea

11 “When Israel was a boy, then I loved him, and out of Egypt I called my son.

2 “They called them. To that same extent they went away from before them. To the Ba′al images they took up sacrificing, and to the graven images they began making sacrificial smoke. 3 But as for me, I taught E′phra·im to walk, taking them upon my arms; and they did not recognize that I had healed them. 4 With the ropes of earthling man I kept drawing them, with the cords of love, so that I became to them as those lifting off a yoke on their jaws, and gently I brought food to each one. 5 He will not return to the land of Egypt, but As·syr′i·a will be his king, because they refused to return. 6 And a sword will certainly whirl about in his cities and make an end of his bars and devour because of their counsels. 7 And my people are tending toward unfaithfulness to me. And upward they call it; no one at all does any rising up.

8 “How can I give you up, O E′phra·im? How can I deliver you up, O Israel? How can I set you as Ad′mah? How can I place you like Ze·boi′im? My heart has changed within me; at the same time my compassions have grown hot. 9 I shall not express my burning anger. I shall not bring E′phra·im to ruin again, for I am God and not man, the Holy One in the midst of you; and I shall not come in excitement. 10 After Jehovah they will walk. Like a lion he will roar; for he himself will roar, and sons will come trembling from the west. 11 Like a bird they will come trembling out of Egypt, and like a dove out of the land of As·syr′i·a; and I shall certainly make them dwell in their houses,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

12 “With lying, E′phra·im has surrounded me, and with deception the house of Israel. But Judah is yet roaming with God, and with the Most Holy One he is trustworthy.”

Joel

1 The word of Jehovah that occurred to Joel the son of Pe·thu′el:

2 “Hear this, YOU older men, and give ear, all YOU inhabitants of the land. Has this occurred in YOUR days, or even in the days of YOUR forefathers? 3 Concerning it give an account to YOUR own sons, and YOUR sons to their sons, and their sons to the following generation. 4 What was left by the caterpillar, the locust has eaten; and what was left by the locust, the creeping, unwinged locust has eaten; and what the creeping, unwinged locust has left, the cockroach has eaten.

5 “Wake up, YOU drunkards, and weep; and howl, all YOU wine drinkers, on account of sweet wine, for it has been cut off from YOUR mouths. 6 For there is a nation that has come up into my land, mighty and without number. Its teeth are the teeth of a lion, and it has the jawbones of a lion. 7 It has set my vine as an object of astonishment, and my fig tree as a stump. It has positively stripped it bare and thrown it away. The twigs of it have become white. 8 Wail, as a virgin girded with sackcloth does over the owner of her youth.

9 “Grain offering and drink offering have been cut off from the house of Jehovah; the priests, the ministers of Jehovah, have mourned. 10 The field has been despoiled, the ground has gone to mourning; for the grain has been despoiled, the new wine has been dried up, the oil has faded away. 11 Farmers have felt shame; vinedressers have howled, on account of wheat and on account of barley; for the harvest of the field has perished. 12 The vine itself has shown dryness, and even the fig tree has faded away. As for the pomegranate tree, also the palm tree and the apple tree, all the trees of the field, they have dried up; for exultation has gone ashamed away from the sons of mankind.

13 “Gird yourselves, and beat YOUR breasts, YOU priests. Howl, YOU ministers of the altar. Come in, spend the night in sackcloth, YOU ministers of my God; for from the house of YOUR God grain offering and drink offering have been withheld. 14 Sanctify a time of fasting. Call together a solemn assembly. Gather together the older men, all the inhabitants of the land, to the house of Jehovah YOUR God, and cry to Jehovah for aid.

15 “Alas for the day; because the day of Jehovah is near, and like a despoiling from the Almighty One it will come! 16 Has not food itself been cut off before our very eyes; from the house of our God, rejoicing and joyfulness? 17 Dried figs have shriveled under their shovels. Storehouses have been laid desolate. Barns have been torn down, for the grain has dried up. 18 O how the domestic animal has sighed! How the droves of cattle have wandered in confusion! For there is no pasturage for them. Also, the droves of the sheep have been the ones made to bear guilt.

19 “To you, O Jehovah, I shall call; for fire itself has devoured the pasture grounds of the wilderness, and a very flame has consumed all the trees of the field. 20 The beasts of the field also keep longing for you, because the channels of water have dried up, and fire itself has devoured the pasture grounds of the wilderness.”

Joel

2 “Blow a horn in Zion, O men, and shout a war cry in my holy mountain. Let all the inhabitants of the land get agitated; for the day of Jehovah is coming, for it is near! 2 It is a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick gloom, like light of dawn spread out upon the mountains.

“There is a people numerous and mighty; one like it has not been made to exist from the indefinite past, and after it there will be none again to the years of generation after generation. 3 Ahead of it a fire has devoured, and behind it a flame consumes. Like the garden of E′den the land is ahead of it; but behind it is a desolate wilderness, and there has also proved to be nothing thereof escaping.

4 “Its appearance is like the appearance of horses, and like steeds is the way they keep running. 5 As with the sound of chariots on the tops of the mountains they keep skipping about, as with the sound of a flaming fire that is devouring stubble. It is like a mighty people, drawn up in battle order. 6 Because of it, peoples will be in severe pains. As for all faces, they will certainly collect a glow of excitement.

7 “Like powerful men they run. Like men of war they go up a wall. And they go each one in his own ways, and they do not alter their paths. 8 And one another they do not shove. As an able-bodied man in his course, they keep going; and should some fall even among the missiles, the others do not break off course.

9 “Into the city they rush. On the wall they run. On the houses they go up. Through the windows they go in like the thief. 10 Before it the land has become agitated, the heavens have rocked. Sun and moon themselves have become dark, and the very stars have withdrawn their brightness. 11 And Jehovah himself will certainly give forth his voice before his military force, for his camp is very numerous. For he who is carrying out his word is mighty; for the day of Jehovah is great and very fear-inspiring, and who can hold up under it?”

12 “And now also,” the utterance of Jehovah is, “come back to me with all YOUR hearts, and with fasting and with weeping and with wailing. 13 And rip apart YOUR hearts, and not YOUR garments; and come back to Jehovah YOUR God, for he is gracious and merciful, slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness, and he will certainly feel regret on account of the calamity. 14 Who is there knowing whether he will turn back and actually feel regret and let remain after it a blessing, a grain offering and a drink offering for Jehovah YOUR God?

15 “Blow a horn in Zion, O men. Sanctify a time of fasting. Call together a solemn assembly. 16 Gather the people together. Sanctify a congregation. Collect the old men together. Gather children and those sucking the breasts together. Let the bridegroom go forth from his interior room, and the bride from her nuptial chamber.

17 “Between the porch and the altar let the priests, the ministers of Jehovah, weep and say, ‘Do feel sorry, O Jehovah, for your people, and do not make your inheritance a reproach, for nations to rule over them. Why should they say among the peoples: “Where is their God?”’ 18 And Jehovah will be zealous for his land and will show compassion upon his people. 19 And Jehovah will answer and say to his people, ‘Here I am sending to YOU the grain and the new wine and the oil, and YOU people will certainly be satisfied with it; and I shall not make YOU anymore a reproach among the nations. 20 And the northerner I shall put far away from upon YOU, and I shall actually disperse him to a waterless land and desolated waste, with his face to the eastern sea and his rear section to the western sea. And the stink from him will certainly ascend, and the stench from him will keep ascending; for He will actually do a great thing in what He does.’

21 “Do not be fearful, O ground. Be joyful and rejoice; for Jehovah will actually do a great thing in what He does. 22 Do not be fearful, YOU beasts of the open field, for the pasture grounds of the wilderness will certainly grow green. For the tree will actually give its fruitage. The fig tree and the vine must give their vital energy. 23 And, YOU sons of Zion, be joyful and rejoice in Jehovah YOUR God; for he will be bound to give YOU the autumn rain in right measure, and he will bring down upon YOU people a downpour, autumn rain and spring rain, as at the first. 24 And the threshing floors must be full of cleansed grain, and the press vats must overflow with new wine and oil. 25 And I will make compensation to YOU for the years that the locust, the creeping, unwinged locust, and the cockroach and the caterpillar have eaten, my great military force that I have sent among YOU. 26 And YOU will certainly eat, eating and becoming satisfied, and YOU will be bound to praise the name of Jehovah YOUR God, who has done with YOU so wonderfully; and my people will not be ashamed to time indefinite. 27 And YOU people will have to know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I am Jehovah YOUR God and there is no other. And my people will not be ashamed to time indefinite.

28 “And after that it must occur that I shall pour out my spirit on every sort of flesh, and YOUR sons and YOUR daughters will certainly prophesy. As for YOUR old men, dreams they will dream. As for YOUR young men, visions they will see. 29 And even on the menservants and on the maidservants in those days I shall pour out my spirit.

30 “And I will give portents in the heavens and on the earth, blood and fire and columns of smoke. 31 The sun itself will be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the coming of the great and fear-inspiring day of Jehovah. 32 And it must occur that everyone who calls on the name of Jehovah will get away safe; for in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will prove to be the escaped ones, just as Jehovah has said, and in among the survivors, whom Jehovah is calling.”

Joel

3 “For, look! in those days and in that time, when I shall bring back the captive ones of Judah and Jerusalem, 2 I will also collect together all the nations and bring them down to the low plain of Je·hosh′a·phat; and I will put myself on judgment with them there on account of my people and my inheritance Israel, whom they scattered among the nations; and they apportioned out my own land. 3 And for my people they kept casting lots; and they would give the male child for a prostitute, and the female child they sold for wine, that they might drink.

4 “And, also, what do YOU have to do with me, O Tyre and Si′don and all YOU regions of Phi·lis′ti·a? Is it the treatment that YOU are giving me as a reward? And if YOU are giving such treatment to me, swiftly, speedily I shall pay back YOUR treatment upon YOUR heads. 5 Because YOU men have taken my own silver and my own gold, and YOU have brought my own desirable good things into YOUR temples; 6 and the sons of Judah and the sons of Jerusalem YOU have sold to the sons of the Greeks, for the purpose of removing them far from their own territory; 7 here I am arousing them to come from the place where YOU have sold them, and I will pay back YOUR treatment upon YOUR own heads. 8 And I will sell YOUR sons and YOUR daughters into the hand of the sons of Judah, and they must sell them to the men of She′ba, to a nation far away; for Jehovah himself has spoken it.

9 “Proclaim this, YOU people, among the nations, ‘Sanctify war! Arouse the powerful men! Let them draw near! Let them come up, all the men of war! 10 Beat YOUR plowshares into swords and YOUR pruning shears into lances. As for the weak one, let him say: “I am a powerful man.” 11 Lend YOUR aid and come, all YOU nations round about, and collect yourselves together.’”

To that place, O Jehovah, bring your powerful ones down.

12 “Let the nations be aroused and come up to the low plain of Je·hosh′a·phat; for there I shall sit in order to judge all the nations round about.

13 “THRUST in a sickle, for harvest has grown ripe. Come, descend, for the winepress has become full. The press vats actually overflow; for their badness has become abundant. 14 Crowds, crowds are in the low plain of the decision, for the day of Jehovah is near in the low plain of the decision. 15 Sun and moon themselves will certainly become dark, and the very stars will actually withdraw their brightness. 16 And out of Zion Jehovah himself will roar, and out of Jerusalem he will give forth his voice. And heaven and earth certainly will rock; but Jehovah will be a refuge for his people, and a fortress for the sons of Israel. 17 And YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah YOUR God, residing in Zion my holy mountain. And Jerusalem must become a holy place; and as regards strangers, they will no more pass through her.

18 “And it must occur in that day that the mountains will drip with sweet wine, and the very hills will flow with milk, and the very streambeds of Judah will all flow with water. And out of the house of Jehovah there will go forth a spring, and it must irrigate the torrent valley of the Acacia Trees. 19 As regards Egypt, a desolate waste it will become; and as regards E′dom, a wilderness of desolate waste it will become, because of the violence to the sons of Judah, in whose land they shed innocent blood. 20 But as for Judah, to time indefinite it will be inhabited, and Jerusalem to generation after generation. 21 And I will consider innocent their blood that I had not considered innocent; and Jehovah will be residing in Zion.”

Jonah

2 Then Jo′nah prayed to Jehovah his God from the inward parts of the fish 2 and said:

“Out of my distress I called out to Jehovah, and he proceeded to answer me.

Out of the belly of She′ol I cried for help.

You heard my voice.

3 When you threw me to the depths, into the heart of the open sea,

Then a very river encircled me.

All your breakers and your waves—over me they passed on.

4 And as for me, I said, ‘I have been driven away from in front of your eyes!

How shall I gaze again upon your holy temple?’

5 Waters encircled me clear to the soul; the watery deep itself kept enclosing me.

Weeds were wound around my head.

6 To the bottoms of the mountains I went down.

As for the earth, its bars were upon me for time indefinite.

But out of the pit you proceeded to bring up my life, O Jehovah my God.

7 When my soul fainted away within me, Jehovah was the One whom I remembered.

Then my prayer came in to you, into your holy temple.

8 As for those who are observing the idols of untruth, they leave their own loving-kindness.

9 But as for me, with the voice of thanksgiving I will sacrifice to you.

What I have vowed, I will pay. Salvation belongs to Jehovah.”

10 In time Jehovah commanded the fish, so that it vomited out Jo′nah onto the dry land.

Micah

3 And I proceeded to say: “Hear, please, YOU heads of Jacob and YOU commanders of the house of Israel. Is it not YOUR business to know justice? 2 YOU haters of what is good and lovers of badness, tearing off their skin from people and their organism from off their bones; 3 YOU the ones who have also eaten the organism of my people, and have stripped their very skin from off them, and smashed to pieces their very bones, and crushed them to pieces like what is in a widemouthed pot and like flesh in the midst of a cooking pot. 4 At that time they will call to Jehovah for aid, but he will not answer them. And he will conceal his face from them in that time, according as they committed badness in their dealings.

5 “This is what Jehovah has said against the prophets that are causing my people to wander, that are biting with their teeth and that actually call out, ‘Peace!’ that, when anyone does not put something into their mouths, also actually sanctify war against him, 6 ‘Therefore YOU men will have night, so that there will be no vision; and darkness YOU will have, so as not to practice divination. And the sun will certainly set upon the prophets, and the day must get dark upon them. 7 And the visionaries will have to be ashamed, and the diviners will certainly be disappointed. And they will have to cover over the mustache, all of them, for there is no answer from God.’”

8 And, on the other hand, I myself have become full of power, with the spirit of Jehovah, and of justice and mightiness, in order to tell to Jacob his revolt and to Israel his sin.

9 Hear, please, this, YOU head ones of the house of Jacob and YOU commanders of the house of Israel, the ones detesting justice and the ones who make even everything that is straight crooked; 10 building Zion with acts of bloodshed and Jerusalem with unrighteousness. 11 Her own head ones judge merely for a bribe, and her own priests instruct just for a price, and her own prophets practice divination simply for money; yet upon Jehovah they keep supporting themselves, saying: “Is not Jehovah in the midst of us? There will come upon us no calamity.” 12 Therefore on account of YOU men Zion will be plowed up as a mere field, and Jerusalem herself will become mere heaps of ruins, and the mountain of the house will be as the high places of a forest.

Micah

4 And it must occur in the final part of the days that the mountain of the house of Jehovah will become firmly established above the top of the mountains, and it will certainly be lifted up above the hills; and to it peoples must stream. 2 And many nations will certainly go and say: “Come, YOU people, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah and to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will instruct us about his ways, and we will walk in his paths.” For out of Zion law will go forth, and the word of Jehovah out of Jerusalem. 3 And he will certainly render judgment among many peoples, and set matters straight respecting mighty nations far away. And they will have to beat their swords into plowshares and their spears into pruning shears. They will not lift up sword, nation against nation, neither will they learn war anymore. 4 And they will actually sit, each one under his vine and under his fig tree, and there will be no one making them tremble; for the very mouth of Jehovah of armies has spoken it.

5 For all the peoples, for their part, will walk each one in the name of its god; but we, for our part, shall walk in the name of Jehovah our God to time indefinite, even forever.

6 “In that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “I will gather her that was limping; and her that was dispersed I will collect together, even her whom I have treated badly. 7 And I shall certainly make her that was limping a remnant, and her that was removed far off a mighty nation; and Jehovah will actually rule as king over them in Mount Zion, from now on and into time indefinite.

8 “And as for you, O tower of the drove, the mound of the daughter of Zion, as far as to you it will come, yes, the first dominion will certainly come, the kingdom belonging to the daughter of Jerusalem.

9 “Now why is it that you keep shouting loudly? Is there no king in you, or has your own counselor perished, so that pangs like those of a woman giving birth have grabbed hold of you? 10 Be in severe pains and burst forth, O daughter of Zion, like a woman giving birth, for now you will go forth from a town, and you will have to reside in the field. And you will have to come as far as to Babylon. There you will be delivered. There Jehovah will buy you back out of the palm of your enemies.

11 “And now there will certainly be gathered against you many nations, those who are saying, ‘Let her be polluted, and may our eyes look upon Zion.’ 12 But as for them, they have not come to know the thoughts of Jehovah, and they have not come to understand his counsel; because he will certainly collect them together like a row of newly cut grain to the threshing floor.

13 “Get up and thresh, O daughter of Zion; for your horn I shall change into iron, and your hoofs I shall change into copper, and you will certainly pulverize many peoples; and by a ban you will actually devote to Jehovah their unjust profit, and their resources to the true Lord of the whole earth.”

Micah

5 “At this time you make cuttings upon yourself, O daughter of an invasion; a siege he has laid against us. With the rod they will strike upon the cheek the judge of Israel.

2 “And you, O Beth′le·hem Eph′ra·thah, the one too little to get to be among the thousands of Judah, from you there will come out to me the one who is to become ruler in Israel, whose origin is from early times, from the days of time indefinite.

3 “Therefore he will give them up until the time that she who is giving birth actually gives birth. And the rest of his brothers will return to the sons of Israel.

4 “And he will certainly stand and do shepherding in the strength of Jehovah, in the superiority of the name of Jehovah his God. And they will certainly keep dwelling, for now he will be great as far as the ends of the earth. 5 And this one must become peace. As for the As·syr′i·an, when he comes into our land and when he treads upon our dwelling towers, we shall also have to raise up against him seven shepherds, yes, eight dukes of mankind. 6 And they will actually shepherd the land of As·syr′i·a with the sword, and the land of Nim′rod in its entrances. And he will certainly bring about deliverance from the As·syr′i·an, when he comes into our land and when he treads upon our territory.

7 “And the remaining ones of Jacob must become in the midst of many peoples like dew from Jehovah, like copious showers upon vegetation, that does not hope for man or wait for the sons of earthling man. 8 And the remaining ones of Jacob must become among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, like a lion among the beasts of a forest, like a maned young lion among droves of sheep, which, when it actually passes through, certainly both tramples down and tears in pieces; and there is no deliverer. 9 Your hand will be high above your adversaries, and all enemies of yours will be cut off.”

10 “And it must occur in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “that I will cut off your horses from the midst of you and destroy your chariots. 11 And I will cut off the cities of your land and tear down all your fortified places. 12 And I will cut off sorceries out of your hand, and no practicers of magic will you continue to have. 13 And I will cut off your graven images and your pillars from the midst of you, and you will no more bow down to the work of your hands. 14 And I will uproot your sacred poles from the midst of you and annihilate your cities. 15 And in anger and in rage I will execute vengeance upon the nations that have not obeyed.”

Micah

6 Hear, please, YOU people, what Jehovah is saying. Get up, conduct a legal case with the mountains, and may the hills hear your voice. 2 Hear, O YOU mountains, the legal case of Jehovah, also YOU durable objects, YOU foundations of the earth; for Jehovah has a legal case with his people, and it is with Israel that he will argue:

3 “O my people, what have I done to you? And in what way have I tired you out? Testify against me. 4 For I brought you up out of the land of Egypt, and from the house of slaves I redeemed you; and I proceeded to send before you Moses, Aaron and Mir′i·am. 5 O my people, remember, please, what Ba′lak the king of Mo′ab counseled, and what Ba′laam the son of Be′or answered him. From Shit′tim it was, all the way to Gil′gal, to the intent that the righteous acts of Jehovah might be known.”

6 With what shall I confront Jehovah? With what shall I bow myself to God on high? Shall I confront him with whole burnt offerings, with calves a year old? 7 Will Jehovah be pleased with thousands of rams, with tens of thousands of torrents of oil? Shall I give my firstborn son for my revolt, the fruitage of my belly for the sin of my soul? 8 He has told you, O earthling man, what is good. And what is Jehovah asking back from you but to exercise justice and to love kindness and to be modest in walking with your God?

9 To the city the very voice of Jehovah calls out, and the person of practical wisdom will fear your name. Hear the rod and who it was that designated it, O YOU people. 10 Do there yet exist in the house of a wicked one the treasures of wickedness, and the scrimped e′phah measure that is denounced? 11 Can I be morally clean with wicked scales and with a bag of deceptive stone weights? 12 For her own rich men have become full of violence, and her own inhabitants have spoken falsehood, and their tongue is tricky in their mouth.

13 “And I also, for my part, shall certainly make you sick by striking you; there will be a desolating of you, on account of your sins. 14 You, for your part, will eat and not get satisfied, and your emptiness will be in the midst of you. And you will remove things, but you will not carry them safely away; and whatever you would carry away safely, I shall give to the sword itself. 15 You, for your part, will sow seed, but you will not reap. You, for your part, will tread olives, but you will not grease yourself with oil; also sweet wine, but you will not drink wine. 16 And the statutes of Om′ri and all the work of the house of A′hab are observed, and YOU people walk in their counsels; to the end that I may make you an object of astonishment and her inhabitants something to be whistled at; and the reproach of peoples YOU men will bear.”

Micah

7 Too bad for me, for I have become like the gatherings of summer fruit, like the gleaning of a grape gathering! There is no grape cluster to eat, no early fig, that my soul would desire! 2 The loyal one has perished from the earth, and among mankind there is no upright one. All of them, for bloodshed they lie in wait. They hunt, everyone his own brother, with a dragnet. 3 Their hands are upon what is bad, to do it well; the prince is asking for something, and the one who is judging does so for the reward, and the great one is speaking forth the craving of his soul, his very own; and they interweave it. 4 Their best one is like a brier, their most upright one is worse than a thorn hedge. The day of your watchmen, of your being given attention, must come. Now will occur the confounding of them.

5 Do not put YOUR faith in a companion. Do not put YOUR trust in a confidential friend. From her who is lying in your bosom guard the openings of your mouth. 6 For a son is despising a father; a daughter is rising up against her mother; a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law; a man’s enemies are the men of his household.

7 But as for me, it is for Jehovah that I shall keep on the lookout. I will show a waiting attitude for the God of my salvation. My God will hear me.

8 Do not rejoice over me, O you woman enemy of mine. Although I have fallen, I shall certainly rise up; although I dwell in the darkness, Jehovah will be a light to me. 9 The raging of Jehovah I shall bear—for I have sinned against him—until he conducts my legal case and actually executes justice for me. He will bring me forth to the light; I shall look upon his righteousness. 10 And my enemy will see, and shame will cover her, who was saying to me: “Where is he, Jehovah your God?” My own eyes will look upon her. Now she will become a place of trampling, like the mire of streets.

11 The day for building your stone walls, at that day the decree will be far away. 12 At that day even all the way to you they will come from As·syr′i·a and the cities of Egypt, and from Egypt even all the way to the River; and from sea to sea, and from mountain to the mountain. 13 And the land must become a desolate waste on account of its inhabitants, because of the fruit of their dealings.

14 Shepherd your people with your staff, the flock of your inheritance, the one who was residing alone in a forest—in the midst of an orchard. Let them feed on Ba′shan and Gil′e·ad as in the days of a long time ago.

15 “As in the days of your coming forth from the land of Egypt I shall show him wonderful things. 16 Nations will see and become ashamed of all their mightiness. They will put their hand upon their mouth; their very ears will become deaf. 17 They will lick up dust like the serpents; like reptiles of the earth they will come in agitation out of their bulwarks. To Jehovah our God they will come quivering, and they will be afraid of you.”

18 Who is a God like you, one pardoning error and passing over transgression of the remnant of his inheritance? He will certainly not hold onto his anger forever, for he is delighting in loving-kindness. 19 He will again show us mercy; he will subject our errors. And you will throw into the depths of the sea all their sins. 20 You will give the trueness given to Jacob, the loving-kindness given to Abraham, which you swore to our forefathers from the days of long ago.

Habakkuk

1 The pronouncement that Ha·bak′kuk the prophet visioned: 2 How long, O Jehovah, must I cry for help, and you do not hear? How long shall I call to you for aid from violence, and you do not save? 3 Why is it that you make me see what is hurtful, and you keep looking upon mere trouble? And why are despoiling and violence in front of me, and why does quarreling occur, and why is strife carried?

4 Therefore law grows numb, and justice never goes forth. Because the wicked one is surrounding the righteous one, for that reason justice goes forth crooked.

5 “See, YOU people, among the nations, and look on, and stare in amazement at one another. Be amazed; for there is an activity that one is carrying on in YOUR days, which YOU people will not believe although it is related. 6 For here I am raising up the Chal·de′ans, the nation bitter and impetuous, which is going to the wide-open places of earth in order to take possession of residences not belonging to it. 7 Frightful and fear-inspiring it is. From itself its own justice and its own dignity go forth. 8 And its horses have proved swifter than leopards, and they have proved fiercer than evening wolves. And its steeds have pawed the ground, and from far away its own steeds come. They fly like the eagle speeding to eat something. 9 In its entirety it comes for mere violence. The assembling of their faces is as the east wind, and it gathers up captives just like the sand. 10 And for its part, it jeers kings themselves, and high officials are something laughable to it. For its part, it laughs even at every fortified place, and it piles up dust and captures it. 11 At that time it will certainly move onward like wind and will pass through and will actually become guilty. This its power is due to its god.”

12 Are you not from long ago, O Jehovah? O my God, my Holy One, you do not die. O Jehovah, for a judgment you have set it; and, O Rock, for a reproving you have founded it.

13 You are too pure in eyes to see what is bad; and to look on trouble you are not able. Why is it that you look on those dealing treacherously, that you keep silent when someone wicked swallows up someone more righteous than he is? 14 And why do you make earthling man like the fishes of the sea, like creeping things over whom no one is ruling? 15 All these he has brought up with a mere fishhook; he drags them away in his dragnet, and he gathers them in his fishing net. That is why he rejoices and is joyful. 16 That is why he offers sacrifice to his dragnet and makes sacrificial smoke to his fishing net; for by them his portion is well oiled, and his food is healthful. 17 Is that why he will empty out his dragnet, and does he have to kill nations constantly, while he shows no compassion?

Zephaniah

3 Woe to her that is rebelling and polluting herself, the oppressive city! 2 She did not listen to a voice; she did not accept discipline. In Jehovah she did not trust. To her God she did not draw near. 3 Her princes in the midst of her were roaring lions. Her judges were evening wolves that did not gnaw bones till the morning. 4 Her prophets were insolent, were men of treachery. Her priests themselves profaned what was holy; they did violence to the law. 5 Jehovah was righteous in the midst of her; he would do no unrighteousness. Morning by morning he kept giving his own judicial decision. At daylight it did not prove lacking. But the unrighteous one was knowing no shame.

6 “I cut off nations; their corner towers were desolated. I devastated their streets, so that there was no one passing through. Their cities were laid waste, so that there was no man, so that there was no inhabitant. 7 I said, ‘Surely you will fear me; you will accept discipline’; so that her dwelling might not be cut off—all that I must call to account against her. Truly they acted promptly in making all their dealings ruinous.

8 “‘Therefore keep yourselves in expectation of me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘till the day of my rising up to the booty, for my judicial decision is to gather nations, for me to collect together kingdoms, in order to pour out upon them my denunciation, all my burning anger; for by the fire of my zeal all the earth will be devoured. 9 For then I shall give to peoples the change to a pure language, in order for them all to call upon the name of Jehovah, in order to serve him shoulder to shoulder.’

10 “From the region of the rivers of E·thi·o′pi·a the ones entreating me, namely, the daughter of my scattered ones, will bring a gift to me. 11 In that day you will not be ashamed because of all your dealings with which you transgressed against me, for then I shall remove from the midst of you your haughtily exultant ones; and you will never again be haughty in my holy mountain. 12 And I shall certainly let remain in the midst of you a people humble and lowly, and they will actually take refuge in the name of Jehovah. 13 As regards the remaining ones of Israel, they will do no unrighteousness, nor speak a lie, nor will there be found in their mouths a tricky tongue; for they themselves will feed and actually lie stretched out, and there will be no one making them tremble.”

14 Joyfully cry out, O daughter of Zion! Break out in cheers, O Israel! Rejoice and exult with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem! 15 Jehovah has removed the judgments upon you. He has turned away your enemy. The king of Israel, Jehovah, is in the midst of you. You will fear calamity no more. 16 In that day it will be said to Jerusalem: “Do not be afraid, O Zion. May your hands not drop down. 17 Jehovah your God is in the midst of you. As a mighty One, he will save. He will exult over you with rejoicing. He will become silent in his love. He will be joyful over you with happy cries.

18 “The ones grief-stricken in absence from your festal season I shall certainly gather together; absent from you they happened to be, because of bearing reproach on her account. 19 Here I am acting against all those afflicting you, at that time; and I will save her that is limping, and her that is dispersed I shall collect together. And I will set them as a praise and as a name in all the land of their shame. 20 At that time I shall bring YOU people in, even in the time of my collecting YOU together. For I shall make YOU people to be a name and a praise among all the peoples of the earth, when I gather back YOUR captive ones before YOUR eyes,” Jehovah has said.

Zechariah

12 A pronouncement:

“The word of Jehovah concerning Israel,” is the utterance of Jehovah, the One who is stretching out the heavens and laying the foundation of the earth and forming the spirit of man inside him. 2 “Here I am making Jerusalem a bowl causing reeling to all the peoples round about; and also against Judah he will come to be in the siege, even against Jerusalem. 3 And it must occur in that day that I shall make Jerusalem a burdensome stone to all the peoples. All those lifting it will without fail get severe scratches for themselves; and against her all the nations of the earth will certainly be gathered. 4 In that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “I shall strike every horse with bewilderment and its rider with madness; and upon the house of Judah I shall open my eyes, and every horse of the peoples I shall strike with loss of sight. 5 And the sheiks of Judah will have to say in their heart, ‘The inhabitants of Jerusalem are a strength to me by Jehovah of armies their God.’ 6 In that day I shall make the sheiks of Judah like a firepot among trees and like a fiery torch in a row of newly cut grain, and they must devour on the right hand and on the left all the peoples round about; and Jerusalem must yet be inhabited in her own place, in Jerusalem.

7 “And Jehovah will certainly save the tents of Judah first, to the end that the beauty of the house of David and the beauty of the inhabitants of Jerusalem may not become too great over Judah. 8 In that day Jehovah will be a defense around the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and the one that is stumbling among them must become in that day like David, and the house of David like God, like Jehovah’s angel before them. 9 And it must occur in that day that I shall seek to annihilate all the nations that are coming against Jerusalem.

10 “And I will pour out upon the house of David and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of favor and entreaties, and they will certainly look to the One whom they pierced through, and they will certainly wail over Him as in the wailing over an only son; and there will be a bitter lamentation over him as when there is bitter lamentation over the firstborn son. 11 In that day the wailing in Jerusalem will be great, like the wailing of Ha·dad·rim′mon in the valley plain of Me·gid′do. 12 And the land will certainly wail, each family by itself; the family of the house of David by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of the house of Nathan by itself, and their women by themselves; 13 the family of the house of Le′vi by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of the Shim′e·ites by itself, and their women by themselves; 14 all the families that are left remaining, each family by itself, and their women by themselves.

Matthew

6 “Take good care not to practice YOUR righteousness in front of men in order to be observed by them; otherwise YOU will have no reward with YOUR Father who is in the heavens. 2 Hence when you go making gifts of mercy, do not blow a trumpet ahead of you, just as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may be glorified by men. Truly I say to YOU, They are having their reward in full. 3 But you, when making gifts of mercy, do not let your left hand know what your right is doing, 4 that your gifts of mercy may be in secret; then your Father who is looking on in secret will repay you.

5 “Also, when YOU pray, YOU must not be as the hypocrites; because they like to pray standing in the synagogues and on the corners of the broad ways to be visible to men. Truly I say to YOU, They are having their reward in full. 6 You, however, when you pray, go into your private room and, after shutting your door, pray to your Father who is in secret; then your Father who looks on in secret will repay you. 7 But when praying, do not say the same things over and over again, just as the people of the nations do, for they imagine they will get a hearing for their use of many words. 8 So, do not make yourselves like them, for God YOUR Father knows what things YOU are needing before ever YOU ask him.

9 “YOU must pray, then, this way:

“‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified. 10 Let your kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also upon earth. 11 Give us today our bread for this day; 12 and forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors. 13 And do not bring us into temptation, but deliver us from the wicked one.’

14 “For if YOU forgive men their trespasses, YOUR heavenly Father will also forgive YOU; 15 whereas if YOU do not forgive men their trespasses, neither will YOUR Father forgive YOUR trespasses.

16 “When YOU are fasting, stop becoming sad-faced like the hypocrites, for they disfigure their faces that they may appear to men to be fasting. Truly I say to YOU, They are having their reward in full. 17 But you, when fasting, grease your head and wash your face, 18 that you may appear to be fasting, not to men, but to your Father who is in secrecy; then your Father who is looking on in secrecy will repay you.

19 “Stop storing up for yourselves treasures upon the earth, where moth and rust consume, and where thieves break in and steal. 20 Rather, store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust consumes, and where thieves do not break in and steal. 21 For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.

22 “The lamp of the body is the eye. If, then, your eye is simple, your whole body will be bright; 23 but if your eye is wicked, your whole body will be dark. If in reality the light that is in you is darkness, how great that darkness is!

24 “No one can slave for two masters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. YOU cannot slave for God and for Riches.

25 “On this account I say to YOU: Stop being anxious about YOUR souls as to what YOU will eat or what YOU will drink, or about YOUR bodies as to what YOU will wear. Does not the soul mean more than food and the body than clothing? 26 Observe intently the birds of heaven, because they do not sow seed or reap or gather into storehouses; still YOUR heavenly Father feeds them. Are YOU not worth more than they are? 27 Who of YOU by being anxious can add one cubit to his life span? 28 Also, on the matter of clothing, why are YOU anxious? Take a lesson from the lilies of the field, how they are growing; they do not toil, nor do they spin; 29 but I say to YOU that not even Sol′o·mon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these. 30 If, now, God thus clothes the vegetation of the field, which is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much rather clothe YOU, YOU with little faith? 31 So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to put on?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. For YOUR heavenly Father knows YOU need all these things.

33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to YOU. 34 So, never be anxious about the next day, for the next day will have its own anxieties. Sufficient for each day is its own badness.

Matthew

7 “Stop judging that YOU may not be judged; 2 for with what judgment YOU are judging, YOU will be judged; and with the measure that YOU are measuring out, they will measure out to YOU. 3 Why, then, do you look at the straw in your brother’s eye, but do not consider the rafter in your own eye? 4 Or how can you say to your brother, ‘Allow me to extract the straw from your eye’; when, look! a rafter is in your own eye? 5 Hypocrite! First extract the rafter from your own eye, and then you will see clearly how to extract the straw from your brother’s eye.

6 “Do not give what is holy to dogs, neither throw YOUR pearls before swine, that they may never trample them under their feet and turn around and rip YOU open.

7 “Keep on asking, and it will be given YOU; keep on seeking, and YOU will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to YOU. 8 For everyone asking receives, and everyone seeking finds, and to everyone knocking it will be opened. 9 Indeed, who is the man among YOU whom his son asks for bread—he will not hand him a stone, will he? 10 Or, perhaps, he will ask for a fish—he will not hand him a serpent, will he? 11 Therefore, if YOU, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to YOUR children, how much more so will YOUR Father who is in the heavens give good things to those asking him!

12 “All things, therefore, that YOU want men to do to YOU, YOU also must likewise do to them; this, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

13 “Go in through the narrow gate; because broad and spacious is the road leading off into destruction, and many are the ones going in through it; 14 whereas narrow is the gate and cramped the road leading off into life, and few are the ones finding it.

15 “Be on the watch for the false prophets that come to YOU in sheep’s covering, but inside they are ravenous wolves. 16 By their fruits YOU will recognize them. Never do people gather grapes from thorns or figs from thistles, do they? 17 Likewise every good tree produces fine fruit, but every rotten tree produces worthless fruit; 18 a good tree cannot bear worthless fruit, neither can a rotten tree produce fine fruit. 19 Every tree not producing fine fruit gets cut down and thrown into the fire. 20 Really, then, by their fruits YOU will recognize those men.

21 “Not everyone saying to me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ will enter into the kingdom of the heavens, but the one doing the will of my Father who is in the heavens will. 22 Many will say to me in that day, ‘Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and expel demons in your name, and perform many powerful works in your name?’ 23 And yet then I will confess to them: I never knew YOU! Get away from me, YOU workers of lawlessness.

24 “Therefore everyone that hears these sayings of mine and does them will be likened to a discreet man, who built his house upon the rock-mass. 25 And the rain poured down and the floods came and the winds blew and lashed against that house, but it did not cave in, for it had been founded upon the rock-mass. 26 Furthermore, everyone hearing these sayings of mine and not doing them will be likened to a foolish man, who built his house upon the sand. 27 And the rain poured down and the floods came and the winds blew and struck against that house and it caved in, and its collapse was great.”

28 Now when Jesus finished these sayings, the effect was that the crowds were astounded at his way of teaching; 29 for he was teaching them as a person having authority, and not as their scribes.

Matthew

18 In that hour the disciples came near to Jesus and said: “Who really is greatest in the kingdom of the heavens?” 2 So, calling a young child to him, he set it in their midst 3 and said: “Truly I say to YOU, Unless YOU turn around and become as young children, YOU will by no means enter into the kingdom of the heavens. 4 Therefore, whoever will humble himself like this young child is the one that is the greatest in the kingdom of the heavens; 5 and whoever receives one such young child on the basis of my name receives me also. 6 But whoever stumbles one of these little ones who put faith in me, it is more beneficial for him to have hung around his neck a millstone such as is turned by an ass and to be sunk in the wide, open sea.

7 “Woe to the world due to the stumbling blocks! Of course, the stumbling blocks must of necessity come, but woe to the man through whom the stumbling block comes! 8 If, then, your hand or your foot is making you stumble, cut it off and throw it away from you; it is finer for you to enter into life maimed or lame than to be thrown with two hands or two feet into the everlasting fire. 9 Also, if your eye is making you stumble, tear it out and throw it away from you; it is finer for you to enter one-eyed into life than to be thrown with two eyes into the fiery Ge·hen′na. 10 See to it that YOU men do not despise one of these little ones; for I tell YOU that their angels in heaven always behold the face of my Father who is in heaven. 11 ——

12 “What do YOU think? If a certain man comes to have a hundred sheep and one of them gets strayed, will he not leave the ninety-nine upon the mountains and set out on a search for the one that is straying? 13 And if he happens to find it, I certainly tell YOU, he rejoices more over it than over the ninety-nine that have not strayed. 14 Likewise it is not a desirable thing with my Father who is in heaven for one of these little ones to perish.

15 “Moreover, if your brother commits a sin, go lay bare his fault between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. 16 But if he does not listen, take along with you one or two more, in order that at the mouth of two or three witnesses every matter may be established. 17 If he does not listen to them, speak to the congregation. If he does not listen even to the congregation, let him be to you just as a man of the nations and as a tax collector.

18 “Truly I say to YOU men, Whatever things YOU may bind on earth will be things bound in heaven, and whatever things YOU may loose on earth will be things loosed in heaven. 19 Again I truly say to YOU, If two of YOU on earth agree concerning anything of importance that they should request, it will take place for them due to my Father in heaven. 20 For where there are two or three gathered together in my name, there I am in their midst.”

21 Then Peter came up and said to him: “Lord, how many times is my brother to sin against me and am I to forgive him? Up to seven times?” 22 Jesus said to him: “I say to you, not, Up to seven times, but, Up to seventy-seven times.

23 “That is why the kingdom of the heavens has become like a man, a king, that wanted to settle accounts with his slaves. 24 When he started to settle them, there was brought in a man who owed him ten thousand talents [=60,000,000 de·nar′i·i]. 25 But because he did not have the means to pay it back, his master ordered him and his wife and his children and all the things he had to be sold and payment to be made. 26 Therefore the slave fell down and began to do obeisance to him, saying, ‘Be patient with me and I will pay back everything to you.’ 27 Moved to pity at this, the master of that slave let him off and canceled his debt. 28 But that slave went out and found one of his fellow slaves that was owing him a hundred de·nar′i·i; and, grabbing him, he began to choke him, saying, ‘Pay back whatever you owe.’ 29 Therefore his fellow slave fell down and began to entreat him, saying, ‘Be patient with me and I will pay you back.’ 30 However, he was not willing, but went off and had him thrown into prison until he should pay back what was owing. 31 When, therefore, his fellow slaves saw the things that had happened, they became very much grieved, and they went and made clear to their master all the things that had happened. 32 Then his master summoned him and said to him, ‘Wicked slave, I canceled all that debt for you, when you entreated me. 33 Ought you not, in turn, to have had mercy on your fellow slave, as I also had mercy on you?’ 34 With that his master, provoked to wrath, delivered him to the jailers, until he should pay back all that was owing. 35 In like manner my heavenly Father will also deal with YOU if YOU do not forgive each one his brother from YOUR hearts.”

Matthew

24 Departing now, Jesus was on his way from the temple, but his disciples approached to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 In response he said to them: “Do YOU not behold all these things? Truly I say to YOU, By no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.”

3 While he was sitting upon the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, When will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence and of the conclusion of the system of things?”

4 And in answer Jesus said to them: “Look out that nobody misleads YOU; 5 for many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and will mislead many. 6 YOU are going to hear of wars and reports of wars; see that YOU are not terrified. For these things must take place, but the end is not yet.

7 “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another. 8 All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress.

9 “Then people will deliver YOU up to tribulation and will kill YOU, and YOU will be objects of hatred by all the nations on account of my name. 10 Then, also, many will be stumbled and will betray one another and will hate one another. 11 And many false prophets will arise and mislead many; 12 and because of the increasing of lawlessness the love of the greater number will cool off. 13 But he that has endured to the end is the one that will be saved. 14 And this good news of the kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations; and then the end will come.

15 “Therefore, when YOU catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation, as spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in a holy place, (let the reader use discernment,) 16 then let those in Ju·de′a begin fleeing to the mountains. 17 Let the man on the housetop not come down to take the goods out of his house; 18 and let the man in the field not return to the house to pick up his outer garment. 19 Woe to the pregnant women and those suckling a baby in those days! 20 Keep praying that YOUR flight may not occur in wintertime, nor on the sabbath day; 21 for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again. 22 In fact, unless those days were cut short, no flesh would be saved; but on account of the chosen ones those days will be cut short.

23 “Then if anyone says to YOU, ‘Look! Here is the Christ,’ or, ‘There!’ do not believe it. 24 For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will give great signs and wonders so as to mislead, if possible, even the chosen ones. 25 Look! I have forewarned YOU. 26 Therefore, if people say to YOU, ‘Look! He is in the wilderness,’ do not go out; ‘Look! He is in the inner chambers,’ do not believe it. 27 For just as the lightning comes out of eastern parts and shines over to western parts, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 28 Wherever the carcass is, there the eagles will be gathered together.

29 “Immediately after the tribulation of those days the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, and the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 30 And then the sign of the Son of man will appear in heaven, and then all the tribes of the earth will beat themselves in lamentation, and they will see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he will send forth his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

32 “Now learn from the fig tree as an illustration this point: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and it puts forth leaves, YOU know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also YOU, when YOU see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to YOU that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things occur. 35 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will by no means pass away.

36 “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father. 37 For just as the days of Noah were, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 38 For as they were in those days before the flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark; 39 and they took no note until the flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 40 Then two men will be in the field: one will be taken along and the other be abandoned; 41 two women will be grinding at the hand mill: one will be taken along and the other be abandoned. 42 Keep on the watch, therefore, because YOU do not know on what day YOUR Lord is coming.

43 “But know one thing, that if the householder had known in what watch the thief was coming, he would have kept awake and not allowed his house to be broken into. 44 On this account YOU too prove yourselves ready, because at an hour that YOU do not think to be it, the Son of man is coming.

45 “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on arriving finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to YOU, He will appoint him over all his belongings.

48 “But if ever that evil slave should say in his heart, ‘My master is delaying,’ 49 and should start to beat his fellow slaves and should eat and drink with the confirmed drunkards, 50 the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and in an hour that he does not know, 51 and will punish him with the greatest severity and will assign him his part with the hypocrites. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.

Matthew

28 After the sabbath, when it was growing light on the first day of the week, Mary Mag′da·lene and the other Mary came to view the grave.

2 And, notice! a great earthquake had taken place; for Jehovah’s angel had descended from heaven and approached and rolled away the stone, and was sitting on it. 3 His outward appearance was as lightning, and his clothing as white as snow. 4 Yes, for fear of him the watchmen trembled and became as dead men.

5 But the angel in answer said to the women: “Do not YOU be fearful, for I know YOU are looking for Jesus who was impaled. 6 He is not here, for he was raised up, as he said. Come, see the place where he was lying. 7 And go quickly and tell his disciples that he was raised up from the dead, and, look! he is going ahead of YOU into Gal′i·lee; there YOU will see him. Look! I have told YOU.”

8 So, quickly leaving the memorial tomb, with fear and great joy, they ran to report to his disciples. 9 And, look! Jesus met them and said: “Good day!” They approached and caught him by his feet and did obeisance to him. 10 Then Jesus said to them: “Have no fear! Go, report to my brothers, that they may go off into Gal′i·lee; and there they will see me.”

11 While they were on their way, look! some of the guard went into the city and reported to the chief priests all the things that had happened. 12 And after these had gathered together with the older men and taken counsel, they gave a sufficient number of silver pieces to the soldiers 13 and said: “Say, ‘His disciples came in the night and stole him while we were sleeping.’ 14 And if this gets to the governor’s ears, we will persuade him and will set YOU free from worry.” 15 So they took the silver pieces and did as they were instructed; and this saying has been spread abroad among the Jews up to this very day.

16 However, the eleven disciples went into Gal′i·lee to the mountain where Jesus had arranged for them, 17 and when they saw him they did obeisance, but some doubted. 18 And Jesus approached and spoke to them, saying: “All authority has been given me in heaven and on the earth. 19 Go therefore and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded YOU. And, look! I am with YOU all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Mark

4 And he again started teaching beside the sea. And a very great crowd gathered near him, so that he went aboard a boat and sat out on the sea, but all the crowd beside the sea were on the shore. 2 So he began to teach them many things with illustrations and to say to them in his teaching: 3 “Listen. Look! The sower went out to sow. 4 And as he was sowing, some seed fell alongside the road, and the birds came and ate it up. 5 And other seed fell upon the rocky place where it, of course, did not have much soil, and it immediately sprang up because of not having depth of soil. 6 But when the sun rose, it was scorched, and for not having root it withered. 7 And other seed fell among the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked it, and it yielded no fruit. 8 But others fell upon the fine soil, and, coming up and increasing, they began to yield fruit, and they were bearing thirtyfold, and sixty and a hundred.” 9 So he added the word: “Let him that has ears to listen listen.”

10 Now when he got to be alone, those around him with the twelve began questioning him on the illustrations. 11 And he proceeded to say to them: “To YOU the sacred secret of the kingdom of God has been given, but to those outside all things occur in illustrations, 12 in order that, though looking, they may look and yet not see, and, though hearing, they may hear and yet not get the sense of it, nor ever turn back and forgiveness be given them.” 13 Further, he said to them: “YOU do not know this illustration, and so how will YOU understand all the other illustrations?

14 “The sower sows the word. 15 These, then, are the ones alongside the road where the word is sown; but as soon as they have heard it Satan comes and takes away the word that was sown in them. 16 And likewise these are the ones sown upon the rocky places: as soon as they have heard the word, they accept it with joy. 17 Yet they have no root in themselves, but they continue for a time; then as soon as tribulation or persecution arises because of the word, they are stumbled. 18 There are still others who are sown among the thorns; these are the ones that have heard the word, 19 but the anxieties of this system of things and the deceptive power of riches and the desires for the rest of the things make inroads and choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful. 20 Finally, the ones that were sown on the fine soil are those who listen to the word and favorably receive it and bear fruit thirtyfold and sixty and a hundred.”

21 And he went on to say to them: “A lamp is not brought to be put under a measuring basket or under a bed, is it? It is brought to be put upon a lampstand, is it not? 22 For there is nothing hidden except for the purpose of being exposed; nothing has become carefully concealed but for the purpose of coming into the open. 23 Whoever has ears to listen, let him listen.”

24 He further said to them: “Pay attention to what YOU are hearing. With the measure that YOU are measuring out, YOU will have it measured out to YOU, yes, YOU will have more added to YOU. 25 For he that has will have more given to him; but he that does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.”

26 So he went on to say: “In this way the kingdom of God is just as when a man casts the seed upon the ground, 27 and he sleeps at night and rises up by day, and the seed sprouts and grows tall, just how he does not know. 28 Of its own self the ground bears fruit gradually, first the grass-blade, then the stalk head, finally the full grain in the head. 29 But as soon as the fruit permits it, he thrusts in the sickle, because the harvesttime has come.”

30 And he went on to say: “With what are we to liken the kingdom of God, or in what illustration shall we set it out? 31 Like a mustard grain, which at the time it was sown in the ground was the tiniest of all the seeds that are on the earth— 32 but when it has been sown, it comes up and becomes greater than all other vegetables and produces great branches, so that the birds of the heaven are able to find lodging under its shadow.”

33 So with many illustrations of that sort he would speak the word to them, as far as they were able to listen. 34 Indeed, without an illustration he would not speak to them, but privately to his disciples he would explain all things.

35 And on that day, when evening had fallen, he said to them: “Let us cross to the other shore.” 36 So, after they had dismissed the crowd, they took him in the boat, just as he was, and there were other boats with him. 37 Now a great violent windstorm broke out, and the waves kept dashing into the boat, so that the boat was close to being swamped. 38 But he was in the stern, sleeping upon a pillow. So they woke him up and said to him: “Teacher, do you not care that we are about to perish?” 39 With that he roused himself and rebuked the wind and said to the sea: “Hush! Be quiet!” And the wind abated, and a great calm set in. 40 So he said to them: “Why are YOU fainthearted? Do YOU not yet have any faith?” 41 But they felt an unusual fear, and they would say to one another: “Who really is this, because even the wind and the sea obey him?”

Mark

16 So when the sabbath had passed, Mary Mag′da·lene, and Mary the mother of James, and Sa·lo′me bought spices in order to come and grease him. 2 And very early on the first day of the week they came to the memorial tomb, when the sun had risen. 3 And they were saying one to another: “Who will roll the stone away from the door of the memorial tomb for us?” 4 But when they looked up, they beheld that the stone had been rolled away, although it was very large. 5 When they entered into the memorial tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side clothed in a white robe, and they were stunned. 6 He said to them: “Stop being stunned. YOU are looking for Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, who was impaled. He was raised up, he is not here. See! The place where they laid him. 7 But go, tell his disciples and Peter, ‘He is going ahead of YOU into Gal′i·lee; there YOU will see him, just as he told YOU.’” 8 So when they came out they fled from the memorial tomb, for trembling and strong emotion were gripping them. And they told nobody anything, for they were in fear.

SHORT CONCLUSION

Some late manuscripts and versions contain a short conclusion after Mark 16:8, as follows:

But all the things that had been commanded they related briefly to those around Peter. Further, after these things, Jesus himself sent out through them from the east to the west the holy and incorruptible proclamation of everlasting salvation.

LONG CONCLUSION

Certain ancient manuscripts (Codex Alexandrinus, Codex Ephraemi, Codex Bezae) and versions (Latin Vulgate, Curetonian Syriac, Syriac Peshitta) add the following long conclusion, but which Codex Sinaiticus, Codex Vaticanus, the Sinaitic Syriac codex, and the Armenian Version omit:

9 After he rose early on the first day of the week he appeared first to Mary Mag′da·lene, from whom he had expelled seven demons. 10 She went and reported to those who had been with him, as they were mourning and weeping. 11 But they, when they heard he had come to life and had been viewed by her, did not believe. 12 Moreover, after these things he appeared in another form to two of them walking along, as they were going into the country; 13 and they came back and reported to the rest. Neither did they believe these. 14 But later he appeared to the eleven themselves as they were reclining at the table, and he reproached their lack of faith and hardheartedness, because they did not believe those who had beheld him now raised up from the dead. 15 And he said to them: “Go into all the world and preach the good news to all creation. 16 He that believes and is baptized will be saved, but he that does not believe will be condemned. 17 Furthermore, these signs will accompany those believing: By the use of my name they will expel demons, they will speak with tongues, 18 and with their hands they will pick up serpents, and if they drink anything deadly it will not hurt them at all. They will lay their hands upon sick persons, and these will become well.”

19 So, then, the Lord Jesus, after having spoken to them, was taken up to heaven and sat down at the right hand of God. 20 They, accordingly, went out and preached everywhere, while the Lord worked with them and backed up the message through the accompanying signs.

Luke

6 Now on a sabbath he happened to be passing through grainfields, and his disciples were plucking and eating the heads of grain, rubbing them with their hands. 2 At this some of the Pharisees said: “Why are YOU doing what is not lawful on the sabbath?” 3 But Jesus said in reply to them: “Have YOU never read the very thing David did when he and the men with him got hungry? 4 How he entered into the house of God and received the loaves of presentation and ate and gave some to the men with him, which it is lawful for no one to eat but for the priests only?” 5 And he went on to say to them: “Lord of the sabbath is what the Son of man is.”

6 In the course of another sabbath he entered into the synagogue and began teaching. And there was a man present whose right hand was withered. 7 The scribes and the Pharisees were now watching him closely to see whether he would cure on the sabbath, in order to find some way to accuse him. 8 He, however, knew their reasonings, yet he said to the man with the withered hand: “Get up and stand in the center.” And he rose and took his stand. 9 Then Jesus said to them: “I ask YOU men, Is it lawful on the sabbath to do good or to do injury, to save or to destroy a soul?” 10 And after looking around at them all, he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” He did so, and his hand was restored. 11 But they became filled with madness, and they began to talk over with one another what they might do to Jesus.

12 In the progress of these days he went out into the mountain to pray, and he continued the whole night in prayer to God. 13 But when it became day he called his disciples to him and chose from among them twelve, whom he also named “apostles”: 14 Simon, whom he also named Peter, and Andrew his brother, and James and John, and Philip and Bar·thol′o·mew, 15 and Matthew and Thomas, and James the son of Al·phae′us, and Simon who is called “the zealous one,” 16 and Judas the son of James, and Judas Is·car′i·ot, who turned traitor.

17 And he came down with them and took his station on a level place, and there was a great crowd of his disciples, and a great multitude of people from all of Ju·de′a and Jerusalem and the maritime country of Tyre and Si′don, who came to hear him and be healed of their sicknesses. 18 Even those troubled with unclean spirits were cured. 19 And all the crowd were seeking to touch him, because power was going out of him and healing them all.

20 And he lifted up his eyes upon his disciples and began to say:

“Happy are YOU poor, because YOURS is the kingdom of God.

21 “Happy are YOU who hunger now, because YOU will be filled.

“Happy are YOU who weep now, because YOU will laugh.

22 “Happy are YOU whenever men hate YOU, and whenever they exclude YOU and reproach YOU and cast out YOUR name as wicked for the sake of the Son of man. 23 Rejoice in that day and leap, for, look! YOUR reward is great in heaven, for those are the same things their forefathers used to do to the prophets.

24 “But woe to YOU rich persons, because YOU are having YOUR consolation in full.

25 “Woe to YOU who are filled up now, because YOU will go hungry.

“Woe, YOU who are laughing now, because YOU will mourn and weep.

26 “Woe, whenever all men speak well of YOU, for things like these are what their forefathers did to the false prophets.

27 “But I say to YOU who are listening, Continue to love YOUR enemies, to do good to those hating YOU, 28 to bless those cursing YOU, to pray for those who are insulting YOU. 29 To him that strikes you on the one cheek, offer the other also; and from him that takes away your outer garment, do not withhold even the undergarment. 30 Give to everyone asking you, and from the one taking your things away do not ask them back.

31 “Also, just as YOU want men to do to YOU, do the same way to them.

32 “And if YOU love those loving YOU, of what credit is it to YOU? For even the sinners love those loving them. 33 And if YOU do good to those doing good to YOU, really of what credit is it to YOU? Even the sinners do the same. 34 Also, if YOU lend without interest to those from whom YOU hope to receive, of what credit is it to YOU? Even sinners lend without interest to sinners that they may get back as much. 35 To the contrary, continue to love YOUR enemies and to do good and to lend without interest, not hoping for anything back; and YOUR reward will be great, and YOU will be sons of the Most High, because he is kind toward the unthankful and wicked. 36 Continue becoming merciful, just as YOUR Father is merciful.

37 “Moreover, stop judging, and YOU will by no means be judged; and stop condemning, and YOU will by no means be condemned. Keep on releasing, and YOU will be released. 38 Practice giving, and people will give to YOU. They will pour into YOUR laps a fine measure, pressed down, shaken together and overflowing. For with the measure that YOU are measuring out, they will measure out to YOU in return.”

39 Then he also spoke an illustration to them: “A blind man cannot guide a blind man, can he? Both will tumble into a pit, will they not? 40 A pupil is not above his teacher, but everyone that is perfectly instructed will be like his teacher. 41 Why, then, do you look at the straw that is in your brother’s eye, but do not observe the rafter that is in your own eye? 42 How can you say to your brother, ‘Brother, allow me to extract the straw that is in your eye,’ while you yourself are not looking at the rafter in that eye of yours? Hypocrite! First extract the rafter from your own eye, and then you will see clearly how to extract the straw that is in your brother’s eye.

43 “For there is not a fine tree producing rotten fruit; again there is not a rotten tree producing fine fruit. 44 For each tree is known by its own fruit. For example, people do not gather figs from thorns, nor do they cut grapes off a thornbush. 45 A good man brings forth good out of the good treasure of his heart, but a wicked man brings forth what is wicked out of his wicked treasure; for out of the heart’s abundance his mouth speaks.

46 “Why, then, do YOU call me ‘Lord! Lord!’ but do not do the things I say? 47 Everyone that comes to me and hears my words and does them, I will show YOU whom he is like: 48 He is like a man building a house, who dug and went down deep and laid a foundation upon the rock-mass. Consequently, when a flood arose, the river dashed against that house, but was not strong enough to shake it, because of its being well built. 49 On the other hand, he who hears and does not do, is like a man who built a house upon the ground without a foundation. Against it the river dashed, and immediately it collapsed, and the ruin of that house became great.”

Luke

11 Now on the occasion of his being in a certain place praying, when he stopped, a certain one of his disciples said to him: “Lord, teach us how to pray, just as John also taught his disciples.”

2 Then he said to them: “Whenever YOU pray, say, ‘Father, let your name be sanctified. Let your kingdom come. 3 Give us our bread for the day according to the day’s requirement. 4 And forgive us our sins, for we ourselves also forgive everyone that is in debt to us; and do not bring us into temptation.’”

5 Further, he said to them: “Who of YOU will have a friend and will go to him at midnight and say to him, ‘Friend, loan me three loaves, 6 because a friend of mine has just come to me on a journey and I have nothing to set before him’? 7 And that one from inside says in reply, ‘Quit making me trouble. The door is already locked, and my young children are with me in bed; I cannot rise up and give you anything.’ 8 I tell YOU, Although he will not rise up and give him anything because of being his friend, certainly because of his bold persistence he will get up and give him what things he needs. 9 Accordingly I say to YOU, Keep on asking, and it will be given YOU; keep on seeking, and YOU will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to YOU. 10 For everyone asking receives, and everyone seeking finds, and to everyone knocking it will be opened. 11 Indeed, which father is there among YOU who, if his son asks for a fish, will perhaps hand him a serpent instead of a fish? 12 Or if he also asks for an egg, will hand him a scorpion? 13 Therefore, if YOU, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to YOUR children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

14 Later he was expelling a dumb demon. After the demon came out, the dumb man spoke. And the crowds marveled. 15 But certain ones of them said: “He expels the demons by means of Be·el′ze·bub the ruler of the demons.” 16 However, others, to tempt him, began seeking a sign out of heaven from him. 17 Knowing their imaginations he said to them: “Every kingdom divided against itself comes to desolation, and a house divided against itself falls. 18 So if Satan is also divided against himself, how will his kingdom stand? Because YOU say I expel the demons by means of Be·el′ze·bub. 19 If it is by means of Be·el′ze·bub I expel the demons, by whom do YOUR sons expel them? Because of this they will be judges of YOU. 20 But if it is by means of God’s finger I expel the demons, the kingdom of God has really overtaken YOU. 21 When a strong man, well armed, guards his palace, his belongings continue in peace. 22 But when someone stronger than he is comes against him and conquers him, he takes away his full armament in which he was trusting, and he divides out the things he despoiled him of. 23 He that is not on my side is against me, and he that does not gather with me scatters.

24 “When an unclean spirit comes out of a man, it passes through parched places in search of a resting-place, and, after finding none, it says, ‘I will return to my house out of which I moved.’ 25 And on arriving it finds it swept clean and adorned. 26 Then it goes its way and takes along seven different spirits more wicked than itself, and, after getting inside, they dwell there; and the final circumstances of that man become worse than the first.”

27 Now as he was saying these things a certain woman out of the crowd raised her voice and said to him: “Happy is the womb that carried you and the breasts that you sucked!” 28 But he said: “No, rather, Happy are those hearing the word of God and keeping it!”

29 When the crowds were massing together, he started to say: “This generation is a wicked generation; it looks for a sign. But no sign will be given it except the sign of Jo′nah. 30 For just as Jo′nah became a sign to the Nin′e·vites, in the same way will the Son of man be also to this generation. 31 The queen of the south will be raised up in the judgment with the men of this generation and will condemn them; because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Sol′o·mon, but, look! something more than Sol′o·mon is here. 32 The men of Nin′e·veh will rise in the judgment with this generation and will condemn it; because they repented at what Jo′nah preached; but, look! something more than Jo′nah is here. 33 After lighting a lamp, a person puts it, not in a vault nor under a measuring basket, but upon the lampstand, that those stepping in may behold the light. 34 The lamp of the body is your eye. When your eye is simple, your whole body is also bright; but when it is wicked, your body is also dark. 35 Be alert, therefore. Perhaps the light that is in you is darkness. 36 Therefore, if your whole body is bright with no part at all dark, it will all be as bright as when a lamp gives you light by its rays.”

37 When he had spoken this, a Pharisee requested him to dine with him. So he went in and reclined at the table. 38 However, the Pharisee was surprised at seeing that he did not first wash before the dinner. 39 But the Lord said to him: “Now YOU Pharisees, YOU cleanse the outside of the cup and dish, but the inside of YOU is full of plunder and wickedness. 40 Unreasonable persons! He that made the outside made also the inside, did he not? 41 Nevertheless, give as gifts of mercy the things that are inside, and, look! all other things are clean about YOU. 42 But woe to YOU Pharisees, because YOU give the tenth of the mint and the rue and of every other vegetable, but YOU pass by the justice and the love of God! These things YOU were under obligation to do, but those other things not to omit. 43 Woe to YOU Pharisees, because YOU love the front seats in the synagogues and the greetings in the marketplaces! 44 Woe to YOU, because YOU are as those memorial tombs which are not in evidence, so that men walk upon them and do not know it!”

45 In answer a certain one of those versed in the Law said to him: “Teacher, in saying these things you also insult us.” 46 Then he said: “Woe also to YOU who are versed in the Law, because YOU load men with loads hard to be borne, but YOU yourselves do not touch the loads with one of YOUR fingers!

47 “Woe to YOU, because YOU build the memorial tombs of the prophets, but YOUR forefathers killed them! 48 Certainly YOU are witnesses of the deeds of YOUR forefathers and yet YOU give consent to them, because these killed the prophets but YOU are building their tombs. 49 On this account the wisdom of God also said, ‘I will send forth to them prophets and apostles, and they will kill and persecute some of them, 50 so that the blood of all the prophets spilled from the founding of the world may be required from this generation, 51 from the blood of Abel down to the blood of Zech·a·ri′ah, who was slain between the altar and the house.’ Yes, I tell YOU, it will be required from this generation.

52 “Woe to YOU who are versed in the Law, because YOU took away the key of knowledge; YOU yourselves did not go in, and those going in YOU hindered!”

53 So when he went out from there the scribes and the Pharisees started in to press upon him terribly and to ply him with questions about further things, 54 lying in wait for him, to catch something out of his mouth.

Luke

21 Now as he looked up he saw the rich dropping their gifts into the treasury chests. 2 Then he saw a certain needy widow drop two small coins of very little value there, 3 and he said: “I tell YOU truthfully, This widow, although poor, dropped in more than they all did. 4 For all these dropped in gifts out of their surplus, but this woman out of her want dropped in all the means of living she had.”

5 Later, as certain ones were speaking concerning the temple, how it was adorned with fine stones and dedicated things, 6 he said: “As for these things that YOU are beholding, the days will come in which not a stone upon a stone will be left here and not be thrown down.” 7 Then they questioned him, saying: “Teacher, when will these things actually be, and what will be the sign when these things are destined to occur?” 8 He said: “Look out that YOU are not misled; for many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am he,’ and, ‘The due time has approached.’ Do not go after them. 9 Furthermore, when YOU hear of wars and disorders, do not be terrified. For these things must occur first, but the end does not occur immediately.”

10 Then he went on to say to them: “Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; 11 and there will be great earthquakes, and in one place after another pestilences and food shortages; and there will be fearful sights and from heaven great signs.

12 “But before all these things people will lay their hands upon YOU and persecute YOU, delivering YOU up to the synagogues and prisons, YOU being haled before kings and governors for the sake of my name. 13 It will turn out to YOU for a witness. 14 Therefore settle it in YOUR hearts not to rehearse beforehand how to make YOUR defense, 15 for I will give YOU a mouth and wisdom, which all YOUR opposers together will not be able to resist or dispute. 16 Moreover, YOU will be delivered up even by parents and brothers and relatives and friends, and they will put some of YOU to death; 17 and YOU will be objects of hatred by all people because of my name. 18 And yet not a hair of YOUR heads will by any means perish. 19 By endurance on YOUR part YOU will acquire YOUR souls.

20 “Furthermore, when YOU see Jerusalem surrounded by encamped armies, then know that the desolating of her has drawn near. 21 Then let those in Ju·de′a begin fleeing to the mountains, and let those in the midst of her withdraw, and let those in the country places not enter into her; 22 because these are days for meting out justice, that all the things written may be fulfilled. 23 Woe to the pregnant women and the ones suckling a baby in those days! For there will be great necessity upon the land and wrath on this people; 24 and they will fall by the edge of the sword and be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem will be trampled on by the nations, until the appointed times of the nations are fulfilled.

25 “Also, there will be signs in sun and moon and stars, and on the earth anguish of nations, not knowing the way out because of the roaring of the sea and its agitation, 26 while men become faint out of fear and expectation of the things coming upon the inhabited earth; for the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 27 And then they will see the Son of man coming in a cloud with power and great glory. 28 But as these things start to occur, raise yourselves erect and lift YOUR heads up, because YOUR deliverance is getting near.”

29 With that he spoke an illustration to them: “Note the fig tree and all the other trees: 30 When they are already in the bud, by observing it YOU know for yourselves that now the summer is near. 31 In this way YOU also, when YOU see these things occurring, know that the kingdom of God is near. 32 Truly I say to YOU, This generation will by no means pass away until all things occur. 33 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will by no means pass away.

34 “But pay attention to yourselves that YOUR hearts never become weighed down with overeating and heavy drinking and anxieties of life, and suddenly that day be instantly upon YOU 35 as a snare. For it will come in upon all those dwelling upon the face of all the earth. 36 Keep awake, then, all the time making supplication that YOU may succeed in escaping all these things that are destined to occur, and in standing before the Son of man.”

37 So by day he would be teaching in the temple, but by night he would go out and lodge on the mountain called the Mount of Olives. 38 And all the people would come early in the day to him in the temple to hear him.

Luke

24 On the first day of the week, however, they went very early to the tomb, bearing the spices they had prepared. 2 But they found the stone rolled away from the memorial tomb, 3 and when they entered they did not find the body of the Lord Jesus. 4 While they were in perplexity over this, look! two men in flashing clothing stood by them. 5 As the women became frightened and kept their faces turned to the ground, the men said to them: “Why are YOU looking for the living One among the dead? 6 [[He is not here, but has been raised up.]] Recall how he spoke to YOU while he was yet in Gal′i·lee, 7 saying that the Son of man must be delivered into the hands of sinful men and be impaled and yet on the third day rise.” 8 So they called his sayings to mind, 9 and they returned from the memorial tomb and reported all these things to the eleven and to all the rest. 10 They were the Mag′da·lene Mary, and Jo·an′na, and Mary the mother of James. Also, the rest of the women with them were telling the apostles these things. 11 However, these sayings appeared as nonsense to them and they would not believe the women.

12 [[But Peter rose and ran to the memorial tomb, and, stooping forward, he beheld the bandages alone. So he went off, wondering within himself at what had occurred.]]

13 But, look! on that very day two of them were journeying to a village about seven miles distant from Jerusalem and named Em·ma′us, 14 and they were conversing with each other over all these things that had come about.

15 Now as they were conversing and discussing, Jesus himself approached and began walking with them; 16 but their eyes were kept from recognizing him. 17 He said to them: “What are these matters that YOU are debating between yourselves as YOU walk along?” And they stood still with sad faces. 18 In answer the one named Cle′o·pas said to him: “Are you dwelling as an alien by yourself in Jerusalem and so do not know the things that have occurred in her in these days?” 19 And he said to them: “What things?” They said to him: “The things concerning Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, who became a prophet powerful in work and word before God and all the people; 20 and how our chief priests and rulers handed him over to the sentence of death and impaled him. 21 But we were hoping that this man was the one destined to deliver Israel; yes, and besides all these things, this makes the third day since these things occurred. 22 Moreover, certain women from among us also astonished us, because they had been early to the memorial tomb 23 but did not find his body and they came saying they had also seen a supernatural sight of angels, who said he is alive. 24 Further, some of those with us went off to the memorial tomb; and they found it so, just as the women had said, but they did not see him.”

25 So he said to them: “O senseless ones and slow in heart to believe on all the things the prophets spoke! 26 Was it not necessary for the Christ to suffer these things and to enter into his glory?” 27 And commencing at Moses and all the Prophets he interpreted to them things pertaining to himself in all the Scriptures.

28 Finally they got close to the village where they were journeying, and he made as if he was journeying on farther. 29 But they used pressure upon him, saying: “Stay with us, because it is toward evening and the day has already declined.” With that he went in to stay with them. 30 And as he was reclining with them at the meal he took the loaf, blessed it, broke it and began to hand it to them. 31 At that their eyes were fully opened and they recognized him; and he disappeared from them. 32 And they said to each other: “Were not our hearts burning as he was speaking to us on the road, as he was fully opening up the Scriptures to us?” 33 And in that very hour they rose and returned to Jerusalem, and they found the eleven and those with them assembled together, 34 saying: “For a fact the Lord was raised up and he appeared to Simon!” 35 Now they themselves related the events on the road and how he became known to them by the breaking of the loaf.

36 While they were speaking of these things he himself stood in their midst [[and said to them: “May YOU have peace.”]] 37 But because they were terrified, and had become frightened, they were imagining they beheld a spirit. 38 So he said to them: “Why are YOU troubled, and why is it doubts come up in YOUR hearts? 39 See my hands and my feet, that it is I myself; feel me and see, because a spirit does not have flesh and bones just as YOU behold that I have.” 40 [[And as he said this he showed them his hands and his feet.]] 41 But while they were still not believing for sheer joy and were wondering, he said to them: “Do YOU have something there to eat?” 42 And they handed him a piece of broiled fish; 43 and he took it and ate it before their eyes.

44 He now said to them: “These are my words which I spoke to YOU while I was yet with YOU, that all the things written in the law of Moses and in the Prophets and Psalms about me must be fulfilled.” 45 Then he opened up their minds fully to grasp the meaning of the Scriptures, 46 and he said to them: “In this way it is written that the Christ would suffer and rise from among the dead on the third day, 47 and on the basis of his name repentance for forgiveness of sins would be preached in all the nations—starting out from Jerusalem, 48 YOU are to be witnesses of these things. 49 And, look! I am sending forth upon YOU that which is promised by my Father. YOU, though, abide in the city until YOU become clothed with power from on high.”

50 But he led them out as far as Beth′a·ny, and he lifted up his hands and blessed them. 51 As he was blessing them he was parted from them and began to be borne up to heaven. 52 And they did obeisance to him and returned to Jerusalem with great joy. 53 And they were continually in the temple blessing God.

John

3 Now there was a man of the Pharisees, Nic·o·de′mus was his name, a ruler of the Jews. 2 This one came to him in the night and said to him: “Rabbi, we know that you as a teacher have come from God; for no one can perform these signs that you perform unless God is with him.” 3 In answer Jesus said to him: “Most truly I say to you, Unless anyone is born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.” 4 Nic·o·de′mus said to him: “How can a man be born when he is old? He cannot enter into the womb of his mother a second time and be born, can he?” 5 Jesus answered: “Most truly I say to you, Unless anyone is born from water and spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God. 6 What has been born from the flesh is flesh, and what has been born from the spirit is spirit. 7 Do not marvel because I told you, YOU people must be born again. 8 The wind blows where it wants to, and you hear the sound of it, but you do not know where it comes from and where it is going. So is everyone that has been born from the spirit.”

9 In answer Nic·o·de′mus said to him: “How can these things come about?” 10 In answer Jesus said to him: “Are you a teacher of Israel and yet do not know these things? 11 Most truly I say to you, What we know we speak and what we have seen we bear witness of, but YOU people do not receive the witness we give. 12 If I have told YOU earthly things and yet YOU do not believe, how will YOU believe if I tell YOU heavenly things? 13 Moreover, no man has ascended into heaven but he that descended from heaven, the Son of man. 14 And just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so the Son of man must be lifted up, 15 that everyone believing in him may have everlasting life.

16 “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, in order that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life. 17 For God sent forth his Son into the world, not for him to judge the world, but for the world to be saved through him. 18 He that exercises faith in him is not to be judged. He that does not exercise faith has been judged already, because he has not exercised faith in the name of the only-begotten Son of God. 19 Now this is the basis for judgment, that the light has come into the world but men have loved the darkness rather than the light, for their works were wicked. 20 For he that practices vile things hates the light and does not come to the light, in order that his works may not be reproved. 21 But he that does what is true comes to the light, in order that his works may be made manifest as having been worked in harmony with God.”

22 After these things Jesus and his disciples went into Ju·de′an country, and there he spent some time with them and did baptizing. 23 But John also was baptizing in Ae′non near Sa′lim, because there was a great quantity of water there, and people kept coming and being baptized; 24 for John had not yet been thrown into prison.

25 Therefore a dispute arose on the part of the disciples of John with a Jew concerning purification. 26 So they came to John and said to him: “Rabbi, the man that was with you across the Jordan, to whom you have borne witness, see, this one is baptizing and all are going to him.” 27 In answer John said: “A man cannot receive a single thing unless it has been given him from heaven. 28 YOU yourselves bear me witness that I said, I am not the Christ, but, I have been sent forth in advance of that one. 29 He that has the bride is the bridegroom. However, the friend of the bridegroom, when he stands and hears him, has a great deal of joy on account of the voice of the bridegroom. Therefore this joy of mine has been made full. 30 That one must go on increasing, but I must go on decreasing.”

31 He that comes from above is over all others. He that is from the earth is from the earth and speaks of things of the earth. He that comes from heaven is over all others. 32 What he has seen and heard, of this he bears witness, but no man is accepting his witness. 33 He that has accepted his witness has put his seal to it that God is true. 34 For the one whom God sent forth speaks the sayings of God, for he does not give the spirit by measure. 35 The Father loves the Son and has given all things into his hand. 36 He that exercises faith in the Son has everlasting life; he that disobeys the Son will not see life, but the wrath of God remains upon him.

John

15 “I am the true vine, and my Father is the cultivator. 2 Every branch in me not bearing fruit he takes away, and every one bearing fruit he cleans, that it may bear more fruit. 3 YOU are already clean because of the word that I have spoken to YOU. 4 Remain in union with me, and I in union with YOU. Just as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself unless it remains in the vine, in the same way neither can YOU, unless YOU remain in union with me. 5 I am the vine, YOU are the branches. He that remains in union with me, and I in union with him, this one bears much fruit; because apart from me YOU can do nothing at all. 6 If anyone does not remain in union with me, he is cast out as a branch and is dried up; and men gather those branches up and pitch them into the fire and they are burned. 7 If YOU remain in union with me and my sayings remain in YOU, ask whatever YOU wish and it will take place for YOU. 8 My Father is glorified in this, that YOU keep bearing much fruit and prove yourselves my disciples. 9 Just as the Father has loved me and I have loved YOU, remain in my love. 10 If YOU observe my commandments, YOU will remain in my love, just as I have observed the commandments of the Father and remain in his love.

11 “These things I have spoken to YOU, that my joy may be in YOU and YOUR joy may be made full. 12 This is my commandment, that YOU love one another just as I have loved YOU. 13 No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his soul in behalf of his friends. 14 YOU are my friends if YOU do what I am commanding YOU. 15 I no longer call YOU slaves, because a slave does not know what his master does. But I have called YOU friends, because all the things I have heard from my Father I have made known to YOU. 16 YOU did not choose me, but I chose YOU, and I appointed YOU to go on and keep bearing fruit and that YOUR fruit should remain; in order that no matter what YOU ask the Father in my name he might give it to YOU.

17 “These things I command YOU, that YOU love one another. 18 If the world hates YOU, YOU know that it has hated me before it hated YOU. 19 If YOU were part of the world, the world would be fond of what is its own. Now because YOU are no part of the world, but I have chosen YOU out of the world, on this account the world hates YOU. 20 Bear in mind the word I said to YOU, A slave is not greater than his master. If they have persecuted me, they will persecute YOU also; if they have observed my word, they will observe YOURS also. 21 But they will do all these things against YOU on account of my name, because they do not know him that sent me. 22 If I had not come and spoken to them, they would have no sin; but now they have no excuse for their sin. 23 He that hates me hates also my Father. 24 If I had not done among them the works that no one else did, they would have no sin; but now they have both seen and hated me as well as my Father. 25 But it is that the word written in their Law may be fulfilled, ‘They hated me without cause.’ 26 When the helper arrives that I will send YOU from the Father, the spirit of the truth, which proceeds from the Father, that one will bear witness about me; 27 and YOU, in turn, are to bear witness, because YOU have been with me from when I began.

Acts of Apostles

1 The first account, O The·oph′i·lus, I composed about all the things Jesus started both to do and to teach, 2 until the day that he was taken up, after he had given commandment through holy spirit to the apostles whom he chose. 3 To these also by many positive proofs he showed himself alive after he had suffered, being seen by them throughout forty days and telling the things about the kingdom of God. 4 And while he was meeting with them he gave them the orders: “Do not withdraw from Jerusalem, but keep waiting for what the Father has promised, about which YOU heard from me; 5 because John, indeed, baptized with water, but YOU will be baptized in holy spirit not many days after this.”

6 When, now, they had assembled, they went asking him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?” 7 He said to them: “It does not belong to YOU to get knowledge of the times or seasons which the Father has placed in his own jurisdiction; 8 but YOU will receive power when the holy spirit arrives upon YOU, and YOU will be witnesses of me both in Jerusalem and in all Ju·de′a and Sa·mar′i·a and to the most distant part of the earth.” 9 And after he had said these things, while they were looking on, he was lifted up and a cloud caught him up from their vision. 10 And as they were gazing into the sky while he was on his way, also, look! two men in white garments stood alongside them, 11 and they said: “Men of Gal′i·lee, why do YOU stand looking into the sky? This Jesus who was received up from YOU into the sky will come thus in the same manner as YOU have beheld him going into the sky.”

12 Then they returned to Jerusalem from a mountain called the Mount of Olives, which is near Jerusalem, being a sabbath day’s journey away. 13 So, when they had entered, they went up into the upper chamber, where they were staying, Peter as well as John and James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bar·thol′o·mew and Matthew, James the son of Al·phae′us and Simon the zealous one, and Judas the son of James. 14 With one accord all these were persisting in prayer, together with some women and Mary the mother of Jesus and with his brothers.

15 Now during these days Peter rose up in the midst of the brothers and said (the crowd of persons was all together about one hundred and twenty): 16 “Men, brothers, it was necessary for the scripture to be fulfilled, which the holy spirit spoke beforehand by David’s mouth about Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus, 17 because he had been numbered among us and he obtained a share in this ministry. 18 (This very man, therefore, purchased a field with the wages for unrighteousness, and pitching head foremost he noisily burst in his midst and all his intestines were poured out. 19 It also became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that that field was called in their language A·kel′da·ma, that is, Field of Blood.) 20 For it is written in the book of Psalms, ‘Let his lodging place become desolate, and let there be no dweller in it,’ and, ‘His office of oversight let someone else take.’ 21 It is therefore necessary that of the men that assembled with us during all the time in which the Lord Jesus went in and out among us, 22 starting with his baptism by John and until the day he was received up from us, one of these men should become a witness with us of his resurrection.”

23 So they put up two, Joseph called Bar′sab·bas, who was surnamed Justus, and Mat·thi′as. 24 And they prayed and said: “You, O Jehovah, who know the hearts of all, designate which one of these two men you have chosen, 25 to take the place of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas deviated to go to his own place.” 26 So they cast lots over them, and the lot fell upon Mat·thi′as; and he was reckoned along with the eleven apostles.

Acts

13 Now in Antioch there were prophets and teachers in the local congregation, Bar′na·bas as well as Sym′e·on who was called Ni′ger, and Lucius of Cy·re′ne, and Man′a·en who was educated with Herod the district ruler, and Saul. 2 As they were publicly ministering to Jehovah and fasting, the holy spirit said: “Of all persons set Bar′na·bas and Saul apart for me for the work to which I have called them.” 3 Then they fasted and prayed and laid their hands upon them and let them go.

4 Accordingly these men, sent out by the holy spirit, went down to Se·leu′cia, and from there they sailed away to Cy′prus. 5 And when they got to be in Sal′a·mis they began publishing the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. They had John also as an attendant.

6 When they had gone through the whole island as far as Pa′phos, they met up with a certain man, a sorcerer, a false prophet, a Jew whose name was Bar-Je′sus, 7 and he was with the proconsul Sergius Paulus, an intelligent man. Calling Bar′na·bas and Saul to him, this man earnestly sought to hear the word of God. 8 But El′y·mas the sorcerer (that, in fact, is the way his name is translated) began opposing them, seeking to turn the proconsul away from the faith. 9 Saul, who is also Paul, becoming filled with holy spirit, looked at him intently 10 and said: “O man full of every sort of fraud and every sort of villainy, you son of the Devil, you enemy of everything righteous, will you not quit distorting the right ways of Jehovah? 11 Well, then, look! Jehovah’s hand is upon you, and you will be blind, not seeing the sunlight for a period of time.” Instantly a thick mist and darkness fell upon him, and he went around seeking men to lead him by the hand. 12 Then the proconsul, upon seeing what had happened, became a believer, as he was astounded at the teaching of Jehovah.

13 The men, together with Paul, now put out to sea from Pa′phos and arrived at Perga in Pam·phyl′i·a. But John withdrew from them and returned to Jerusalem. 14 They, however, went on from Perga and came to Antioch in Pi·sid′i·a and, going into the synagogue on the sabbath day, they took a seat. 15 After the public reading of the Law and of the Prophets the presiding officers of the synagogue sent out to them, saying: “Men, brothers, if there is any word of encouragement for the people that YOU have, tell it.” 16 So Paul rose, and motioning with his hand, he said:

“Men, Israelites and YOU others that fear God, hear. 17 The God of this people Israel chose our forefathers, and he exalted the people during their alien residence in the land of Egypt and brought them out of it with an uplifted arm. 18 And for a period of about forty years he put up with their manner of action in the wilderness. 19 After destroying seven nations in the land of Ca′naan, he distributed the land of them by lot: 20 all that during about four hundred and fifty years.

“And after these things he gave them judges until Samuel the prophet. 21 But from then on they demanded a king, and God gave them Saul son of Kish, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, for forty years. 22 And after removing him, he raised up for them David as king, respecting whom he bore witness and said, ‘I have found David the son of Jes′se, a man agreeable to my heart, who will do all the things I desire.’ 23 From the offspring of this man according to his promise God has brought to Israel a savior, Jesus, 24 after John, in advance of the entry of that One, had preached publicly to all the people of Israel baptism in symbol of repentance. 25 But as John was fulfilling his course, he would say, ‘What do YOU suppose I am? I am not he. But, look! one is coming after me the sandals of whose feet I am not worthy to untie.’

26 “Men, brothers, YOU sons of the stock of Abraham and those others among YOU who fear God, the word of this salvation has been sent forth to us. 27 For the inhabitants of Jerusalem and their rulers did not know this One, but, when acting as judges, they fulfilled the things voiced by the Prophets, which things are read aloud every Sabbath, 28 and, although they found no cause for death, they demanded of Pilate that he be executed. 29 When, now, they had accomplished all the things written about him, they took him down from the stake and laid him in a memorial tomb. 30 But God raised him up from the dead; 31 and for many days he became visible to those who had gone up with him from Gal′i·lee to Jerusalem, who are now his witnesses to the people.

32 “And so we are declaring to YOU the good news about the promise made to the forefathers, 33 that God has entirely fulfilled it to us their children in that he resurrected Jesus; even as it is written in the second psalm, ‘You are my son, I have become your Father this day.’ 34 And that fact that he resurrected him from the dead destined no more to return to corruption, he has stated in this way, ‘I will give YOU people the loving-kindnesses to David that are faithful.’ 35 Hence he also says in another psalm, ‘You will not allow your loyal one to see corruption.’ 36 For David, on the one hand, served the express will of God in his own generation and fell asleep in death and was laid with his forefathers and did see corruption. 37 On the other hand, he whom God raised up did not see corruption.

38 “Let it therefore be known to YOU, brothers, that through this One a forgiveness of sins is being published to YOU; 39 and that from all the things from which YOU could not be declared guiltless by means of the law of Moses, everyone who believes is declared guiltless by means of this One. 40 Therefore see to it that what is said in the Prophets does not come upon YOU, 41 ‘Behold it, YOU scorners, and wonder at it, and vanish away, because I am working a work in YOUR days, a work that YOU will by no means believe even if anyone relates it to YOU in detail.’”

42 Now when they were going out, the people began entreating for these matters to be spoken to them on the following sabbath. 43 So after the synagogue assembly was dissolved, many of the Jews and of the proselytes who worshiped God followed Paul and Bar′na·bas, who in speaking to them began urging them to continue in the undeserved kindness of God.

44 The next sabbath nearly all the city gathered together to hear the word of Jehovah. 45 When the Jews got sight of the crowds, they were filled with jealousy and began blasphemously contradicting the things being spoken by Paul. 46 And so, talking with boldness, Paul and Bar′na·bas said: “It was necessary for the word of God to be spoken first to YOU. Since YOU are thrusting it away from YOU and do not judge yourselves worthy of everlasting life, look! we turn to the nations. 47 In fact, Jehovah has laid commandment upon us in these words, ‘I have appointed you as a light of nations, for you to be a salvation to the extremity of the earth.’”

48 When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers. 49 Furthermore, the word of Jehovah went on being carried throughout the whole country. 50 But the Jews stirred up the reputable women who worshiped God and the principal men of the city, and they raised up a persecution against Paul and Bar′na·bas and threw them outside their boundaries. 51 These shook the dust off their feet against them and went to I·co′ni·um. 52 And the disciples continued to be filled with joy and holy spirit.

Acts

14 Now in I·co′ni·um they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews and spoke in such a manner that a great multitude of both Jews and Greeks became believers. 2 But the Jews that did not believe stirred up and wrongly influenced the souls of people of the nations against the brothers. 3 Therefore they spent considerable time speaking with boldness by the authority of Jehovah, who bore witness to the word of his undeserved kindness by granting signs and portents to occur through their hands. 4 However, the multitude of the city was split, and some were for the Jews but others for the apostles. 5 Now when a violent attempt took place on the part of both people of the nations and Jews with their rulers, to treat them insolently and pelt them with stones, 6 they, on being informed of it, fled to the cities of Lyc·a·o′ni·a, Lys′tra and Der′be and the country round about; 7 and there they went on declaring the good news.

8 Now in Lys′tra there was sitting a certain man disabled in his feet, lame from his mother’s womb, and he had never walked at all. 9 This man was listening to Paul speak, who, on looking at him intently and seeing he had faith to be made well, 10 said with a loud voice: “Stand up erect on your feet.” And he leaped up and began walking. 11 And the crowds, seeing what Paul had done, raised their voices, saying in the Lyc·a·o′ni·an tongue: “The gods have become like humans and have come down to us!” 12 And they went calling Bar′na·bas Zeus, but Paul Her′mes, since he was the one taking the lead in speaking. 13 And the priest of Zeus, whose temple was before the city, brought bulls and garlands to the gates and was desiring to offer sacrifices with the crowds.

14 However, when the apostles Bar′na·bas and Paul heard of it, they ripped their outer garments and leaped out into the crowd, crying out 15 and saying: “Men, why are YOU doing these things? We also are humans having the same infirmities as YOU do, and are declaring the good news to YOU, for YOU to turn from these vain things to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them. 16 In the past generations he permitted all the nations to go on in their ways, 17 although, indeed, he did not leave himself without witness in that he did good, giving YOU rains from heaven and fruitful seasons, filling YOUR hearts to the full with food and good cheer.” 18 And yet by saying these things they scarcely restrained the crowds from sacrificing to them.

19 But Jews arrived from Antioch and I·co′ni·um and persuaded the crowds, and they stoned Paul and dragged him outside the city, imagining he was dead. 20 However, when the disciples surrounded him, he rose up and entered into the city. And on the next day he left with Bar′na·bas for Der′be. 21 And after declaring the good news to that city and making quite a few disciples, they returned to Lys′tra and to I·co′ni·um and to Antioch, 22 strengthening the souls of the disciples, encouraging them to remain in the faith and saying: “We must enter into the kingdom of God through many tribulations.” 23 Moreover, they appointed older men for them in each congregation and, offering prayer with fastings, they committed them to Jehovah in whom they had become believers.

24 And they went through Pi·sid′i·a and came into Pam·phyl′i·a, 25 and, after speaking the word in Perga, they went down to At·ta·li′a. 26 And from there they sailed off for Antioch, where they had been entrusted to the undeserved kindness of God for the work they had fully performed.

27 When they had arrived and had gathered the congregation together, they proceeded to relate the many things God had done by means of them, and that he had opened to the nations the door to faith. 28 So they spent not a little time with the disciples.

Acts

16 So he arrived at Der′be and also at Lys′tra. And, look! a certain disciple was there by the name of Timothy, the son of a believing Jewish woman but of a Greek father, 2 and he was well reported on by the brothers in Lys′tra and I·co′ni·um. 3 Paul expressed the desire for this man to go out with him, and he took him and circumcised him because of the Jews that were in those places, for one and all knew that his father was a Greek. 4 Now as they traveled on through the cities they would deliver to those there for observance the decrees that had been decided upon by the apostles and older men who were in Jerusalem. 5 Therefore, indeed, the congregations continued to be made firm in the faith and to increase in number from day to day.

6 Moreover, they went through Phryg′i·a and the country of Ga·la′ti·a, because they were forbidden by the holy spirit to speak the word in the district of Asia. 7 Further, when getting down to Mys′i·a they made efforts to go into Bi·thyn′i·a, but the spirit of Jesus did not permit them. 8 So they passed Mys′i·a by and came down to Tro′as. 9 And during the night a vision appeared to Paul: a certain Mac·e·do′ni·an man was standing and entreating him and saying: “Step over into Mac·e·do′ni·a and help us.” 10 Now as soon as he had seen the vision, we sought to go forth into Mac·e·do′ni·a, drawing the conclusion that God had summoned us to declare the good news to them.

11 Therefore we put out to sea from Tro′as and came with a straight run to Sam′o·thrace, but on the following day to Ne·ap′o·lis, 12 and from there to Phi·lip′pi, a colony, which is the principal city of the district of Mac·e·do′ni·a. We continued in this city, spending some days. 13 And on the sabbath day we went forth outside the gate beside a river, where we were thinking there was a place of prayer; and we sat down and began speaking to the women that had assembled. 14 And a certain woman named Lyd′i·a, a seller of purple, of the city of Thy·a·ti′ra and a worshiper of God, was listening, and Jehovah opened her heart wide to pay attention to the things being spoken by Paul. 15 Now when she and her household got baptized, she said with entreaty: “If YOU men have judged me to be faithful to Jehovah, enter into my house and stay.” And she just made us come.

16 And it happened that as we were going to the place of prayer, a certain servant girl with a spirit, a demon of divination, met us. She used to furnish her masters with much gain by practicing the art of prediction. 17 This girl kept following Paul and us and crying out with the words: “These men are slaves of the Most High God, who are publishing to YOU the way of salvation.” 18 This she kept doing for many days. Finally Paul got tired of it and turned and said to the spirit: “I order you in the name of Jesus Christ to come out of her.” And it came out that very hour.

19 Well, when her masters saw that their hope of gain had left, they laid hold of Paul and Silas and dragged them into the marketplace to the rulers, 20 and, leading them up to the civil magistrates, they said: “These men are disturbing our city very much, they being Jews, 21 and they are publishing customs that it is not lawful for us to take up or practice, seeing we are Romans.” 22 And the crowd rose up together against them; and the civil magistrates, after tearing the outer garments off them, gave the command to beat them with rods. 23 After they had inflicted many blows upon them, they threw them into prison, ordering the jailer to keep them securely. 24 Because he got such an order, he threw them into the inner prison and made their feet fast in the stocks.

25 But about the middle of the night Paul and Silas were praying and praising God with song; yes, the prisoners were hearing them. 26 Suddenly a great earthquake occurred, so that the foundations of the jail were shaken. Moreover, all the doors were instantly opened, and the bonds of all were loosened. 27 The jailer, being awakened out of sleep and seeing the prison doors were open, drew his sword and was about to do away with himself, imagining that the prisoners had escaped. 28 But Paul called out with a loud voice, saying: “Do not hurt yourself, for we are all here!” 29 So he asked for lights and leaped in and, seized with trembling, he fell down before Paul and Silas. 30 And he brought them outside and said: “Sirs, what must I do to get saved?” 31 They said: “Believe on the Lord Jesus and you will get saved, you and your household.” 32 And they spoke the word of Jehovah to him together with all those in his house. 33 And he took them along in that hour of the night and bathed their stripes; and, one and all, he and his were baptized without delay. 34 And he brought them into his house and set a table before them, and he rejoiced greatly with all his household now that he had believed God.

35 When it became day, the civil magistrates dispatched the constables to say: “Release those men.” 36 So the jailer reported their words to Paul: “The civil magistrates have dispatched men that YOU two might be released. Now, therefore, come out and go YOUR way in peace.” 37 But Paul said to them: “They flogged us publicly uncondemned, men who are Romans, and threw us into prison; and are they now throwing us out secretly? No, indeed! but let them come themselves and bring us out.” 38 So the constables reported these sayings to the civil magistrates. These grew fearful when they heard that the men were Romans. 39 Consequently they came and entreated them and, after bringing them out, they requested them to depart from the city. 40 But they came out of the prison and went to the home of Lyd′i·a, and when they saw the brothers they encouraged them and departed.

Acts

27 Now as it was decided for us to sail away to Italy, they proceeded to hand both Paul and certain other prisoners over to an army officer named Julius of the band of Au·gus′tus. 2 Going aboard a boat from Ad·ra·myt′ti·um that was about to sail to places along the coast of the district of Asia, we set sail, there being with us Ar·is·tar′chus a Mac·e·do′ni·an from Thes·sa·lo·ni′ca. 3 And the next day we landed at Si′don, and Julius treated Paul with human kindness and permitted him to go to his friends and enjoy their care.

4 And putting out to sea from there we sailed under the shelter of Cy′prus, because the winds were contrary; 5 and we navigated through the open sea along Ci·li′cia and Pam·phyl′i·a and put into port at My′ra in Ly′ci·a. 6 But there the army officer found a boat from Alexandria that was sailing for Italy, and he made us board it. 7 Then, after sailing on slowly quite a number of days and coming to Cni′dus with difficulty, because the wind did not let us get on, we sailed under the shelter of Crete at Sal·mo′ne, 8 and coasting along it with difficulty we came to a certain place called Fair Havens, near which was the city La·se′a.

9 As considerable time had passed and by now it was hazardous to navigate because even the fast of atonement day had already passed by, Paul made a recommendation, 10 saying to them: “Men, I perceive that navigation is going to be with damage and great loss not only of the cargo and the boat but also of our souls.” 11 However, the army officer went heeding the pilot and the shipowner rather than the things said by Paul. 12 Now as the harbor was inconvenient for wintering, the majority advised setting sail from there, to see if they could somehow make it to Phoenix to winter, a harbor of Crete that opens toward the northeast and toward the southeast.

13 Moreover, when the south wind blew softly, they thought they had as good as realized their purpose, and they lifted anchor and began coasting inshore along Crete. 14 After no great while, however, a tempestuous wind called Eu·ro·aq′ui·lo rushed down upon it. 15 As the boat was violently seized and was not able to keep its head against the wind, we gave way and were borne along. 16 Now we ran under the shelter of a certain small island called Cau′da, and yet we were hardly able to get possession of the skiff at the stern. 17 But after hoisting it aboard they began using helps to undergird the boat; and being in fear of running aground on the Syr′tis, they lowered the gear and thus were driven along. 18 Yet because we were being violently tossed with the tempest, the following day they began to lighten the ship; 19 and the third day, with their own hands, they threw away the tackling of the boat.

20 When, now, neither sun nor stars appeared for many days, and no little tempest was lying upon us, all hope of our being saved finally began to be cut off. 21 And when there had been a long abstinence from food, then Paul stood up in the midst of them and said: “Men, YOU certainly ought to have taken my advice and not have put out to sea from Crete and have sustained this damage and loss. 22 Still, now I recommend to YOU to be of good cheer, for not a soul of YOU will be lost, only the boat will. 23 For this night there stood near me an angel of the God to whom I belong and to whom I render sacred service, 24 saying, ‘Have no fear, Paul. You must stand before Caesar, and, look! God has freely given you all those sailing with you.’ 25 Therefore be of good cheer, men; for I believe God that it will be exactly as it has been told me. 26 However, we must be cast ashore on a certain island.”

27 Now as the fourteenth night fell and we were being tossed to and fro on the sea of A′dri·a, at midnight the sailors began to suspect they were drawing near to some land. 28 And they sounded the depth and found it twenty fathoms; so they proceeded a short distance and again made a sounding and found it fifteen fathoms. 29 And because of fearing we might be cast somewhere upon the rocks, they cast out four anchors from the stern and began wishing for it to become day. 30 But when the sailors began seeking to escape from the boat and lowered the skiff into the sea under the pretense of intending to let down anchors from the prow, 31 Paul said to the army officer and the soldiers: “Unless these men remain in the boat, YOU cannot be saved.” 32 Then the soldiers cut away the ropes of the skiff and let it fall off.

33 Now close to the approach of day Paul began to encourage one and all to take some food, saying: “Today is the fourteenth day YOU have been on the watch and YOU are continuing without food, having taken nothing for yourselves. 34 Therefore I encourage YOU to take some food, for this is in the interest of YOUR safety; for not a hair of the head of one of YOU will perish.” 35 After he said this, he also took a loaf, gave thanks to God before them all and broke it and started eating. 36 So they all became cheerful and themselves began taking some food. 37 Now, all together, we souls in the boat were two hundred and seventy-six. 38 When they had been satisfied with food, they proceeded to lighten the boat by throwing the wheat overboard into the sea.

39 Finally when it became day, they could not recognize the land but they were observing a certain bay with a beach, and on this they were determined, if they could, to beach the boat. 40 So, cutting away the anchors, they let them fall into the sea, at the same time loosing the lashings of the rudder oars and, after hoisting the foresail to the wind, they made for the beach. 41 When they lighted upon a shoal washed on each side by the sea, they ran the ship aground and the prow got stuck and stayed immovable, but the stern began to be violently broken to pieces. 42 At this it became the determination of the soldiers to kill the prisoners, that no one might swim away and escape. 43 But the army officer desired to bring Paul safely through and restrained them from their purpose. And he commanded those able to swim to cast themselves into the sea and make it to land first, 44 and the rest to do so, some upon planks and some upon certain things from the boat. And thus it came about that all were brought safely to land.

Romans

3 What, then, is the superiority of the Jew, or what is the benefit of the circumcision? 2 A great deal in every way. First of all, because they were entrusted with the sacred pronouncements of God. 3 What, then, is the case? If some did not express faith, will their lack of faith perhaps make the faithfulness of God without effect? 4 Never may that happen! But let God be found true, though every man be found a liar, even as it is written: “That you might be proved righteous in your words and might win when you are being judged.” 5 However, if our unrighteousness brings God’s righteousness to the fore, what shall we say? God is not unjust when he vents his wrath, is he? (I am speaking as a man does.) 6 Never may that happen! How, otherwise, will God judge the world?

7 Yet if by reason of my lie the truth of God has been made more prominent to his glory, why am I also yet being judged as a sinner? 8 And why not say, just as it is falsely charged to us and just as some men state that we say: “Let us do the bad things that the good things may come”? The judgment against those men is in harmony with justice.

9 What then? Are we in a better position? Not at all! For above we have made the charge that Jews as well as Greeks are all under sin; 10 just as it is written: “There is not a righteous man, not even one; 11 there is no one that has any insight, there is no one that seeks for God. 12 All men have deflected, all of them together have become worthless; there is no one that does kindness, there is not so much as one.” 13 “Their throat is an opened grave, they have used deceit with their tongues.” “Poison of asps is behind their lips.” 14 “And their mouth is full of cursing and bitter expression.” 15 “Their feet are speedy to shed blood.” 16 “Ruin and misery are in their ways, 17 and they have not known the way of peace.” 18 “There is no fear of God before their eyes.”

19 Now we know that all the things the Law says it addresses to those under the Law, so that every mouth may be stopped and all the world may become liable to God for punishment. 20 Therefore by works of law no flesh will be declared righteous before him, for by law is the accurate knowledge of sin.

21 But now apart from law God’s righteousness has been made manifest, as it is borne witness to by the Law and the Prophets; 22 yes, God’s righteousness through the faith in Jesus Christ, for all those having faith. For there is no distinction. 23 For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, 24 and it is as a free gift that they are being declared righteous by his undeserved kindness through the release by the ransom paid by Christ Jesus. 25 God set him forth as an offering for propitiation through faith in his blood. This was in order to exhibit his own righteousness, because he was forgiving the sins that occurred in the past while God was exercising forbearance; 26 so as to exhibit his own righteousness in this present season, that he might be righteous even when declaring righteous the man that has faith in Jesus.

27 Where, then, is the boasting? It is shut out. Through what law? That of works? No indeed, but through the law of faith. 28 For we reckon that a man is declared righteous by faith apart from works of law. 29 Or is he the God of the Jews only? Is he not also of people of the nations? Yes, of people of the nations also, 30 if truly God is one, who will declare circumcised people righteous as a result of faith and uncircumcised people righteous by means of their faith. 31 Do we, then, abolish law by means of our faith? Never may that happen! On the contrary, we establish law.

Romans

4 That being so, what shall we say about Abraham our forefather according to the flesh? 2 If, for instance, Abraham were declared righteous as a result of works, he would have ground for boasting; but not with God. 3 For what does the scripture say? “Abraham exercised faith in Jehovah, and it was counted to him as righteousness.” 4 Now to the man that works the pay is counted, not as an undeserved kindness, but as a debt. 5 On the other hand, to the man that does not work but puts faith in him who declares the ungodly one righteous, his faith is counted as righteousness. 6 Just as David also speaks of the happiness of the man to whom God counts righteousness apart from works: 7 “Happy are those whose lawless deeds have been pardoned and whose sins have been covered; 8 happy is the man whose sin Jehovah will by no means take into account.”

9 Does this happiness, then, come upon circumcised people or also upon uncircumcised people? For we say: “His faith was counted to Abraham as righteousness.” 10 Under what circumstances, then, was it counted? When he was in circumcision or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision. 11 And he received a sign, namely, circumcision, as a seal of the righteousness by the faith he had while in his uncircumcised state, that he might be the father of all those having faith while in uncircumcision, in order for righteousness to be counted to them; 12 and a father of circumcised offspring, not only to those who adhere to circumcision, but also to those who walk orderly in the footsteps of that faith while in the uncircumcised state which our father Abraham had.

13 For it was not through law that Abraham or his seed had the promise that he should be heir of a world, but it was through the righteousness by faith. 14 For if those who adhere to law are heirs, faith has been made useless and the promise has been abolished. 15 In reality the Law produces wrath, but where there is no law, neither is there any transgression.

16 On this account it was as a result of faith, that it might be according to undeserved kindness, in order for the promise to be sure to all his seed, not only to that which adheres to the Law, but also to that which adheres to the faith of Abraham. (He is the father of us all, 17 just as it is written: “I have appointed you a father of many nations.”) This was in the sight of the One in whom he had faith, even of God, who makes the dead alive and calls the things that are not as though they were. 18 Although beyond hope, yet based on hope he had faith, that he might become the father of many nations in accord with what had been said: “So your seed will be.” 19 And, although he did not grow weak in faith, he considered his own body, now already deadened, as he was about one hundred years old, also the deadness of the womb of Sarah. 20 But because of the promise of God he did not waver in a lack of faith, but became powerful by his faith, giving God glory 21 and being fully convinced that what he had promised he was also able to do. 22 Hence “it was counted to him as righteousness.”

23 That “it was counted to him” was written, however, not for his sake only, 24 but also for the sake of us to whom it is destined to be counted, because we believe on him who raised Jesus our Lord up from the dead. 25 He was delivered up for the sake of our trespasses and was raised up for the sake of declaring us righteous.

Romans

5 Therefore, now that we have been declared righteous as a result of faith, let us enjoy peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ, 2 through whom also we have gained our approach by faith into this undeserved kindness in which we now stand; and let us exult, based on hope of the glory of God. 3 And not only that, but let us exult while in tribulations, since we know that tribulation produces endurance; 4 endurance, in turn, an approved condition; the approved condition, in turn, hope, 5 and the hope does not lead to disappointment; because the love of God has been poured out into our hearts through the holy spirit, which was given us.

6 For, indeed, Christ, while we were yet weak, died for ungodly men at the appointed time. 7 For hardly will anyone die for a righteous man; indeed, for the good man, perhaps, someone even dares to die. 8 But God recommends his own love to us in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. 9 Much more, therefore, since we have been declared righteous now by his blood, shall we be saved through him from wrath. 10 For if, when we were enemies, we became reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, now that we have become reconciled, we shall be saved by his life. 11 And not only that, but we are also exulting in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation.

12 That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and thus death spread to all men because they had all sinned—. 13 For until the Law sin was in the world, but sin is not charged against anyone when there is no law. 14 Nevertheless, death ruled as king from Adam down to Moses, even over those who had not sinned after the likeness of the transgression by Adam, who bears a resemblance to him that was to come.

15 But it is not with the gift as it was with the trespass. For if by one man’s trespass many died, the undeserved kindness of God and his free gift with the undeserved kindness by the one man Jesus Christ abounded much more to many. 16 Also, it is not with the free gift as it was with the way things worked through the one man that sinned. For the judgment resulted from one trespass in condemnation, but the gift resulted from many trespasses in a declaration of righteousness. 17 For if by the trespass of the one man death ruled as king through that one, much more will those who receive the abundance of the undeserved kindness and of the free gift of righteousness rule as kings in life through the one person, Jesus Christ.

18 So, then, as through one trespass the result to men of all sorts was condemnation, likewise also through one act of justification the result to men of all sorts is a declaring of them righteous for life. 19 For just as through the disobedience of the one man many were constituted sinners, likewise also through the obedience of the one person many will be constituted righteous. 20 Now the Law came in beside in order that trespassing might abound. But where sin abounded, undeserved kindness abounded still more. 21 To what end? That, just as sin ruled as king with death, likewise also undeserved kindness might rule as king through righteousness with everlasting life in view through Jesus Christ our Lord.

Romans

11 I ask, then, God did not reject his people, did he? Never may that happen! For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. 2 God did not reject his people, whom he first recognized. Why, do YOU not know what the Scripture says in connection with E·li′jah, as he pleads with God against Israel? 3 “Jehovah, they have killed your prophets, they have dug up your altars, and I alone am left, and they are looking for my soul.” 4 Yet, what does the divine pronouncement say to him? “I have left seven thousand men over for myself, men who have not bent the knee to Ba′al.” 5 In this way, therefore, at the present season also a remnant has turned up according to a choosing due to undeserved kindness. 6 Now if it is by undeserved kindness, it is no longer due to works; otherwise, the undeserved kindness no longer proves to be undeserved kindness.

7 What, then? The very thing Israel is earnestly seeking he did not obtain, but the ones chosen obtained it. The rest had their sensibilities blunted; 8 just as it is written: “God has given them a spirit of deep sleep, eyes so as not to see and ears so as not to hear, down to this very day.” 9 Also, David says: “Let their table become for them a snare and a trap and a stumbling block and a retribution; 10 let their eyes become darkened so as not to see, and always bow down their back.”

11 Therefore I ask, Did they stumble so that they fell completely? Never may that happen! But by their false step there is salvation to people of the nations, to incite them to jealousy. 12 Now if their false step means riches to the world, and their decrease means riches to people of the nations, how much more will the full number of them mean it!

13 Now I speak to YOU who are people of the nations. Forasmuch as I am, in reality, an apostle to the nations, I glorify my ministry, 14 if I may by any means incite those who are my own flesh to jealousy and save some from among them. 15 For if the casting of them away means reconciliation for the world, what will the receiving of them mean but life from the dead? 16 Further, if the part taken as firstfruits is holy, the lump is also; and if the root is holy, the branches are also.

17 However, if some of the branches were broken off but you, although being a wild olive, were grafted in among them and became a sharer of the olive’s root of fatness, 18 do not be exulting over the branches. If, though, you are exulting over them, it is not you that bear the root, but the root bears you. 19 You will say, then: “Branches were broken off that I might be grafted in.” 20 All right! For their lack of faith they were broken off, but you are standing by faith. Quit having lofty ideas, but be in fear. 21 For if God did not spare the natural branches, neither will he spare you. 22 See, therefore, God’s kindness and severity. Toward those who fell there is severity, but toward you there is God’s kindness, provided you remain in his kindness; otherwise, you also will be lopped off. 23 They also, if they do not remain in their lack of faith, will be grafted in; for God is able to graft them in again. 24 For if you were cut out of the olive tree that is wild by nature and were grafted contrary to nature into the garden olive tree, how much rather will these who are natural be grafted into their own olive tree!

25 For I do not want YOU, brothers, to be ignorant of this sacred secret, in order for YOU not to be discreet in YOUR own eyes: that a dulling of sensibilities has happened in part to Israel until the full number of people of the nations has come in, 26 and in this manner all Israel will be saved. Just as it is written: “The deliverer will come out of Zion and turn away ungodly practices from Jacob. 27 And this is the covenant on my part with them, when I take their sins away.” 28 True, with reference to the good news they are enemies for YOUR sakes, but with reference to God’s choosing they are beloved for the sake of their forefathers. 29 For the gifts and the calling of God are not things he will regret. 30 For just as YOU were once disobedient to God but have now been shown mercy because of their disobedience, 31 so also these now have been disobedient with mercy resulting to YOU, that they themselves also may now be shown mercy. 32 For God has shut them all up together in disobedience, that he might show all of them mercy.

33 O the depth of God’s riches and wisdom and knowledge! How unsearchable his judgments are and past tracing out his ways are! 34 For “who has come to know Jehovah’s mind, or who has become his counselor?” 35 Or, “Who has first given to him, so that it must be repaid to him?” 36 Because from him and by him and for him are all things. To him be the glory forever. Amen.

Romans

12 Consequently I entreat YOU by the compassions of God, brothers, to present YOUR bodies a sacrifice living, holy, acceptable to God, a sacred service with YOUR power of reason. 2 And quit being fashioned after this system of things, but be transformed by making YOUR mind over, that YOU may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

3 For through the undeserved kindness given to me I tell everyone there among YOU not to think more of himself than it is necessary to think; but to think so as to have a sound mind, each one as God has distributed to him a measure of faith. 4 For just as we have in one body many members, but the members do not all have the same function, 5 so we, although many, are one body in union with Christ, but members belonging individually to one another. 6 Since, then, we have gifts differing according to the undeserved kindness given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the faith proportioned to us; 7 or a ministry, let us be at this ministry; or he that teaches, let him be at his teaching; 8 or he that exhorts, let him be at his exhortation; he that distributes, let him do it with liberality; he that presides, let him do it in real earnest; he that shows mercy, let him do it with cheerfulness.

9 Let YOUR love be without hypocrisy. Abhor what is wicked, cling to what is good. 10 In brotherly love have tender affection for one another. In showing honor to one another take the lead. 11 Do not loiter at YOUR business. Be aglow with the spirit. Slave for Jehovah. 12 Rejoice in the hope. Endure under tribulation. Persevere in prayer. 13 Share with the holy ones according to their needs. Follow the course of hospitality. 14 Keep on blessing those who persecute; be blessing and do not be cursing. 15 Rejoice with people who rejoice; weep with people who weep. 16 Be minded the same way toward others as to yourselves; do not be minding lofty things, but be led along with the lowly things. Do not become discreet in YOUR own eyes.

17 Return evil for evil to no one. Provide fine things in the sight of all men. 18 If possible, as far as it depends upon YOU, be peaceable with all men. 19 Do not avenge yourselves, beloved, but yield place to the wrath; for it is written: “Vengeance is mine; I will repay, says Jehovah.” 20 But, “if your enemy is hungry, feed him; if he is thirsty, give him something to drink; for by doing this you will heap fiery coals upon his head.” 21 Do not let yourself be conquered by the evil, but keep conquering the evil with the good.

Romans

13 Let every soul be in subjection to the superior authorities, for there is no authority except by God; the existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God. 2 Therefore he who opposes the authority has taken a stand against the arrangement of God; those who have taken a stand against it will receive judgment to themselves. 3 For those ruling are an object of fear, not to the good deed, but to the bad. Do you, then, want to have no fear of the authority? Keep doing good, and you will have praise from it; 4 for it is God’s minister to you for your good. But if you are doing what is bad, be in fear: for it is not without purpose that it bears the sword; for it is God’s minister, an avenger to express wrath upon the one practicing what is bad.

5 There is therefore compelling reason for YOU people to be in subjection, not only on account of that wrath but also on account of YOUR conscience. 6 For that is why YOU are also paying taxes; for they are God’s public servants constantly serving this very purpose. 7 Render to all their dues, to him who calls for the tax, the tax; to him who calls for the tribute, the tribute; to him who calls for fear, such fear; to him who calls for honor, such honor.

8 Do not YOU people be owing anybody a single thing, except to love one another; for he that loves his fellowman has fulfilled the law. 9 For the law code, “You must not commit adultery, You must not murder, You must not steal, You must not covet,” and whatever other commandment there is, is summed up in this word, namely, “You must love your neighbor as yourself.” 10 Love does not work evil to one’s neighbor; therefore love is the law’s fulfillment.

11 Do this, too, because YOU people know the season, that it is already the hour for YOU to awake from sleep, for now our salvation is nearer than at the time when we became believers. 12 The night is well along; the day has drawn near. Let us therefore put off the works belonging to darkness and let us put on the weapons of the light. 13 As in the daytime let us walk decently, not in revelries and drunken bouts, not in illicit intercourse and loose conduct, not in strife and jealousy. 14 But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and do not be planning ahead for the desires of the flesh.

Romans

15 We, though, who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of those not strong, and not to be pleasing ourselves. 2 Let each of us please his neighbor in what is good for his upbuilding. 3 For even the Christ did not please himself; but just as it is written: “The reproaches of those who were reproaching you have fallen upon me.” 4 For all the things that were written aforetime were written for our instruction, that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope. 5 Now may the God who supplies endurance and comfort grant YOU to have among yourselves the same mental attitude that Christ Jesus had, 6 that with one accord YOU may with one mouth glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

7 Therefore welcome one another, just as the Christ also welcomed us, with glory to God in view. 8 For I say that Christ actually became a minister of those who are circumcised in behalf of God’s truthfulness, so as to verify the promises He made to their forefathers, 9 and that the nations might glorify God for his mercy. Just as it is written: “That is why I will openly acknowledge you among the nations and to your name I will make melody.” 10 And again he says: “Be glad, YOU nations, with his people.” 11 And again: “Praise Jehovah, all YOU nations, and let all the peoples praise him.” 12 And again Isaiah says: “There will be the root of Jes′se, and there will be one arising to rule nations; on him nations will rest their hope.” 13 May the God who gives hope fill YOU with all joy and peace by YOUR believing, that YOU may abound in hope with power of holy spirit.

14 Now I myself also am persuaded about YOU, my brothers, that YOU yourselves are also full of goodness, as YOU have been filled with all knowledge, and that YOU can also admonish one another. 15 However, I am writing YOU the more outspokenly on some points, as if reminding YOU again, because of the undeserved kindness given to me from God 16 for me to be a public servant of Christ Jesus to the nations, engaging in the holy work of the good news of God, in order that the offering, namely, these nations, might prove to be acceptable, it being sanctified with holy spirit.

17 Therefore I have cause for exulting in Christ Jesus when it comes to things pertaining to God. 18 For I will not venture to tell one thing if it is not of those things which Christ worked through me for the nations to be obedient, by my word and deed, 19 with the power of signs and portents, with the power of holy spirit; so that from Jerusalem and in a circuit as far as Il·lyr′i·cum I have thoroughly preached the good news about the Christ. 20 In this way, indeed, I made it my aim not to declare the good news where Christ had already been named, in order that I might not be building on another man’s foundation; 21 but, just as it is written: “Those to whom no announcement has been made about him will see, and those who have not heard will understand.”

22 Therefore also I was many times hindered from getting to YOU. 23 But now that I no longer have untouched territory in these regions, and for some years having had a longing to get to YOU 24 whenever I am on my way to Spain, I hope, above all, when I am on the journey there, to get a look at YOU and to be escorted partway there by YOU after I have first in some measure been satisfied with YOUR company. 25 But now I am about to journey to Jerusalem to minister to the holy ones. 26 For those in Mac·e·do′ni·a and A·cha′ia have been pleased to share up their things by a contribution to the poor of the holy ones in Jerusalem. 27 True, they have been pleased to do so, and yet they were debtors to them; for if the nations have shared in their spiritual things, they also owe it to minister publicly to these with things for the fleshly body. 28 Hence after I have finished with this and have got this fruit securely to them, I shall depart by way of YOU for Spain. 29 Moreover, I know that when I do come to YOU I shall come with a full measure of blessing from Christ.

30 Now I exhort YOU, brothers, through our Lord Jesus Christ and through the love of the spirit, that YOU exert yourselves with me in prayers to God for me, 31 that I may be delivered from the unbelievers in Ju·de′a and that my ministry which is for Jerusalem may prove to be acceptable to the holy ones, 32 so that when I get to YOU with joy by God’s will I shall be refreshed together with YOU. 33 May the God who gives peace be with all of YOU. Amen.

Romans

16 I recommend to YOU Phoe′be our sister, who is a minister of the congregation that is in Cen′chre·ae, 2 that YOU may welcome her in the Lord in a way worthy of the holy ones, and that YOU may assist her in any matter where she may need YOU, for she herself also proved to be a defender of many, yes, of me myself.

3 Give my greetings to Pris′ca and Aq′ui·la my fellow workers in Christ Jesus, 4 who have risked their own necks for my soul, to whom not only I but also all the congregations of the nations render thanks; 5 and greet the congregation that is in their house. Greet my beloved E·pae′ne·tus, who is a firstfruits of Asia for Christ. 6 Greet Mary, who has performed many labors for YOU. 7 Greet An·dron′i·cus and Ju′ni·as my relatives and my fellow captives, who are men of note among the apostles and who have been in union with Christ longer than I have.

8 Give my greetings to Am·pli·a′tus my beloved in the Lord. 9 Greet Ur·ba′nus our fellow worker in Christ, and my beloved Sta′chys. 10 Greet A·pel′les, the approved one in Christ. Greet those from the household of A·ris·tob′u·lus. 11 Greet He·ro′di·on my relative. Greet those from the household of Nar·cis′sus who are in the Lord. 12 Greet Try·phae′na and Try·pho′sa, women who are working hard in the Lord. Greet Per′sis our beloved one, for she performed many labors in the Lord. 13 Greet Ru′fus the chosen one in the Lord, and his mother and mine. 14 Greet A·syn′cri·tus, Phle′gon, Her′mes, Pat′ro·bas, Her′mas, and the brothers with them. 15 Greet Phi·lol′o·gus and Julia, Ne′reus and his sister, and O·lym′pas, and all the holy ones with them. 16 Greet one another with a holy kiss. All the congregations of the Christ greet YOU.

17 Now I exhort YOU, brothers, to keep YOUR eye on those who cause divisions and occasions for stumbling contrary to the teaching that YOU have learned, and avoid them. 18 For men of that sort are slaves, not of our Lord Christ, but of their own bellies; and by smooth talk and complimentary speech they seduce the hearts of guileless ones. 19 For YOUR obedience has come to the notice of all. I therefore rejoice over YOU. But I want YOU to be wise as to what is good, but innocent as to what is evil. 20 For his part, the God who gives peace will crush Satan under YOUR feet shortly. May the undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus be with YOU.

21 Timothy my fellow worker greets YOU, and so do Lucius and Ja′son and So·sip′a·ter my relatives.

22 I, Ter′tius, who have done the writing of this letter, greet YOU in the Lord.

23 Ga′ius, my host and that of all the congregation, greets YOU. E·ras′tus the city steward greets YOU, and so does Quar′tus his brother. 24 ——

25 Now to him who can make YOU firm in accord with the good news I declare and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the sacred secret which has been kept in silence for long-lasting times 26 but has now been made manifest and has been made known through the prophetic scriptures among all the nations in accord with the command of the everlasting God to promote obedience by faith; 27 to God, wise alone, be the glory through Jesus Christ forever. Amen.

1 Corinthians

2 And so I, when I came to YOU, brothers, did not come with an extravagance of speech or of wisdom declaring the sacred secret of God to YOU. 2 For I decided not to know anything among YOU except Jesus Christ, and him impaled. 3 And I came to YOU in weakness and in fear and with much trembling; 4 and my speech and what I preached were not with persuasive words of wisdom but with a demonstration of spirit and power, 5 that YOUR faith might be, not in men’s wisdom, but in God’s power.

6 Now we speak wisdom among those who are mature, but not the wisdom of this system of things nor that of the rulers of this system of things, who are to come to nothing. 7 But we speak God’s wisdom in a sacred secret, the hidden wisdom, which God foreordained before the systems of things for our glory. 8 This wisdom not one of the rulers of this system of things came to know, for if they had known it they would not have impaled the glorious Lord. 9 But just as it is written: “Eye has not seen and ear has not heard, neither have there been conceived in the heart of man the things that God has prepared for those who love him.” 10 For it is to us God has revealed them through his spirit, for the spirit searches into all things, even the deep things of God.

11 For who among men knows the things of a man except the spirit of man that is in him? So, too, no one has come to know the things of God, except the spirit of God. 12 Now we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is from God, that we might know the things that have been kindly given us by God. 13 These things we also speak, not with words taught by human wisdom, but with those taught by the spirit, as we combine spiritual matters with spiritual words.

14 But a physical man does not receive the things of the spirit of God, for they are foolishness to him; and he cannot get to know them, because they are examined spiritually. 15 However, the spiritual man examines indeed all things, but he himself is not examined by any man. 16 For “who has come to know the mind of Jehovah, that he may instruct him?” But we do have the mind of Christ.

1 Corinthians

3 And so, brothers, I was not able to speak to YOU as to spiritual men, but as to fleshly men, as to babes in Christ. 2 I fed YOU milk, not something to eat, for YOU were not yet strong enough. In fact, neither are YOU strong enough now, 3 for YOU are yet fleshly. For whereas there are jealousy and strife among YOU, are YOU not fleshly and are YOU not walking as men do? 4 For when one says: “I belong to Paul,” but another says: “I to A·pol′los,” are YOU not simply men?

5 What, then, is A·pol′los? Yes, what is Paul? Ministers through whom YOU became believers, even as the Lord granted each one. 6 I planted, A·pol′los watered, but God kept making it grow; 7 so that neither is he that plants anything nor is he that waters, but God who makes it grow. 8 Now he that plants and he that waters are one, but each person will receive his own reward according to his own labor. 9 For we are God’s fellow workers. YOU people are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

10 According to the undeserved kindness of God that was given to me, as a wise director of works I laid a foundation, but someone else is building on it. But let each one keep watching how he is building on it. 11 For no man can lay any other foundation than what is laid, which is Jesus Christ. 12 Now if anyone builds on the foundation gold, silver, precious stones, wood materials, hay, stubble, 13 each one’s work will become manifest, for the day will show it up, because it will be revealed by means of fire; and the fire itself will prove what sort of work each one’s is. 14 If anyone’s work that he has built on it remains, he will receive a reward; 15 if anyone’s work is burned up, he will suffer loss, but he himself will be saved; yet, if so, it will be as through fire.

16 Do YOU not know that YOU people are God’s temple, and that the spirit of God dwells in YOU? 17 If anyone destroys the temple of God, God will destroy him; for the temple of God is holy, which temple YOU people are.

18 Let no one be seducing himself: If anyone among YOU thinks he is wise in this system of things, let him become a fool, that he may become wise. 19 For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God; for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.” 20 And again: “Jehovah knows that the reasonings of the wise men are futile.” 21 Hence let no one be boasting in men; for all things belong to YOU, 22 whether Paul or A·pol′los or Ce′phas or the world or life or death or things now here or things to come, all things belong to YOU; 23 in turn YOU belong to Christ; Christ, in turn, belongs to God.

1 Corinthians

6 Does anyone of YOU that has a case against the other dare to go to court before unrighteous men, and not before the holy ones? 2 Or do YOU not know that the holy ones will judge the world? And if the world is to be judged by YOU, are YOU unfit to try very trivial matters? 3 Do YOU not know that we shall judge angels? Why, then, not matters of this life? 4 If, then, YOU do have matters of this life to be tried, is it the men looked down upon in the congregation that YOU put in as judges? 5 I am speaking to move YOU to shame. Is it true that there is not one wise man among YOU that will be able to judge between his brothers, 6 but brother goes to court with brother, and that before unbelievers?

7 Really, then, it means altogether a defeat for YOU that YOU are having lawsuits with one another. Why do YOU not rather let yourselves be wronged? Why do YOU not rather let yourselves be defrauded? 8 To the contrary, YOU wrong and defraud, and YOUR brothers at that.

9 What! Do YOU not know that unrighteous persons will not inherit God’s kingdom? Do not be misled. Neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor men kept for unnatural purposes, nor men who lie with men, 10 nor thieves, nor greedy persons, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners will inherit God’s kingdom. 11 And yet that is what some of YOU were. But YOU have been washed clean, but YOU have been sanctified, but YOU have been declared righteous in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ and with the spirit of our God.

12 All things are lawful for me; but not all things are advantageous. All things are lawful for me; but I will not let myself be brought under authority by anything. 13 Foods for the belly, and the belly for foods; but God will bring both it and them to nothing. Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord is for the body. 14 But God both raised up the Lord and will raise us up out of death through his power.

15 Do YOU not know that YOUR bodies are members of Christ? Shall I, then, take the members of the Christ away and make them members of a harlot? Never may that happen! 16 What! Do YOU not know that he who is joined to a harlot is one body? For, “The two,” says he, “will be one flesh.” 17 But he who is joined to the Lord is one spirit. 18 Flee from fornication. Every other sin that a man may commit is outside his body, but he that practices fornication is sinning against his own body. 19 What! Do YOU not know that the body of YOU people is the temple of the holy spirit within YOU, which YOU have from God? Also, YOU do not belong to yourselves, 20 for YOU were bought with a price. By all means, glorify God in the body of YOU people.

1 Corinthians

9 Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord? Are not YOU my work in the Lord? 2 If I am not an apostle to others, I most certainly am to YOU, for YOU are the seal confirming my apostleship in relation to the Lord.

3 My defense to those who examine me is as follows: 4 We have authority to eat and drink, do we not? 5 We have authority to lead about a sister as a wife, even as the rest of the apostles and the Lord’s brothers and Ce′phas, do we not? 6 Or is it only Bar′na·bas and I that do not have authority to refrain from secular work? 7 Who is it that ever serves as a soldier at his own expense? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat of its fruit? Or who shepherds a flock and does not eat some of the milk of the flock?

8 Am I speaking these things by human standards? Or does not the Law also say these things? 9 For in the law of Moses it is written: “You must not muzzle a bull when it is threshing out the grain.” Is it bulls God is caring for? 10 Or is it altogether for our sakes he says it? Really for our sakes it was written, because the man who plows ought to plow in hope and the man who threshes ought to do so in hope of being a partaker.

11 If we have sown spiritual things to YOU, is it something great if we shall reap things for the flesh from YOU? 12 If other men partake of this authority over YOU, do we not much more so? Nevertheless, we have not made use of this authority, but we are bearing all things, in order that we might not offer any hindrance to the good news about the Christ. 13 Do YOU not know that the men performing sacred duties eat the things of the temple, and those constantly attending at the altar have a portion for themselves with the altar? 14 In this way, too, the Lord ordained for those proclaiming the good news to live by means of the good news.

15 But I have not made use of a single one of these provisions. Indeed, I have not written these things that it should become so in my case, for it would be finer for me to die than—no man is going to make my reason for boasting void! 16 If, now, I am declaring the good news, it is no reason for me to boast, for necessity is laid upon me. Really, woe is me if I did not declare the good news! 17 If I perform this willingly, I have a reward; but if I do it against my will, all the same I have a stewardship entrusted to me. 18 What, then, is my reward? That while declaring the good news I may furnish the good news without cost, to the end that I may not abuse my authority in the good news.

19 For, though I am free from all persons, I have made myself the slave to all, that I may gain the most persons. 20 And so to the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain Jews; to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, that I might gain those under law. 21 To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ, that I might gain those without law. 22 To the weak I became weak, that I might gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, that I might by all means save some. 23 But I do all things for the sake of the good news, that I may become a sharer of it with others.

24 Do YOU not know that the runners in a race all run, but only one receives the prize? Run in such a way that YOU may attain it. 25 Moreover, every man taking part in a contest exercises self-control in all things. Now they, of course, do it that they may get a corruptible crown, but we an incorruptible one. 26 Therefore, the way I am running is not uncertainly; the way I am directing my blows is so as not to be striking the air; 27 but I pummel my body and lead it as a slave, that, after I have preached to others, I myself should not become disapproved somehow.

1 Corinthians

16 Now concerning the collection that is for the holy ones, just as I gave orders to the congregations of Ga·la′ti·a, do that way also yourselves. 2 Every first day of the week let each of YOU at his own house set something aside in store as he may be prospering, so that when I arrive collections will not take place then. 3 But when I get there, whatever men YOU approve of by letters, these I shall send to carry YOUR kind gift to Jerusalem. 4 However, if it is fitting for me to go there also, they will go there with me.

5 But I shall come to YOU when I have gone through Mac·e·do′ni·a, for I am going through Mac·e·do′ni·a; 6 and perhaps I shall stay or even pass the winter with YOU, that YOU may conduct me partway to where I may be going. 7 For I do not want to see YOU just now on my passing through, for I hope to remain some time with YOU, if Jehovah permits. 8 But I am remaining in Eph′e·sus until the festival of Pentecost; 9 for a large door that leads to activity has been opened to me, but there are many opposers.

10 However, if Timothy arrives, see that he becomes free of fear among YOU, for he is performing the work of Jehovah, even as I am. 11 Let no one, therefore, look down upon him. Conduct him partway in peace, that he may get here to me, for I am waiting for him with the brothers.

12 Now concerning A·pol′los our brother, I entreated him very much to come to YOU with the brothers, and yet it was not his will at all to come now; but he will come when he has the opportunity.

13 Stay awake, stand firm in the faith, carry on as men, grow mighty. 14 Let all YOUR affairs take place with love.

15 Now I exhort YOU, brothers: YOU know that the household of Steph′a·nas is the firstfruits of A·cha′ia and that they set themselves to minister to the holy ones. 16 May YOU also keep submitting yourselves to persons of that kind and to everyone cooperating and laboring. 17 But I rejoice over the presence of Steph′a·nas and For·tu·na′tus and A·cha′i·cus, because they have made up for YOUR not being here. 18 For they have refreshed my spirit and YOURS. Therefore recognize men of that sort.

19 The congregations of Asia send YOU their greetings. Aq′ui·la and Pris′ca together with the congregation that is in their house greet YOU heartily in the Lord. 20 All the brothers greet YOU. Greet one another with a holy kiss.

21 Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand.

22 If anyone has no affection for the Lord, let him be accursed. O our Lord, come! 23 May the undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus be with YOU. 24 May my love be with all of YOU in union with Christ Jesus.

2 Corinthians

2 For this is what I have decided for myself, not to come to YOU again in sadness. 2 For if I make YOU sad, who indeed is there to cheer me except the one that is made sad by me? 3 And so I wrote this very thing, that, when I come, I may not get sad because of those over whom I ought to rejoice; because I have confidence in all of YOU that the joy I have is that of all of YOU. 4 For out of much tribulation and anguish of heart I wrote YOU with many tears, not that YOU might be saddened, but that YOU might know the love that I have more especially for YOU.

5 Now if anyone has caused sadness, he has saddened, not me, but all of YOU to an extent—not to be too harsh in what I say. 6 This rebuke given by the majority is sufficient for such a man, 7 so that, on the contrary now, YOU should kindly forgive and comfort him, that somehow such a man may not be swallowed up by his being overly sad. 8 Therefore I exhort YOU to confirm YOUR love for him. 9 For to this end also I write to ascertain the proof of YOU, whether YOU are obedient in all things. 10 Anything YOU kindly forgive anyone, I do too. In fact, as for me, whatever I have kindly forgiven, if I have kindly forgiven anything, it has been for YOUR sakes in Christ’s sight; 11 that we may not be overreached by Satan, for we are not ignorant of his designs.

12 Now when I arrived in Tro′as to declare the good news about the Christ, and a door was opened to me in the Lord, 13 I got no relief in my spirit on account of not finding Titus my brother, but I said good-bye to them and departed for Mac·e·do′ni·a.

14 But thanks be to God who always leads us in a triumphal procession in company with the Christ and makes the odor of the knowledge of him perceptible through us in every place! 15 For to God we are a sweet odor of Christ among those who are being saved and among those who are perishing; 16 to the latter ones an odor issuing from death to death, to the former ones an odor issuing from life to life. And who is adequately qualified for these things? 17 We are; for we are not peddlers of the word of God as many men are, but as out of sincerity, yes, as sent from God, under God’s view, in company with Christ, we are speaking.

2 Corinthians

3 Are we starting again to recommend ourselves? Or do we, perhaps, like some men, need letters of recommendation to YOU or from YOU? 2 YOU yourselves are our letter, inscribed on our hearts and known and being read by all mankind. 3 For YOU are shown to be a letter of Christ written by us as ministers, inscribed not with ink but with spirit of a living God, not on stone tablets, but on fleshly tablets, on hearts.

4 Now through the Christ we have this sort of confidence toward God. 5 Not that we of ourselves are adequately qualified to reckon anything as issuing from ourselves, but our being adequately qualified issues from God, 6 who has indeed adequately qualified us to be ministers of a new covenant, not of a written code, but of spirit; for the written code condemns to death, but the spirit makes alive.

7 Moreover, if the code which administers death and which was engraved in letters in stones came about in a glory, so that the sons of Israel could not gaze intently at the face of Moses because of the glory of his face, a glory that was to be done away with, 8 why should not the administering of the spirit be much more with glory? 9 For if the code administering condemnation was glorious, much more does the administering of righteousness abound with glory. 10 In fact, even that which has once been made glorious has been stripped of glory in this respect, because of the glory that excels it. 11 For if that which was to be done away with was brought in with glory, much more would that which remains be with glory.

12 Therefore, as we have such a hope, we are using great freeness of speech, 13 and not doing as when Moses would put a veil upon his face, that the sons of Israel might not gaze intently at the end of that which was to be done away with. 14 But their mental powers were dulled. For to this present day the same veil remains unlifted at the reading of the old covenant, because it is done away with by means of Christ. 15 In fact, down till today whenever Moses is read, a veil lies upon their hearts. 16 But when there is a turning to Jehovah, the veil is taken away. 17 Now Jehovah is the Spirit; and where the spirit of Jehovah is, there is freedom. 18 And all of us, while we with unveiled faces reflect like mirrors the glory of Jehovah, are transformed into the same image from glory to glory, exactly as done by Jehovah the Spirit.

2 Corinthians

4 That is why, since we have this ministry according to the mercy that was shown us, we do not give up; 2 but we have renounced the underhanded things of which to be ashamed, not walking with cunning, neither adulterating the word of God, but by making the truth manifest recommending ourselves to every human conscience in the sight of God. 3 If, now, the good news we declare is in fact veiled, it is veiled among those who are perishing, 4 among whom the god of this system of things has blinded the minds of the unbelievers, that the illumination of the glorious good news about the Christ, who is the image of God, might not shine through. 5 For we are preaching, not ourselves, but Christ Jesus as Lord, and ourselves as YOUR slaves for Jesus’ sake. 6 For God is he who said: “Let the light shine out of darkness,” and he has shone on our hearts to illuminate them with the glorious knowledge of God by the face of Christ.

7 However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not that out of ourselves. 8 We are pressed in every way, but not cramped beyond movement; we are perplexed, but not absolutely with no way out; 9 we are persecuted, but not left in the lurch; we are thrown down, but not destroyed. 10 Always we endure everywhere in our body the death-dealing treatment given to Jesus, that the life of Jesus may also be made manifest in our body. 11 For we who live are ever being brought face to face with death for Jesus’ sake, that the life of Jesus may also be made manifest in our mortal flesh. 12 Consequently death is at work in us, but life in YOU.

13 Now because we have the same spirit of faith as that of which it is written: “I exercised faith, therefore I spoke,” we too exercise faith and therefore we speak, 14 knowing that he who raised Jesus up will raise us up also together with Jesus and will present us together with YOU. 15 For all things are for YOUR sakes, in order that the undeserved kindness which was multiplied should abound because of the thanksgiving of many more to the glory of God.

16 Therefore we do not give up, but even if the man we are outside is wasting away, certainly the man we are inside is being renewed from day to day. 17 For though the tribulation is momentary and light, it works out for us a glory that is of more and more surpassing weight and is everlasting; 18 while we keep our eyes, not on the things seen, but on the things unseen. For the things seen are temporary, but the things unseen are everlasting.

2 Corinthians

5 For we know that if our earthly house, this tent, should be dissolved, we are to have a building from God, a house not made with hands, everlasting in the heavens. 2 For in this dwelling house we do indeed groan, earnestly desiring to put on the one for us from heaven, 3 so that, having really put it on, we shall not be found naked. 4 In fact, we who are in this tent groan, being weighed down; because we want, not to put it off, but to put on the other, that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life. 5 Now he that produced us for this very thing is God, who gave us the token of what is to come, that is, the spirit.

6 We are therefore always of good courage and know that, while we have our home in the body, we are absent from the Lord, 7 for we are walking by faith, not by sight. 8 But we are of good courage and are well pleased rather to become absent from the body and to make our home with the Lord. 9 Therefore we are also making it our aim that, whether having our home with him or being absent from him, we may be acceptable to him. 10 For we must all be made manifest before the judgment seat of the Christ, that each one may get his award for the things done through the body, according to the things he has practiced, whether it is good or vile.

11 Knowing, therefore, the fear of the Lord, we keep persuading men, but we have been made manifest to God. However, I hope that we have been made manifest also to YOUR consciences. 12 We are not again recommending ourselves to YOU, but giving YOU an inducement for boasting in respect to us, that YOU may have an answer for those who boast over the outward appearance but not over the heart. 13 For if we were out of our mind, it was for God; if we are sound in mind, it is for YOU. 14 For the love the Christ has compels us, because this is what we have judged, that one man died for all; so, then, all had died; 15 and he died for all that those who live might live no longer for themselves, but for him who died for them and was raised up.

16 Consequently from now on we know no man according to the flesh. Even if we have known Christ according to the flesh, certainly we now know him so no more. 17 Consequently if anyone is in union with Christ, he is a new creation; the old things passed away, look! new things have come into existence. 18 But all things are from God, who reconciled us to himself through Christ and gave us the ministry of the reconciliation, 19 namely, that God was by means of Christ reconciling a world to himself, not reckoning to them their trespasses, and he committed the word of the reconciliation to us.

20 We are therefore ambassadors substituting for Christ, as though God were making entreaty through us. As substitutes for Christ we beg: “Become reconciled to God.” 21 The one who did not know sin he made to be sin for us, that we might become God’s righteousness by means of him.

2 Corinthians

7 Therefore, since we have these promises, beloved ones, let us cleanse ourselves of every defilement of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in God’s fear.

2 ALLOW room for us. We have wronged no one, we have corrupted no one, we have taken advantage of no one. 3 I do not say this to condemn YOU. For I have said before that YOU are in our hearts to die and to live with us. 4 I have great freeness of speech toward YOU. I have great boasting in regard to YOU. I am filled with comfort, I am overflowing with joy in all our affliction.

5 In fact, when we arrived in Mac·e·do′ni·a, our flesh got no relief, but we continued to be afflicted in every manner—there were fights without, fears within. 6 Nevertheless God, who comforts those laid low, comforted us by the presence of Titus; 7 yet not alone by his presence, but also by the comfort with which he had been comforted over YOU, as he brought us word again of YOUR longing, YOUR mourning, YOUR zeal for me; so that I rejoiced yet more.

8 Hence even if I saddened YOU by my letter, I do not regret it. Even if I did at first regret it, (I see that that letter saddened YOU, though but for a little while,) 9 now I rejoice, not because YOU were just saddened, but because YOU were saddened into repenting; for YOU were saddened in a godly way, that YOU might suffer no damage in anything due to us. 10 For sadness in a godly way makes for repentance to salvation that is not to be regretted; but the sadness of the world produces death. 11 For, look! this very thing, YOUR being saddened in a godly way, what a great earnestness it produced in YOU, yes, clearing of yourselves, yes, indignation, yes, fear, yes, longing, yes, zeal, yes, righting of the wrong! In every respect YOU demonstrated yourselves to be chaste in this matter. 12 Certainly, although I wrote YOU, I did it, neither for the one who did the wrong, nor for the one who was wronged, but that YOUR earnestness for us might be made manifest among YOU in the sight of God. 13 That is why we have been comforted.

However, in addition to our comfort we rejoiced still more abundantly due to the joy of Titus, because his spirit has been refreshed by all of YOU. 14 For if I have made any boast to him about YOU, I have not been put to shame; but as we have spoken all things to YOU in truth, so also our boasting before Titus has proved to be true. 15 Also, his tender affections are more abundant toward YOU, while he calls to mind the obedience of all of YOU, how YOU received him with fear and trembling. 16 I rejoice that in every way I may have good courage by reason of YOU.

2 Corinthians

8 Now we let YOU know, brothers, about the undeserved kindness of God that has been bestowed upon the congregations of Mac·e·do′ni·a, 2 that during a great test under affliction their abundance of joy and their deep poverty made the riches of their generosity abound. 3 For according to their actual ability, yes, I testify, beyond their actual ability this was, 4 while they of their own accord kept begging us with much entreaty for the privilege of kindly giving and for a share in the ministry destined for the holy ones. 5 And not merely as we had hoped, but first they gave themselves to the Lord and to us through God’s will. 6 This led us to encourage Titus that, just as he had been the one to initiate it among YOU, so too he should complete this same kind giving on YOUR part. 7 Nevertheless, just as YOU are abounding in everything, in faith and word and knowledge and all earnestness and in this love of ours to YOU, may YOU also abound in this kind giving.

8 It is not in the way of commanding YOU, but in view of the earnestness of others and to make a test of the genuineness of YOUR love, that I am speaking. 9 For YOU know the undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus Christ, that though he was rich he became poor for YOUR sakes, that YOU might become rich through his poverty.

10 And in this I render an opinion: for this matter is of benefit to YOU, seeing that already a year ago YOU initiated not only the doing but also the wanting to do; 11 now, then, finish up also the doing of it, in order that, just as there was a readiness to want to do, so also there should be a finishing up of it out of what YOU have. 12 For if the readiness is there first, it is especially acceptable according to what a person has, not according to what a person does not have. 13 For I do not mean for it to be easy for others, but hard on YOU; 14 but that by means of an equalizing YOUR surplus just now might offset their deficiency, in order that their surplus might also come to offset YOUR deficiency, that an equalizing might take place. 15 Just as it is written: “The person with much did not have too much, and the person with little did not have too little.”

16 Now thanks be to God for putting the same earnestness for YOU in the heart of Titus, 17 because he has indeed responded to the encouragement, but, being very earnest, he is going forth of his own accord to YOU. 18 But we are sending along with him the brother whose praise in connection with the good news has spread through all the congregations. 19 Not only that, but he was also appointed by the congregations to be our traveling companion in connection with this kind gift to be administered by us for the glory of the Lord and in proof of our ready mind. 20 Thus we are avoiding having any man find fault with us in connection with this liberal contribution to be administered by us. 21 For we “make honest provision, not only in the sight of Jehovah, but also in the sight of men.”

22 Moreover, we are sending with them our brother whom we have often proved in many things to be earnest, but now much more earnest due to his great confidence in YOU. 23 If, though, there is any question about Titus, he is a sharer with me and a fellow worker for YOUR interests; or if about our brothers, they are apostles of congregations and a glory of Christ. 24 Therefore demonstrate to them the proof of YOUR love and of what we boasted about YOU, before the face of the congregations.

2 Corinthians

10 Now I myself, Paul, entreat YOU by the mildness and kindness of the Christ, lowly though I am in appearance among YOU, whereas when absent I am bold toward YOU. 2 Indeed I beg that, when present, I may not use boldness with that confidence with which I am counting on taking bold measures against some who appraise us as if we walked according to what we are in the flesh. 3 For though we walk in the flesh, we do not wage warfare according to what we are in the flesh. 4 For the weapons of our warfare are not fleshly, but powerful by God for overturning strongly entrenched things. 5 For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God; and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ; 6 and we are holding ourselves in readiness to inflict punishment for every disobedience, as soon as YOUR own obedience has been fully carried out.

7 YOU look at things according to their face value. If anyone trusts in himself that he belongs to Christ, let him again take this fact into account for himself, that, just as he belongs to Christ, so do we also. 8 For even if I should boast a bit too much about the authority that the Lord gave us to build YOU up and not to tear YOU down, I would not be put to shame, 9 that I may not seem to want to terrify YOU by my letters. 10 For, say they: “His letters are weighty and forceful, but his presence in person is weak and his speech contemptible.” 11 Let such a man take this into account, that what we are in our word by letters when absent, such we shall also be in action when present. 12 For we do not dare to class ourselves among some or compare ourselves with some who recommend themselves. Certainly they in measuring themselves by themselves and comparing themselves with themselves have no understanding.

13 For our part we will boast, not outside our assigned boundaries, but according to the boundary of the territory that God apportioned to us by measure, making it reach even as far as YOU. 14 Really we are not overstretching ourselves as if we did not reach to YOU, for we were the first to come even as far as YOU in declaring the good news about the Christ. 15 No, we are not boasting outside our assigned boundaries in the labors of someone else, but we entertain hope that, as YOUR faith is being increased, we may be made great among YOU with reference to our territory. Then we will abound still more, 16 to declare the good news to the countries beyond YOU, so as not to boast in someone else’s territory where things are already prepared. 17 “But he that boasts, let him boast in Jehovah.” 18 For not the one who recommends himself is approved, but the man whom Jehovah recommends.

2 Corinthians

12 I have to boast. It is not beneficial; but I shall pass on to supernatural visions and revelations of the Lord. 2 I know a man in union with Christ who, fourteen years ago—whether in the body I do not know, or out of the body I do not know; God knows—was caught away as such to the third heaven. 3 Yes, I know such a man—whether in the body or apart from the body, I do not know, God knows— 4 that he was caught away into paradise and heard unutterable words which it is not lawful for a man to speak. 5 Over such a man I will boast, but I will not boast over myself, except as respects my weaknesses. 6 For if I ever do want to boast, I shall not be unreasonable, for I shall say the truth. But I abstain, in order that no one should put to my credit more than what he sees I am or he hears from me, 7 just because of the excess of the revelations.

Therefore, that I might not feel overly exalted, there was given me a thorn in the flesh, an angel of Satan, to keep slapping me, that I might not be overly exalted. 8 In this behalf I three times entreated the Lord that it might depart from me; 9 and yet he really said to me: “My undeserved kindness is sufficient for you; for my power is being made perfect in weakness.” Most gladly, therefore, will I rather boast as respects my weaknesses, that the power of the Christ may like a tent remain over me. 10 Therefore I take pleasure in weaknesses, in insults, in cases of need, in persecutions and difficulties, for Christ. For when I am weak, then I am powerful.

11 I have become unreasonable. YOU compelled me to, for I ought to have been recommended by YOU. For I did not prove to be inferior to YOUR superfine apostles in a single thing, even if I am nothing. 12 Indeed, the signs of an apostle were produced among YOU by all endurance, and by signs and portents and powerful works. 13 For in what respect is it that YOU became less than the rest of the congregations, except that I myself did not become a burden to YOU? Kindly forgive me this wrong.

14 Look! This is the third time I am ready to come to YOU, and yet I will not become a burden. For I am seeking, not YOUR possessions, but YOU; for the children ought not to lay up for their parents, but the parents for their children. 15 For my part I will most gladly spend and be completely spent for YOUR souls. If I love YOU the more abundantly, am I to be loved the less? 16 But be that as it may, I did not burden YOU down. Nevertheless, YOU say, I was “crafty” and I caught YOU “by trickery.” 17 As for any one of those I have dispatched to YOU, I did not take advantage of YOU through him, did I? 18 I urged Titus and I dispatched the brother with him. Titus did not take advantage of YOU at all, did he? We walked in the same spirit, did we not? In the same footsteps, did we not?

19 Have YOU been thinking all this while that we have been making our defense to YOU? It is before God that we are speaking in connection with Christ. But, beloved ones, all things are for YOUR upbuilding. 20 For I am afraid that somehow, when I arrive, I may find YOU not as I could wish and I may prove to be to YOU not as YOU could wish, but, instead, there should somehow be strife, jealousy, cases of anger, contentions, backbitings, whisperings, cases of being puffed up, disorders. 21 Perhaps, when I come again, my God might humiliate me among YOU, and I might mourn over many of those who formerly sinned but have not repented over their uncleanness and fornication and loose conduct that they have practiced.

Galatians

3 O senseless Ga·la′tians, who is it that brought YOU under evil influence, YOU before whose eyes Jesus Christ was openly portrayed impaled? 2 This alone I want to learn from YOU: Did YOU receive the spirit due to works of law or due to a hearing by faith? 3 Are YOU so senseless? After starting in spirit are YOU now being completed in flesh? 4 Did YOU undergo so many sufferings to no purpose? If it really was to no purpose. 5 He, therefore, who supplies YOU the spirit and performs powerful works among YOU, does he do it owing to works of law or owing to a hearing by faith? 6 Just as Abraham “put faith in Jehovah, and it was counted to him as righteousness.”

7 Surely YOU know that those who adhere to faith are the ones who are sons of Abraham. 8 Now the Scripture, seeing in advance that God would declare people of the nations righteous due to faith, declared the good news beforehand to Abraham, namely: “By means of you all the nations will be blessed.” 9 Consequently those who adhere to faith are being blessed together with faithful Abraham.

10 For all those who depend upon works of law are under a curse; for it is written: “Cursed is every one that does not continue in all the things written in the scroll of the Law in order to do them.” 11 Moreover, that by law no one is declared righteous with God is evident, because “the righteous one will live by reason of faith.” 12 Now the Law does not adhere to faith, but “he that does them shall live by means of them.” 13 Christ by purchase released us from the curse of the Law by becoming a curse instead of us, because it is written: “Accursed is every man hanged upon a stake.” 14 The purpose was that the blessing of Abraham might come to be by means of Jesus Christ for the nations, that we might receive the promised spirit through our faith.

15 Brothers, I speak with a human illustration: A validated covenant, though it is a man’s, no one sets aside or attaches additions to it. 16 Now the promises were spoken to Abraham and to his seed. It says, not: “And to seeds,” as in the case of many such, but as in the case of one: “And to your seed,” who is Christ. 17 Further, I say this: As to the covenant previously validated by God, the Law that has come into being four hundred and thirty years later does not invalidate it, so as to abolish the promise. 18 For if the inheritance is due to law, it is no longer due to promise; whereas God has kindly given it to Abraham through a promise.

19 Why, then, the Law? It was added to make transgressions manifest, until the seed should arrive to whom the promise had been made; and it was transmitted through angels by the hand of a mediator. 20 Now there is no mediator where only one person is concerned, but God is only one. 21 Is the Law, therefore, against the promises of God? May that never happen! For if a law had been given that was able to give life, righteousness would actually have been by means of law. 22 But the Scripture delivered up all things together to the custody of sin, that the promise resulting from faith toward Jesus Christ might be given to those exercising faith.

23 However, before the faith arrived, we were being guarded under law, being delivered up together into custody, looking to the faith that was destined to be revealed. 24 Consequently the Law has become our tutor leading to Christ, that we might be declared righteous due to faith. 25 But now that the faith has arrived, we are no longer under a tutor.

26 YOU are all, in fact, sons of God through YOUR faith in Christ Jesus. 27 For all of YOU who were baptized into Christ have put on Christ. 28 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither slave nor freeman, there is neither male nor female; for YOU are all one person in union with Christ Jesus. 29 Moreover, if YOU belong to Christ, YOU are really Abraham’s seed, heirs with reference to a promise.

Galatians

4 Now I say that as long as the heir is a babe he does not differ at all from a slave, lord of all things though he is, 2 but he is under men in charge and under stewards until the day his father appointed beforehand. 3 Likewise we also, when we were babes, continued enslaved by the elementary things belonging to the world. 4 But when the full limit of the time arrived, God sent forth his Son, who came to be out of a woman and who came to be under law, 5 that he might release by purchase those under law, that we, in turn, might receive the adoption as sons.

6 Now because YOU are sons, God has sent forth the spirit of his Son into our hearts and it cries out: “Abba, Father!” 7 So, then, you are no longer a slave but a son; and if a son, also an heir through God.

8 Nevertheless, when YOU did not know God, then it was that YOU slaved for those who by nature are not gods. 9 But now that YOU have come to know God, or rather now that YOU have come to be known by God, how is it that YOU are turning back again to the weak and beggarly elementary things and want to slave for them over again? 10 YOU are scrupulously observing days and months and seasons and years. 11 I fear for YOU, that somehow I have toiled to no purpose respecting YOU.

12 Brothers, I beg YOU, Become as I am, because I used to be also as YOU are. YOU did me no wrong. 13 But YOU know that it was through a sickness of my flesh I declared the good news to YOU the first time. 14 And what was a trial to YOU in my flesh, YOU did not treat with contempt or spit at in disgust; but YOU received me like an angel of God, like Christ Jesus. 15 Where, then, is that happiness YOU had? For I bear YOU witness that, if it had been possible, YOU would have gouged out YOUR eyes and given them to me. 16 Well, then, have I become YOUR enemy because I tell YOU the truth? 17 They zealously seek YOU, not in a fine way, but they want to shut YOU off from me, that YOU may zealously seek them. 18 However, it is fine for YOU to be zealously sought for in a fine cause at all times, and not only when I am present with YOU, 19 my little children, with whom I am again in childbirth pains until Christ is formed in YOU. 20 But I could wish to be present with YOU just now and to speak in a different way, because I am perplexed over YOU.

21 Tell me, YOU who want to be under law, Do YOU not hear the Law? 22 For example, it is written that Abraham acquired two sons, one by the servant girl and one by the free woman; 23 but the one by the servant girl was actually born in the manner of flesh, the other by the free woman through a promise. 24 These things stand as a symbolic drama; for these women mean two covenants, the one from Mount Si′nai, which brings forth children for slavery, and which is Ha′gar. 25 Now this Ha′gar means Si′nai, a mountain in Arabia, and she corresponds with the Jerusalem today, for she is in slavery with her children. 26 But the Jerusalem above is free, and she is our mother.

27 For it is written: “Be glad, you barren woman who does not give birth; break out and cry aloud, you woman who does not have childbirth pains; for the children of the desolate woman are more numerous than those of her who has the husband.” 28 Now we, brothers, are children belonging to the promise the same as Isaac was. 29 But just as then the one born in the manner of flesh began persecuting the one born in the manner of spirit, so also now. 30 Nevertheless, what does the Scripture say? “Drive out the servant girl and her son, for by no means shall the son of the servant girl be an heir with the son of the free woman.” 31 Wherefore, brothers, we are children, not of a servant girl, but of the free woman.

Galatians

5 For such freedom Christ set us free. Therefore stand fast, and do not let yourselves be confined again in a yoke of slavery.

2 See! I, Paul, am telling YOU that if YOU become circumcised, Christ will be of no benefit to YOU. 3 Moreover, I bear witness again to every man getting circumcised that he is under obligation to perform the whole Law. 4 YOU are parted from Christ, whoever YOU are that try to be declared righteous by means of law; YOU have fallen away from his undeserved kindness. 5 For our part we by spirit are eagerly waiting for the hoped-for righteousness as a result of faith. 6 For as regards Christ Jesus neither circumcision is of any value nor is uncircumcision, but faith operating through love is.

7 YOU were running well. Who hindered YOU from keeping on obeying the truth? 8 This sort of persuasion is not from the One calling YOU. 9 A little leaven ferments the whole lump. 10 I am confident about YOU who are in union with the Lord that YOU will not come to think otherwise; but the one who is causing YOU trouble will bear his judgment, no matter who he may be. 11 As for me, brothers, if I am still preaching circumcision, why am I still being persecuted? Then, indeed, the stumbling block of the torture stake has been abolished. 12 I wish the men who are trying to overturn YOU would even get themselves emasculated.

13 YOU were, of course, called for freedom, brothers; only do not use this freedom as an inducement for the flesh, but through love slave for one another. 14 For the entire Law stands fulfilled in one saying, namely: “You must love your neighbor as yourself.” 15 If, though, YOU keep on biting and devouring one another, look out that YOU do not get annihilated by one another.

16 But I say, Keep walking by spirit and YOU will carry out no fleshly desire at all. 17 For the flesh is against the spirit in its desire, and the spirit against the flesh; for these are opposed to each other, so that the very things that YOU would like to do YOU do not do. 18 Furthermore, if YOU are being led by spirit, YOU are not under law.

19 Now the works of the flesh are manifest, and they are fornication, uncleanness, loose conduct, 20 idolatry, practice of spiritism, enmities, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, contentions, divisions, sects, 21 envies, drunken bouts, revelries, and things like these. As to these things I am forewarning YOU, the same way as I did forewarn YOU, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s kingdom.

22 On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, long-suffering, kindness, goodness, faith, 23 mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law. 24 Moreover, those who belong to Christ Jesus impaled the flesh together with its passions and desires.

25 If we are living by spirit, let us go on walking orderly also by spirit. 26 Let us not become egotistical, stirring up competition with one another, envying one another.

Galatians

6 Brothers, even though a man takes some false step before he is aware of it, YOU who have spiritual qualifications try to readjust such a man in a spirit of mildness, as you each keep an eye on yourself, for fear you also may be tempted. 2 Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and thus fulfill the law of the Christ. 3 For if anyone thinks he is something when he is nothing, he is deceiving his own mind. 4 But let each one prove what his own work is, and then he will have cause for exultation in regard to himself alone, and not in comparison with the other person. 5 For each one will carry his own load.

6 Moreover, let anyone who is being orally taught the word share in all good things with the one who gives such oral teaching.

7 Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a man is sowing, this he will also reap; 8 because he who is sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but he who is sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit. 9 So let us not give up in doing what is fine, for in due season we shall reap if we do not tire out. 10 Really, then, as long as we have time favorable for it, let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

11 SEE with what large letters I have written YOU with my own hand.

12 All those who want to make a pleasing appearance in the flesh are the ones that try to compel YOU to get circumcised, only that they may not be persecuted for the torture stake of the Christ, Jesus. 13 For not even do those who are getting circumcised keep the Law themselves, but they want YOU to be circumcised that they may have cause for boasting in YOUR flesh. 14 Never may it occur that I should boast, except in the torture stake of our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom the world has been impaled to me and I to the world. 15 For neither is circumcision anything nor is uncircumcision, but a new creation is something. 16 And all those who will walk orderly by this rule of conduct, upon them be peace and mercy, even upon the Israel of God.

17 Henceforth let no one be making trouble for me, for I am carrying on my body the brand marks of a slave of Jesus.

18 The undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus Christ be with the spirit YOU show, brothers. Amen.

Ephesians

4 I, therefore, the prisoner in the Lord, entreat YOU to walk worthily of the calling with which YOU were called, 2 with complete lowliness of mind and mildness, with long-suffering, putting up with one another in love, 3 earnestly endeavoring to observe the oneness of the spirit in the uniting bond of peace. 4 One body there is, and one spirit, even as YOU were called in the one hope to which YOU were called; 5 one Lord, one faith, one baptism; 6 one God and Father of all persons, who is over all and through all and in all.

7 Now to each one of us undeserved kindness was given according to how the Christ measured out the free gift. 8 Wherefore he says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.” 9 Now the expression “he ascended,” what does it mean but that he also descended into the lower regions, that is, the earth? 10 The very one that descended is also the one that ascended far above all the heavens, that he might give fullness to all things.

11 And he gave some as apostles, some as prophets, some as evangelizers, some as shepherds and teachers, 12 with a view to the readjustment of the holy ones, for ministerial work, for the building up of the body of the Christ, 13 until we all attain to the oneness in the faith and in the accurate knowledge of the Son of God, to a full-grown man, to the measure of stature that belongs to the fullness of the Christ; 14 in order that we should no longer be babes, tossed about as by waves and carried hither and thither by every wind of teaching by means of the trickery of men, by means of cunning in contriving error. 15 But speaking the truth, let us by love grow up in all things into him who is the head, Christ. 16 From him all the body, by being harmoniously joined together and being made to cooperate through every joint that gives what is needed, according to the functioning of each respective member in due measure, makes for the growth of the body for the building up of itself in love.

17 This, therefore, I say and bear witness to in the Lord, that YOU no longer go on walking just as the nations also walk in the unprofitableness of their minds, 18 while they are in darkness mentally, and alienated from the life that belongs to God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the insensibility of their hearts. 19 Having come to be past all moral sense, they gave themselves over to loose conduct to work uncleanness of every sort with greediness.

20 But YOU did not learn the Christ to be so, 21 provided, indeed, that YOU heard him and were taught by means of him, just as truth is in Jesus, 22 that YOU should put away the old personality which conforms to YOUR former course of conduct and which is being corrupted according to his deceptive desires; 23 but that YOU should be made new in the force actuating YOUR mind, 24 and should put on the new personality which was created according to God’s will in true righteousness and loyalty.

25 Wherefore, now that YOU have put away falsehood, speak truth each one of YOU with his neighbor, because we are members belonging to one another. 26 Be wrathful, and yet do not sin; let the sun not set with YOU in a provoked state, 27 neither allow place for the Devil. 28 Let the stealer steal no more, but rather let him do hard work, doing with his hands what is good work, that he may have something to distribute to someone in need. 29 Let a rotten saying not proceed out of YOUR mouth, but whatever saying is good for building up as the need may be, that it may impart what is favorable to the hearers. 30 Also, do not be grieving God’s holy spirit, with which YOU have been sealed for a day of releasing by ransom.

31 Let all malicious bitterness and anger and wrath and screaming and abusive speech be taken away from YOU along with all badness. 32 But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave YOU.

Colossians

2 For I want YOU to realize how great a struggle I am having in behalf of YOU and of those at La·o·di·ce′a and of all those who have not seen my face in the flesh, 2 that their hearts may be comforted, that they may be harmoniously joined together in love and with a view to all the riches of the full assurance of their understanding, with a view to an accurate knowledge of the sacred secret of God, namely, Christ. 3 Carefully concealed in him are all the treasures of wisdom and of knowledge. 4 This I am saying that no man may delude YOU with persuasive arguments. 5 For though I am absent in the flesh, all the same I am with YOU in the spirit, rejoicing and beholding YOUR good order and the firmness of YOUR faith toward Christ.

6 Therefore, as YOU have accepted Christ Jesus the Lord, go on walking in union with him, 7 rooted and being built up in him and being stabilized in the faith, just as YOU were taught, overflowing with faith in thanksgiving.

8 Look out: perhaps there may be someone who will carry YOU off as his prey through the philosophy and empty deception according to the tradition of men, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ; 9 because it is in him that all the fullness of the divine quality dwells bodily. 10 And so YOU are possessed of a fullness by means of him, who is the head of all government and authority. 11 By relationship with him YOU were also circumcised with a circumcision performed without hands by the stripping off the body of the flesh, by the circumcision that belongs to the Christ, 12 for YOU were buried with him in his baptism, and by relationship with him YOU were also raised up together through YOUR faith in the operation of God, who raised him up from the dead.

13 Furthermore, though YOU were dead in YOUR trespasses and in the uncircumcised state of YOUR flesh, God made YOU alive together with him. He kindly forgave us all our trespasses 14 and blotted out the handwritten document against us, which consisted of decrees and which was in opposition to us; and He has taken it out of the way by nailing it to the torture stake. 15 Stripping the governments and the authorities bare, he exhibited them in open public as conquered, leading them in a triumphal procession by means of it.

16 Therefore let no man judge YOU in eating and drinking or in respect of a festival or of an observance of the new moon or of a sabbath; 17 for those things are a shadow of the things to come, but the reality belongs to the Christ. 18 Let no man deprive YOU of the prize who takes delight in a mock humility and a form of worship of the angels, “taking his stand on” the things he has seen, puffed up without proper cause by his fleshly frame of mind, 19 whereas he is not holding fast to the head, to the one from whom all the body, being supplied and harmoniously joined together by means of its joints and ligaments, goes on growing with the growth that God gives.

20 If YOU died together with Christ toward the elementary things of the world, why do YOU, as if living in the world, further subject yourselves to the decrees: 21 “Do not handle, nor taste, nor touch,” 22 respecting things that are all destined to destruction by being used up, in accordance with the commands and teachings of men? 23 Those very things are, indeed, possessed of an appearance of wisdom in a self-imposed form of worship and mock humility, a severe treatment of the body; but they are of no value in combating the satisfying of the flesh.

Colossians

3 If, however, YOU were raised up with the Christ, go on seeking the things above, where the Christ is seated at the right hand of God. 2 Keep YOUR minds fixed on the things above, not on the things upon the earth. 3 For YOU died, and YOUR life has been hidden with the Christ in union with God. 4 When the Christ, our life, is made manifest, then YOU also will be made manifest with him in glory.

5 Deaden, therefore, YOUR body members that are upon the earth as respects fornication, uncleanness, sexual appetite, hurtful desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry. 6 On account of those things the wrath of God is coming. 7 In those very things YOU, too, once walked when YOU used to live in them. 8 But now really put them all away from YOU, wrath, anger, badness, abusive speech, and obscene talk out of YOUR mouth. 9 Do not be lying to one another. Strip off the old personality with its practices, 10 and clothe yourselves with the new personality, which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it, 11 where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, foreigner, Scyth′i·an, slave, freeman, but Christ is all things and in all.

12 Accordingly, as God’s chosen ones, holy and loved, clothe yourselves with the tender affections of compassion, kindness, lowliness of mind, mildness, and long-suffering. 13 Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Even as Jehovah freely forgave YOU, so do YOU also. 14 But, besides all these things, clothe yourselves with love, for it is a perfect bond of union.

15 Also, let the peace of the Christ control in YOUR hearts, for YOU were, in fact, called to it in one body. And show yourselves thankful. 16 Let the word of the Christ reside in YOU richly in all wisdom. Keep on teaching and admonishing one another with psalms, praises to God, spiritual songs with graciousness, singing in YOUR hearts to Jehovah. 17 And whatever it is that YOU do in word or in work, do everything in the name of the Lord Jesus, thanking God the Father through him.

18 YOU wives, be in subjection to YOUR husbands, as it is becoming in the Lord. 19 YOU husbands, keep on loving YOUR wives and do not be bitterly angry with them. 20 YOU children, be obedient to YOUR parents in everything, for this is well-pleasing in the Lord. 21 YOU fathers, do not be exasperating YOUR children, so that they do not become downhearted. 22 YOU slaves, be obedient in everything to those who are YOUR masters in a fleshly sense, not with acts of eye-service, as men pleasers, but with sincerity of heart, with fear of Jehovah. 23 Whatever YOU are doing, work at it whole-souled as to Jehovah, and not to men, 24 for YOU know that it is from Jehovah YOU will receive the due reward of the inheritance. SLAVE for the Master, Christ. 25 Certainly the one that is doing wrong will receive back what he wrongly did, and there is no partiality.

Colossians

4 YOU masters, keep dealing out what is righteous and what is fair to YOUR slaves, knowing that YOU also have a Master in heaven.

2 Be persevering in prayer, remaining awake in it with thanksgiving, 3 at the same time praying also for us, that God may open a door of utterance to us, to speak the sacred secret about the Christ, for which, in fact, I am in prison bonds; 4 so that I shall make it manifest as I ought to speak.

5 Go on walking in wisdom toward those on the outside, buying out the opportune time for yourselves. 6 Let YOUR utterance be always with graciousness, seasoned with salt, so as to know how YOU ought to give an answer to each one.

7 All my affairs Tych′i·cus, my beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will make known to YOU. 8 For the very purpose of YOUR knowing the things having to do with us and that he may comfort YOUR hearts, I am sending him to YOU 9 along with O·nes′i·mus, my faithful and beloved brother, who is from among YOU. All the things here they will make known to YOU.

10 Ar·is·tar′chus my fellow captive sends YOU his greetings, and so does Mark the cousin of Bar′na·bas, (concerning whom YOU received commands to welcome him if ever he comes to YOU,) 11 and Jesus who is called Justus, these being of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the kingdom of God, and these very ones have become a strengthening aid to me. 12 Ep′a·phras, who is from among YOU, a slave of Christ Jesus, sends YOU his greetings, always exerting himself in YOUR behalf in his prayers, that YOU may finally stand complete and with firm conviction in all the will of God. 13 I indeed bear him witness that he puts himself to great effort in behalf of YOU and of those at La·o·di·ce′a and of those at Hi·e·rap′o·lis.

14 Luke the beloved physician sends YOU his greetings, and so does De′mas. 15 Give my greetings to the brothers at La·o·di·ce′a and to Nym′pha and to the congregation at her house. 16 And when this letter has been read among YOU, arrange that it also be read in the congregation of the La·o·di·ce′ans and that YOU also read the one from La·o·di·ce′a. 17 Also, tell Ar·chip′pus: “Keep watching the ministry which you accepted in the Lord, that you fulfill it.”

18 Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand. Continue bearing my prison bonds in mind. The undeserved kindness be with YOU.

1 Thessalonians

2 To be sure, YOU yourselves know, brothers, how our visit to YOU has not been without results, 2 but how, after we had first suffered and been insolently treated (just as YOU know) in Phi·lip′pi, we mustered up boldness by means of our God to speak to YOU the good news of God with a great deal of struggling. 3 For the exhortation we give does not arise from error or from uncleanness or with deceit, 4 but, just as we have been proved by God as fit to be entrusted with the good news, so we speak, as pleasing, not men, but God, who makes proof of our hearts.

5 In fact, at no time have we turned up either with flattering speech, (just as YOU know) or with a false front for covetousness, God is witness! 6 Neither have we been seeking glory from men, no, either from YOU or from others, though we could be an expensive burden as apostles of Christ. 7 To the contrary, we became gentle in the midst of YOU, as when a nursing mother cherishes her own children. 8 So, having a tender affection for YOU, we were well pleased to impart to YOU, not only the good news of God, but also our own souls, because YOU became beloved to us.

9 Certainly YOU bear in mind, brothers, our labor and toil. It was with working night and day, so as not to put an expensive burden upon any one of YOU, that we preached the good news of God to YOU. 10 YOU are witnesses, God is also, how loyal and righteous and unblamable we proved to be to YOU believers. 11 In harmony with that YOU well know how, as a father does his children, we kept exhorting each one of YOU, and consoling and bearing witness to YOU, 12 to the end that YOU should go on walking worthily of God who is calling YOU to his kingdom and glory.

13 Indeed, that is why we also thank God incessantly, because when YOU received God’s word, which YOU heard from us, YOU accepted it, not as the word of men, but, just as it truthfully is, as the word of God, which is also at work in YOU believers. 14 For YOU became imitators, brothers, of the congregations of God that are in Ju·de′a in union with Christ Jesus, because YOU also began suffering at the hands of YOUR own countrymen the same things as they also are suffering at the hands of the Jews, 15 who killed even the Lord Jesus and the prophets and persecuted us. Furthermore, they are not pleasing God, but are against the interests of all men, 16 as they try to hinder us from speaking to people of the nations that these might be saved, with the result that they always fill up the measure of their sins. But his wrath has at length come upon them.

17 As for ourselves, brothers, when we were bereaved of YOU for but a short time, in person, not in heart, we endeavored far more than is usual to see YOUR faces with great desire. 18 For this reason we wanted to come to YOU, yes, I Paul, both once and a second time, but Satan cut across our path. 19 For what is our hope or joy or crown of exultation—why, is it not in fact YOU?—before our Lord Jesus at his presence? 20 YOU certainly are our glory and joy.

2 Thessalonians

2 However, brothers, respecting the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ and our being gathered together to him, we request of YOU 2 not to be quickly shaken from YOUR reason nor to be excited either through an inspired expression or through a verbal message or through a letter as though from us, to the effect that the day of Jehovah is here.

3 Let no one seduce YOU in any manner, because it will not come unless the apostasy comes first and the man of lawlessness gets revealed, the son of destruction. 4 He is set in opposition and lifts himself up over everyone who is called “god” or an object of reverence, so that he sits down in the temple of The God, publicly showing himself to be a god. 5 Do YOU not remember that, while I was yet with YOU, I used to tell YOU these things?

6 And so now YOU know the thing that acts as a restraint, with a view to his being revealed in his own due time. 7 True, the mystery of this lawlessness is already at work; but only till he who is right now acting as a restraint gets to be out of the way. 8 Then, indeed, the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will do away with by the spirit of his mouth and bring to nothing by the manifestation of his presence. 9 But the lawless one’s presence is according to the operation of Satan with every powerful work and lying signs and portents 10 and with every unrighteous deception for those who are perishing, as a retribution because they did not accept the love of the truth that they might be saved. 11 So that is why God lets an operation of error go to them, that they may get to believing the lie, 12 in order that they all may be judged because they did not believe the truth but took pleasure in unrighteousness.

13 However, we are obligated to thank God always for YOU, brothers loved by Jehovah, because God selected YOU from the beginning for salvation by sanctifying YOU with spirit and by YOUR faith in the truth. 14 To this very destiny he called YOU through the good news we declare, for the purpose of acquiring the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. 15 So, then, brothers, stand firm and maintain YOUR hold on the traditions that YOU were taught, whether it was through a verbal message or through a letter of ours. 16 Moreover, may our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father, who loved us and gave everlasting comfort and good hope by means of undeserved kindness, 17 comfort YOUR hearts and make YOU firm in every good deed and word.

1 Timothy

5 Do not severely criticize an older man. To the contrary, entreat him as a father, younger men as brothers, 2 older women as mothers, younger women as sisters with all chasteness.

3 Honor widows that are actually widows. 4 But if any widow has children or grandchildren, let these learn first to practice godly devotion in their own household and to keep paying a due compensation to their parents and grandparents, for this is acceptable in God’s sight. 5 Now the woman who is actually a widow and left destitute has put her hope in God and persists in supplications and prayers night and day. 6 But the one that goes in for sensual gratification is dead though she is living. 7 So keep on giving these commands, that they may be irreprehensible. 8 Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

9 Let a widow be put on the list who has become not less than sixty years old, a wife of one husband, 10 having a witness borne to her for fine works, if she reared children, if she entertained strangers, if she washed the feet of holy ones, if she relieved those in tribulation, if she diligently followed every good work.

11 On the other hand, turn down younger widows, for when their sexual impulses have come between them and the Christ, they want to marry, 12 having a judgment because they have disregarded their first expression of faith. 13 At the same time they also learn to be unoccupied, gadding about to the houses; yes, not only unoccupied, but also gossipers and meddlers in other people’s affairs, talking of things they ought not. 14 Therefore I desire the younger widows to marry, to bear children, to manage a household, to give no inducement to the opposer to revile. 15 Already, in fact, some have been turned aside to follow Satan. 16 If any believing woman has widows, let her relieve them, and let the congregation not be under the burden. Then it can relieve those who are actually widows.

17 Let the older men who preside in a fine way be reckoned worthy of double honor, especially those who work hard in speaking and teaching. 18 For the scripture says: “You must not muzzle a bull when it threshes out the grain”; also: “The workman is worthy of his wages.” 19 Do not admit an accusation against an older man, except only on the evidence of two or three witnesses. 20 Reprove before all onlookers persons who practice sin, that the rest also may have fear. 21 I solemnly charge you before God and Christ Jesus and the chosen angels to keep these things without prejudgment, doing nothing according to a biased leaning.

22 Never lay your hands hastily upon any man; neither be a sharer in the sins of others; preserve yourself chaste.

23 Do not drink water any longer, but use a little wine for the sake of your stomach and your frequent cases of sickness.

24 The sins of some men are publicly manifest, leading directly to judgment, but as for other men their sins also become manifest later. 25 In the same way also the fine works are publicly manifest and those that are otherwise cannot be kept hid.

1 Timothy

6 Let as many as are slaves under a yoke keep on considering their owners worthy of full honor, that the name of God and the teaching may never be spoken of injuriously. 2 Moreover, let those having believing owners not look down on them, because they are brothers. On the contrary, let them the more readily be slaves, because those receiving the benefit of their good service are believers and beloved.

Keep on teaching these things and giving these exhortations. 3 If any man teaches other doctrine and does not assent to healthful words, those of our Lord Jesus Christ, nor to the teaching that accords with godly devotion, 4 he is puffed up with pride, not understanding anything, but being mentally diseased over questionings and debates about words. From these things spring envy, strife, abusive speeches, wicked suspicions, 5 violent disputes about trifles on the part of men corrupted in mind and despoiled of the truth, thinking that godly devotion is a means of gain. 6 To be sure, it is a means of great gain, this godly devotion along with self-sufficiency. 7 For we have brought nothing into the world, and neither can we carry anything out. 8 So, having sustenance and covering, we shall be content with these things.

9 However, those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and hurtful desires, which plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

11 However, you, O man of God, flee from these things. But pursue righteousness, godly devotion, faith, love, endurance, mildness of temper. 12 Fight the fine fight of the faith, get a firm hold on the everlasting life for which you were called and you offered the fine public declaration in front of many witnesses.

13 In the sight of God, who preserves all things alive, and of Christ Jesus, who as a witness made the fine public declaration before Pontius Pilate, I give you orders 14 that you observe the commandment in a spotless and irreprehensible way until the manifestation of our Lord Jesus Christ. 15 This manifestation the happy and only Potentate will show in its own appointed times, he the King of those who rule as kings and Lord of those who rule as lords, 16 the one alone having immortality, who dwells in unapproachable light, whom not one of men has seen or can see. To him be honor and might everlasting. Amen.

17 Give orders to those who are rich in the present system of things not to be high-minded, and to rest their hope, not on uncertain riches, but on God, who furnishes us all things richly for our enjoyment; 18 to work at good, to be rich in fine works, to be liberal, ready to share, 19 safely treasuring up for themselves a fine foundation for the future, in order that they may get a firm hold on the real life.

20 O Timothy, guard what is laid up in trust with you, turning away from the empty speeches that violate what is holy and from the contradictions of the falsely called “knowledge.” 21 For making a show of such knowledge some have deviated from the faith.

May the undeserved kindness be with YOU people.

The Second to Timothy

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will according to the promise of the life that is in union with Christ Jesus, 2 to Timothy, a beloved child:

May there be undeserved kindness, mercy, peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.

3 I am grateful to God, to whom I am rendering sacred service as my forefathers did and with a clean conscience, that I never leave off remembering you in my supplications, night and day 4 longing to see you, as I remember your tears, that I may get filled with joy. 5 For I recollect the faith which is in you without any hypocrisy, and which dwelt first in your grandmother Lo′is and your mother Eu′nice, but which I am confident is also in you.

6 For this very cause I remind you to stir up like a fire the gift of God which is in you through the laying of my hands upon you. 7 For God gave us not a spirit of cowardice, but that of power and of love and of soundness of mind. 8 Therefore do not become ashamed of the witness about our Lord, neither of me a prisoner for his sake, but take your part in suffering evil for the good news according to the power of God. 9 He saved us and called us with a holy calling, not by reason of our works, but by reason of his own purpose and undeserved kindness. This was given us in connection with Christ Jesus before times long lasting, 10 but now it has been made clearly evident through the manifestation of our Savior, Christ Jesus, who has abolished death but has shed light upon life and incorruption through the good news, 11 for which I was appointed a preacher and apostle and teacher.

12 For this very cause I am also suffering these things, but I am not ashamed. For I know the one whom I have believed, and I am confident he is able to guard what I have laid up in trust with him until that day. 13 Keep holding the pattern of healthful words that you heard from me with the faith and love that are in connection with Christ Jesus. 14 This fine trust guard through the holy spirit which is dwelling in us.

15 You know this, that all the men in the district of Asia have turned away from me. Phy·gel′us and Her·mog′e·nes are of that number. 16 May the Lord grant mercy to the household of On·e·siph′o·rus, because he often brought me refreshment, and he did not become ashamed of my chains. 17 On the contrary, when he happened to be in Rome, he diligently looked for me and found me. 18 May the Lord grant him to find mercy from Jehovah in that day. And all the services he rendered in Eph′e·sus you know well enough.

Hebrews

6 For this reason, now that we have left the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity, not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works, and faith toward God, 2 the teaching on baptisms and the laying on of the hands, the resurrection of the dead and everlasting judgment. 3 And this we will do, if God indeed permits.

4 For it is impossible as regards those who have once for all been enlightened, and who have tasted the heavenly free gift, and who have become partakers of holy spirit, 5 and who have tasted the fine word of God and powers of the coming system of things, 6 but who have fallen away, to revive them again to repentance, because they impale the Son of God afresh for themselves and expose him to public shame. 7 For example, the ground that drinks in the rain which often comes upon it, and that then brings forth vegetation suitable to those for whom it is also cultivated, receives in return a blessing from God. 8 But if it produces thorns and thistles, it is rejected and is near to being cursed; and it ends up with being burned.

9 However, in YOUR case, beloved ones, we are convinced of better things and things accompanied with salvation, although we are speaking in this way. 10 For God is not unrighteous so as to forget YOUR work and the love YOU showed for his name, in that YOU have ministered to the holy ones and continue ministering. 11 But we desire each one of YOU to show the same industriousness so as to have the full assurance of the hope down to the end, 12 in order that YOU may not become sluggish, but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

13 For when God made his promise to Abraham, since he could not swear by anyone greater, he swore by himself, 14 saying: “Assuredly in blessing I will bless you, and in multiplying I will multiply you.” 15 And thus after Abraham had shown patience, he obtained this promise. 16 For men swear by the one greater, and their oath is the end of every dispute, as it is a legal guarantee to them. 17 In this manner God, when he purposed to demonstrate more abundantly to the heirs of the promise the unchangeableness of his counsel, stepped in with an oath, 18 in order that, through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie, we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to lay hold on the hope set before us. 19 This hope we have as an anchor for the soul, both sure and firm, and it enters in within the curtain, 20 where a forerunner has entered in our behalf, Jesus, who has become a high priest according to the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek forever.

Hebrews

11 Faith is the assured expectation of things hoped for, the evident demonstration of realities though not beheld. 2 For by means of this the men of old times had witness borne to them.

3 By faith we perceive that the systems of things were put in order by God’s word, so that what is beheld has come to be out of things that do not appear.

4 By faith Abel offered God a sacrifice of greater worth than Cain, through which faith he had witness borne to him that he was righteous, God bearing witness respecting his gifts; and through it he, although he died, yet speaks.

5 By faith E′noch was transferred so as not to see death, and he was nowhere to be found because God had transferred him; for before his transference he had the witness that he had pleased God well. 6 Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please him well, for he that approaches God must believe that he is and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

7 By faith Noah, after being given divine warning of things not yet beheld, showed godly fear and constructed an ark for the saving of his household; and through this faith he condemned the world, and he became an heir of the righteousness that is according to faith.

8 By faith Abraham, when he was called, obeyed in going out into a place he was destined to receive as an inheritance; and he went out, although not knowing where he was going. 9 By faith he resided as an alien in the land of the promise as in a foreign land, and dwelt in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the very same promise. 10 For he was awaiting the city having real foundations, the builder and maker of which city is God.

11 By faith also Sarah herself received power to conceive seed, even when she was past the age limit, since she esteemed him faithful who had promised. 12 Hence also from one man, and him as good as dead, there were born children just as the stars of heaven for multitude and as the sands that are by the seaside, innumerable.

13 In faith all these died, although they did not get the fulfillment of the promises, but they saw them afar off and welcomed them and publicly declared that they were strangers and temporary residents in the land. 14 For those who say such things give evidence that they are earnestly seeking a place of their own. 15 And yet, if they had indeed kept remembering that place from which they had gone forth, they would have had opportunity to return. 16 But now they are reaching out for a better place, that is, one belonging to heaven. Hence God is not ashamed of them, to be called upon as their God, for he has made a city ready for them.

17 By faith Abraham, when he was tested, as good as offered up Isaac, and the man that had gladly received the promises attempted to offer up his only-begotten son, 18 although it had been said to him: “What will be called ‘your seed’ will be through Isaac.” 19 But he reckoned that God was able to raise him up even from the dead; and from there he did receive him also in an illustrative way.

20 By faith also Isaac blessed Jacob and E′sau concerning things to come.

21 By faith Jacob, when about to die, blessed each of the sons of Joseph and worshiped leaning upon the top of his staff.

22 By faith Joseph, nearing his end, made mention of the exodus of the sons of Israel; and he gave a command concerning his bones.

23 By faith Moses was hid for three months by his parents after his birth, because they saw the young child was beautiful and they did not fear the order of the king. 24 By faith Moses, when grown up, refused to be called the son of the daughter of Phar′aoh, 25 choosing to be ill-treated with the people of God rather than to have the temporary enjoyment of sin, 26 because he esteemed the reproach of the Christ as riches greater than the treasures of Egypt; for he looked intently toward the payment of the reward. 27 By faith he left Egypt, but not fearing the anger of the king, for he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible. 28 By faith he had celebrated the passover and the splashing of the blood, that the destroyer might not touch their firstborn ones.

29 By faith they passed through the Red Sea as on dry land, but on venturing out upon it the Egyptians were swallowed up.

30 By faith the walls of Jer′i·cho fell down after they had been encircled for seven days. 31 By faith Ra′hab the harlot did not perish with those who acted disobediently, because she received the spies in a peaceable way.

32 And what more shall I say? For the time will fail me if I go on to relate about Gid′e·on, Ba′rak, Samson, Jeph′thah, David as well as Samuel and the other prophets, 33 who through faith defeated kingdoms in conflict, effected righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions, 34 stayed the force of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, from a weak state were made powerful, became valiant in war, routed the armies of foreigners. 35 Women received their dead by resurrection; but other men were tortured because they would not accept release by some ransom, in order that they might attain a better resurrection. 36 Yes, others received their trial by mockings and scourgings, indeed, more than that, by bonds and prisons. 37 They were stoned, they were tried, they were sawn asunder, they died by slaughter with the sword, they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins, while they were in want, in tribulation, under ill-treatment; 38 and the world was not worthy of them. They wandered about in deserts and mountains and caves and dens of the earth.

39 And yet all these, although they had witness borne to them through their faith, did not get the fulfillment of the promise, 40 as God foresaw something better for us, in order that they might not be made perfect apart from us.

Hebrews

12 So, then, because we have so great a cloud of witnesses surrounding us, let us also put off every weight and the sin that easily entangles us, and let us run with endurance the race that is set before us, 2 as we look intently at the Chief Agent and Perfecter of our faith, Jesus. For the joy that was set before him he endured a torture stake, despising shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God. 3 Indeed, consider closely the one who has endured such contrary talk by sinners against their own interests, that YOU may not get tired and give out in YOUR souls.

4 In carrying on YOUR contest against that sin YOU have never yet resisted as far as blood, 5 but YOU have entirely forgotten the exhortation which addresses YOU as sons: “My son, do not belittle the discipline from Jehovah, neither give out when you are corrected by him; 6 for whom Jehovah loves he disciplines; in fact, he scourges every one whom he receives as a son.”

7 It is for discipline YOU are enduring. God is dealing with YOU as with sons. For what son is he that a father does not discipline? 8 But if YOU are without the discipline of which all have become partakers, YOU are really illegitimate children, and not sons. 9 Furthermore, we used to have fathers who were of our flesh to discipline us, and we used to give them respect. Shall we not much more subject ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life and live? 10 For they for a few days used to discipline us according to what seemed good to them, but he does so for our profit that we may partake of his holiness. 11 True, no discipline seems for the present to be joyous, but grievous; yet afterward to those who have been trained by it it yields peaceable fruit, namely, righteousness.

12 Hence straighten up the hands that hang down and the enfeebled knees, 13 and keep making straight paths for YOUR feet, that what is lame may not be put out of joint, but rather that it may be healed. 14 Pursue peace with all people, and the sanctification without which no man will see the Lord, 15 carefully watching that no one may be deprived of the undeserved kindness of God; that no poisonous root may spring up and cause trouble and that many may not be defiled by it; 16 that there may be no fornicator nor anyone not appreciating sacred things, like E′sau, who in exchange for one meal gave away his rights as firstborn. 17 For YOU know that afterward also when he wanted to inherit the blessing he was rejected, for, although he earnestly sought a change of mind with tears, he found no place for it.

18 For YOU have not approached that which can be felt and which has been set aflame with fire, and a dark cloud and thick darkness and a tempest, 19 and the blare of a trumpet and the voice of words; on hearing which voice the people implored that no word should be added to them. 20 For the command was not bearable to them: “And if a beast touches the mountain, it must be stoned.” 21 Also, the display was so fearsome that Moses said: “I am fearful and trembling.” 22 But YOU have approached a Mount Zion and a city of the living God, heavenly Jerusalem, and myriads of angels, 23 in general assembly, and the congregation of the firstborn who have been enrolled in the heavens, and God the Judge of all, and the spiritual lives of righteous ones who have been made perfect, 24 and Jesus the mediator of a new covenant, and the blood of sprinkling, which speaks in a better way than Abel’s blood.

25 See that YOU do not beg off from him who is speaking. For if they did not escape who begged off from him who was giving divine warning upon earth, much more shall we not if we turn away from him who speaks from the heavens. 26 At that time his voice shook the earth, but now he has promised, saying: “Yet once more I will set in commotion not only the earth but also the heaven.” 27 Now the expression “Yet once more” signifies the removal of the things being shaken as things that have been made, in order that the things not being shaken may remain. 28 Wherefore, seeing that we are to receive a kingdom that cannot be shaken, let us continue to have undeserved kindness, through which we may acceptably render God sacred service with godly fear and awe. 29 For our God is also a consuming fire.

Hebrews

13 Let YOUR brotherly love continue. 2 Do not forget hospitality, for through it some, unknown to themselves, entertained angels. 3 Keep in mind those in prison bonds as though YOU have been bound with them, and those being ill-treated, since YOU yourselves also are still in a body. 4 Let marriage be honorable among all, and the marriage bed be without defilement, for God will judge fornicators and adulterers. 5 Let YOUR manner of life be free of the love of money, while YOU are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will by no means leave you nor by any means forsake you.” 6 So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

7 Remember those who are taking the lead among YOU, who have spoken the word of God to YOU, and as YOU contemplate how their conduct turns out imitate their faith.

8 Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and today, and forever.

9 Do not be carried away with various and strange teachings; for it is fine for the heart to be given firmness by undeserved kindness, not by eatables, by which those who occupy themselves with them have not been benefited.

10 We have an altar from which those who do sacred service at the tent have no authority to eat. 11 For the bodies of those animals whose blood is taken into the holy place by the high priest for sin are burned up outside the camp. 12 Hence Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people with his own blood, suffered outside the gate. 13 Let us, then, go forth to him outside the camp, bearing the reproach he bore, 14 for we do not have here a city that continues, but we are earnestly seeking the one to come. 15 Through him let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise, that is, the fruit of lips which make public declaration to his name. 16 Moreover, do not forget the doing of good and the sharing of things with others, for with such sacrifices God is well pleased.

17 Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among YOU and be submissive, for they are keeping watch over YOUR souls as those who will render an account; that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to YOU.

18 Carry on prayer for us, for we trust we have an honest conscience, as we wish to conduct ourselves honestly in all things. 19 But I exhort YOU more especially to do this, that I may be restored to YOU the sooner.

20 Now may the God of peace, who brought up from the dead the great shepherd of the sheep with the blood of an everlasting covenant, our Lord Jesus, 21 equip YOU with every good thing to do his will, performing in us through Jesus Christ that which is well-pleasing in his sight; to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.

22 Now I exhort YOU, brothers, to bear with this word of encouragement, for I have, indeed, composed a letter to YOU in few words. 23 Take note that our brother Timothy has been released, with whom, if he comes quite soon, I shall see YOU.

24 Give my greetings to all those who are taking the lead among YOU and to all the holy ones. Those in Italy send YOU their greetings.

25 The undeserved kindness be with all of YOU.

James

2 My brothers, YOU are not holding the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, our glory, with acts of favoritism, are YOU? 2 For, if a man with gold rings on his fingers and in splendid clothing enters into a gathering of YOU, but a poor man in filthy clothing also enters, 3 yet YOU look with favor upon the one wearing the splendid clothing and say: “You take this seat here in a fine place,” and YOU say to the poor one: “You keep standing,” or: “Take that seat there under my footstool,” 4 YOU have class distinctions among yourselves and YOU have become judges rendering wicked decisions, is that not so?

5 Listen, my beloved brothers. God chose the ones who are poor respecting the world to be rich in faith and heirs of the kingdom, which he promised to those who love him, did he not? 6 YOU, though, have dishonored the poor man. The rich oppress YOU, and they drag YOU before law courts, do they not? 7 They blaspheme the fine name by which YOU were called, do they not? 8 If, now, YOU practice carrying out the kingly law according to the scripture: “You must love your neighbor as yourself,” YOU are doing quite well. 9 But if YOU continue showing favoritism, YOU are working a sin, for YOU are reproved by the law as transgressors.

10 For whoever observes all the Law but makes a false step in one point, he has become an offender against them all. 11 For he who said: “You must not commit adultery,” said also: “You must not murder.” If, now, you do not commit adultery but you do murder, you have become a transgressor of law. 12 Keep on speaking in such a way and keep on doing in such a way as those do who are going to be judged by the law of a free people. 13 For the one that does not practice mercy will have his judgment without mercy. Mercy exults triumphantly over judgment.

14 Of what benefit is it, my brothers, if a certain one says he has faith but he does not have works? That faith cannot save him, can it? 15 If a brother or a sister is in a naked state and lacking the food sufficient for the day, 16 yet a certain one of YOU says to them: “Go in peace, keep warm and well fed,” but YOU do not give them the necessities for their body, of what benefit is it? 17 Thus, too, faith, if it does not have works, is dead in itself.

18 Nevertheless, a certain one will say: “You have faith, and I have works. Show me your faith apart from the works, and I shall show you my faith by my works.” 19 You believe there is one God, do you? You are doing quite well. And yet the demons believe and shudder. 20 But do you care to know, O empty man, that faith apart from works is inactive? 21 Was not Abraham our father declared righteous by works after he had offered up Isaac his son upon the altar? 22 You behold that his faith worked along with his works and by his works his faith was perfected, 23 and the scripture was fulfilled which says: “Abraham put faith in Jehovah, and it was counted to him as righteousness,” and he came to be called “Jehovah’s friend.”

24 YOU see that a man is to be declared righteous by works, and not by faith alone. 25 In the same manner was not also Ra′hab the harlot declared righteous by works, after she had received the messengers hospitably and sent them out by another way? 26 Indeed, as the body without spirit is dead, so also faith without works is dead.